<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fedora | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/fedora/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-26T10:31:39+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Last 3 Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello folks, this is my book list for the past 3 months. It ranges from
tech and start-up related to Japanese and kid stories. Here's my quick review.</p>

<h2>Lean UX</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449311652/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1449311652&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=JNQIKHJJXU3KJ33H">Lean UX: Applying Lean Principles to Improve User Experience</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1449311652" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
is the second book I read on the subject after first reading
<a href="/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/">UX for Lean Startups</a>.</p>

<p>It is published before <em>UX for Lean Startups</em> and is much more about principles than
any practical methods. Honestly I'm not sure if I took any real value out of it.
Maybe if I had read these two books in reverse order it would have been better.</p>

<h2>The Hacienda - How Not to Run a Club</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00DEKLESK/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00DEKLESK&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FOMGYFQW4BHGPPOL">The Hacienda: How Not to Run a Club</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00DEKLESK" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Peter Hook is one of my favorites. It covers a great deal of music and clubland history,
depicts crazy parties and describes the adventure of owning one of the most
popular nightclubs in the world. All of that while struggling to make a buck and
pouring countless pounds into a black hole.</p>

<p>The irony is The Hacienda became a legendary place only after it had closed down
and later on being demolished.</p>

<p>A must read for anyone who is considering business in the entertainment industry
or wants to read a piece of history. My favorite quote of the book:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Years after, Tony Wilson found himself sitting opposite Madonna at dinner.</p></p><p><p>‘I eventually plucked up the courage to look across the table to Madonna and ask,<br/>“Are you aware that the first place you appeared outside of New York was our club in Manchester?”</p></p><p><p>‘She gave me an ice-cold stare and said, “My memory seems to have wiped that.”’</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Simple Science Experiments</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0713428945/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0713428945&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=HU6TVCNR6DG67EFG">Simple Science Experiments</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0713428945" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Hans Jürgen Press is a very old book listing 200 experiments which you can
do at home using household materials. It is great for teaching basic science
to children. The book is very popular and is available in many languages
and editions - just search for it.</p>

<p>I used to have this as a kid and was able to purchase the 1987 Bulgarian edition
at an antique bookstore in Varna two months ago.</p>

<h2>Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</h2>

<p>Decided to experiment a little bit and found
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0140317201/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0140317201&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FDHOPXQCZPMYCAA2">Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0140317201" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />.
It's a child's book telling the story of two kids whose fathers are rival
robbers. The book is an easy read (2-3 hrs before bed time) with stories
of magic woods, dwarfs and scary creatures mixed with human emotions
and the good vs. bad theme.</p>

<h2>Japanese Short Stories</h2>

<p>I've managed to find a 1973 compilation of Japanese short stories
translated into Bulgarian. Also one of my favorite books.</p>

<p>If I'm not mistaken these are classic
Japanese authors, nothing modern or cutting edge. Most of the action happens
during the early 1900s as far as I can tell.
What impresses me most is the detailed description of nature and
surrounding details in all of the stories.</p>

<h2>The Singularity Is Near</h2>

<p>I've also started
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143037889/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143037889&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=BKMQ47NQEXNTDDRR">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0143037889" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Ray Kurzweil.</p>

<p>It's a bit hard to read because the book is full of so many technical details
about genetics, nanotechnology, robotics and AI.</p>

<p>Ray depicts a bright future where humans will transcend our biological
limitations and essentially become pure intelligence. Definitely a good
read and I will tell you more about it when I finish it.</p>

<hr />

<p>What have you been reading since January ? I'd love to see your book list
or connect on
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/16191345-alexander-todorov">Goodreads</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenSource.com article - 10 steps to migrate your closed software to open source]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/06/opensource-dot-com-article-10-steps-to-migrate-your-closed-software-to-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T16:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/06/opensource-dot-com-article-10-steps-to-migrate-your-closed-software-to-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Difio is a Django based application that keeps track of packages and tells you when they change.<br/>Difio was created as closed software, then I decided to migrate it to open source ....</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Read more at
<a href="http://opensource.com/business/14/5/10-steps-migrate-closed-to-open-source">OpenSource.com</a></p>

<p>Btw I'm wondering if Telerik will share their experience opening up
the core of their Kendo UI framework on the
<a href="http://www.telerik.com/campaigns/kendo-ui-build-free">webinar tomorrow</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Screen Magnifier and Smart Phone! Has Anyone Used It ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/04/screen-magnifier-and-smart-phone-has-anyone-used-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-04T10:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/04/screen-magnifier-and-smart-phone-has-anyone-used-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you remember I was going to
<a href="/blog/2013/08/01/laptop-vs-smartphone-part-one/">replace my laptop for a smartphone</a>.
There's the issue with a desk working environment and one solution is to buy an external
display. The other one is to use a
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=screen%20magnifier&linkCode=ur2&rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Ascreen%20magnifier&sprefix=screen%20magnifie%2Ccomputers%2C277&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Daps&linkId=KGF6F22QDNBRWAMP">screen magnifier</a><img src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
as shown on the picture
(source <a href="http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/2PC-Enlarger-Magnifier-for-Mobile-Screen-3-Times-for-All-Mobiles-Senior-2014-New-/181398272903?pt=UK_Holders_Mounts&amp;hash=item2a3c2dfb87">eBay</a>).</p>

<p><img src="/images/mobile_screen_magnifier.jpg" title="Mobile Screen Magnifier" alt="Mobile Screen Magnifier" /></p>

<p>Does anyone have experience with these? Ultimately it should be possible to use
any 3x Fresnel lens magnifier and make your 5" phone display into a 15" laptop size one.
The magnifiers used for reading,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001TLJXJ8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B001TLJXJ8&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=HS6EY4BELCHBZ6HC">this one</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B001TLJXJ8" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
are cheap and portable but don't look very well around the edges.</p>

<p>If anyone has such a device at hand I'd love to see if this works for you or not.
Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spoiler: How to Open Source Existing Proprietary Code in 10 Steps]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/23/how-to-open-source-existing-proprietary-code-in-10-steps/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T22:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/23/how-to-open-source-existing-proprietary-code-in-10-steps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We've heard about companies opening up their proprietary software products,
this is hardly news nowadays. But have you wondered what it is like to migrate
production software from closed to open source? I would like to share my own
experience about going open source as seen from behind the keyboard.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dif.io">Difio</a> was recently open sourced and the steps to go through
were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Simplify - remove everything that can be deleted</li>
<li>Create self contained modules aka re-organize the file structure</li>
<li>Separate internal from external modules</li>
<li>Refactor the existing code</li>
<li>Select license and update copyright</li>
<li>Update 3rd party dependencies to latest versions and add requirements.txt</li>
<li>Add README and verbose settings example</li>
<li>Split difio/ into its own git repository</li>
<li>Test stand alone deployments on fresh environment</li>
<li>Announce</li>
</ul>


<p>Do you want to know more? Use the comments and tell me what exactly!
I'm writing a longer version of this article so stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Positive Biological Effects of Open Source on Humans]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/08/positive-biological-effects-of-open-source-on-humans/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T16:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/08/positive-biological-effects-of-open-source-on-humans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I watched a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ReRcHdeUG9Y">talk by Simon Sinek</a>
about leadership. He talks about Endorphins, Dopamine, Serotonin and Oxytocin
and how they make us feel and act a particular way. Then I though - maybe that's why working
in the open source field always felt great and natural to me. Maybe we humans
are programmed to follow the open source way!</p>

<p>This article scratches the surface where body chemistry and open source intersect.
I hope it will help both volunteers and community managers get an insight of the
driving forces in our bodies, how they relate to the open source world and promt
further exploration. By seeking to better understand the positive effects and avoid
the negative ones we can become better contributors and leaders which ultimately
helps our communities.</p>

<h2>Endorphins</h2>

<p>Endorphins stand for endurance. Their job is to mask physical pain and it has been
suggested to have evolutionary roots based on the theory that they helped with the
survival of early humans. Athletes experience so called Runner's high.</p>

<p>In the open source world one may work on a feature or task for hours and hours
without feeling exhausted. The task itself keeps you going and excited.
This is endorphins going through your brain.</p>

<p>In software one may experience an endorphin rush during public release days for example. For large
projects like Fedora the release process includes many steps and may take several hours.
During all that time the release engineer is usually available regardless of their native
time zone.</p>

<p>Effects of endorphins could potentially increase the likelihood of injury or extreme exhaustion,
as pain sensation could be more easily ignored. Work and rest cycles need to be properly balanced.</p>

<h2>Dopamine</h2>

<p>This is the feeling when we achieve our goals or found something we were looking for.
Dopamine helps us get things done! This is why we're told to write down our goals and then
cross them off. It makes people more productive.</p>

<p>Getting dopamine through open source is very easy - all you need to do is fix a bug,
then another one, and another one, and another one ... After every task you complete the body
gets a small dopamine fix. "Release early, release often ..." and you get your fix :).</p>

<p>Dopamine however is highly addictive and destructive if unbalanced. It has the same negative
effects as any other addiction - alcohol, drugs, etc. Be aware of that and don't fall for the
performance trap.</p>

<p>Endorphins and Dopamine are so called selfish chemicals. You can get them without external help.
The next two are the social chemicals.</p>

<h2>Serotonin</h2>

<p>It is responsible for feelings of pride and status and assessing social rank.
Serotonin is produced when you are recognized for achievements by the open source community
or credited by somebody (e.g. Johnny Bravo mentioned a great idea on IRC today).</p>

<p>As a contributor one may work on items which will help you get recognition but ultimately this
is not for you to decide. However practice shows that credit and recognition are relatively easy
to get in the open source world provided one has contributed to make the project and the
community better in some sort.</p>

<p>In software this is being granted commit rights to a repository, being in the top spot of
some metrics, having your blog read by other members or simply people asking for help or
what you think about some topic.</p>

<p>Serotonin is considered the leadership chemical. As one becomes a leader recognized by the
community there's a catch - the more your status goes up the more work you have to
do. The more people recognize you as the leader the more they expect you to sacrifice yourself
in case it all goes Pete Tong. If you are not ready to step up find a more suitable place in
the community instead.</p>

<h2>Oxytocin</h2>

<p>Oxytocin is responsible for feelings of love, trust and friendship. It makes us feel safe.
It is also very good for the body because it makes us healthier, boosts our
immune system, increases ability to solve problems and increases creativity.</p>

<p>One way to get Oxytocin is by physical touch - e.g. a hand shake. This is probably one of
the reasons beer gatherings are so popular among open source developers.
Working digitally we need a way to
reinforce human bonds in our communities. Knowing the person on the other end of the wire
ultimately makes us feel safer. If you are in open source just go for that conference or a
local beer bash you wanted to go - it is good for you (but don't get drunk).</p>

<p>Another way to get Oxytocin is by performing or witnessing acts of human generosity.
This comes natural in open source world where people give up their free time and energy to work towards
a shared goal. Just by working in an open source environment you get all that goodness for you.</p>

<p>The best thing about Oxytocin is that it is not addictive and slowly builds up in the body.
The bad side is that it takes a while to build up. This is why you have to stay a little longer
in open source before it starts feeling safe and welcoming.</p>

<h2>Cortisol</h2>

<p>The last chemical Simon talks about is Cortisol. It is bad, very bad. It will crash your body.
Cortisol means stress. It is designed to keep humans (and animals) alive by hyper tuning
our senses in case of danger. Trouble is you are not supposed to have it in your body for
long periods of time because it shuts down non-essential systems to deliver that extra energy.</p>

<p>Luckily most open source projects are not stressful and I think can be considered a safe place
to work in. In the end one can always shift to another role or move to another project if it
becomes too pressing.</p>

<p>By committing
to help another member or perform service to the community our bodies get all the good
stuff and beat the negative. Service to a community is exactly what open source does!
See, humans are programmed to live and work the open source way!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
