<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fedora | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/fedora/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-27T23:11:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SNAKE is no Longer Needed to Run Installation Tests in Beaker]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/07/18/snake-is-no-longer-needed-to-run-installation-tests-in-beaker/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-18T23:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/07/18/snake-is-no-longer-needed-to-run-installation-tests-in-beaker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a quick status update for one of the pieces of
<a href="/blog/2013/11/19/open-source-quality-assurance-infrastructure-for-fedora-qa/">Fedora QA infrastructure</a>
and mostly a self-note.</p>

<p>Previously to control the kickstart configuration used during installation in Beaker one
had to either modify the job XML in Beaker or use SNAKE (<code>bkr workflow-snake</code>) to render
a kickstart configuration from a Python template.</p>

<p>SNAKE presented challenges when deploying and using
<a href="https://beaker.fedoraproject.org">beaker.fedoraproject.org</a> and is
virtually unmaintained.</p>

<p>I present the new <code>bkr workflow-installer-test</code> which uses Jinja2 templates to
generate a kickstart configuration when provisioning the system. This is already
available in beaker-client-0.17.1.</p>

<p>The templates make use of all Jinja2 features (as far as I can tell) so you can create
very complex ones. You can even include snippets from one template into another if required.
The standard context that is passed to the template is:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>DISTRO</strong> - if specified, the distro name</li>
<li><strong>FAMILY</strong> - as returned by Beaker server, e.g. <em>RedHatEnterpriseLinux6</em></li>
<li><strong>OS_MAJOR</strong> and <strong>OS_MINOR</strong> - also taken from Beaker server. e.g. OS_MAJOR=6 and OS_MINOR=5 for RHEL 6.5</li>
<li><strong>VARIANT</strong> - if specified</li>
<li><strong>ARCH</strong> - CPU architecture like x86_64</li>
<li>any parameters passed to the test job with <code>--taskparam</code>. They are processed last and can override previous values.</li>
</ul>


<p>Installation related tests at <a href="https://bitbucket.org/fedoraqa/fedora-beaker-tests">fedora-beaker-tests</a>
have been updated with a <code>ks.cfg.tmpl</code> templates to use with this new workflow.</p>

<p>This workflow also has the ability to return boot arguments for the installer if needed.
If any, they should be defined in a {% block kernel_options %}{% endblock %}
block inside the template. A simpler variant is to define a comment line that stars with
<em>## kernel_options:</em></p>

<p>There are still a few issues which need to be fixed before beaker.fedoraproject.org
can be used by the general public though. I will be writing another post about that
so stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Last 3 Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello folks, this is my book list for the past 3 months. It ranges from
tech and start-up related to Japanese and kid stories. Here's my quick review.</p>

<h2>Lean UX</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449311652/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1449311652&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=JNQIKHJJXU3KJ33H">Lean UX: Applying Lean Principles to Improve User Experience</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1449311652" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
is the second book I read on the subject after first reading
<a href="/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/">UX for Lean Startups</a>.</p>

<p>It is published before <em>UX for Lean Startups</em> and is much more about principles than
any practical methods. Honestly I'm not sure if I took any real value out of it.
Maybe if I had read these two books in reverse order it would have been better.</p>

<h2>The Hacienda - How Not to Run a Club</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00DEKLESK/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00DEKLESK&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FOMGYFQW4BHGPPOL">The Hacienda: How Not to Run a Club</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00DEKLESK" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Peter Hook is one of my favorites. It covers a great deal of music and clubland history,
depicts crazy parties and describes the adventure of owning one of the most
popular nightclubs in the world. All of that while struggling to make a buck and
pouring countless pounds into a black hole.</p>

<p>The irony is The Hacienda became a legendary place only after it had closed down
and later on being demolished.</p>

<p>A must read for anyone who is considering business in the entertainment industry
or wants to read a piece of history. My favorite quote of the book:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Years after, Tony Wilson found himself sitting opposite Madonna at dinner.</p></p><p><p>‘I eventually plucked up the courage to look across the table to Madonna and ask,<br/>“Are you aware that the first place you appeared outside of New York was our club in Manchester?”</p></p><p><p>‘She gave me an ice-cold stare and said, “My memory seems to have wiped that.”’</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Simple Science Experiments</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0713428945/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0713428945&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=HU6TVCNR6DG67EFG">Simple Science Experiments</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0713428945" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Hans Jürgen Press is a very old book listing 200 experiments which you can
do at home using household materials. It is great for teaching basic science
to children. The book is very popular and is available in many languages
and editions - just search for it.</p>

<p>I used to have this as a kid and was able to purchase the 1987 Bulgarian edition
at an antique bookstore in Varna two months ago.</p>

<h2>Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</h2>

<p>Decided to experiment a little bit and found
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0140317201/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0140317201&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FDHOPXQCZPMYCAA2">Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0140317201" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />.
It's a child's book telling the story of two kids whose fathers are rival
robbers. The book is an easy read (2-3 hrs before bed time) with stories
of magic woods, dwarfs and scary creatures mixed with human emotions
and the good vs. bad theme.</p>

<h2>Japanese Short Stories</h2>

<p>I've managed to find a 1973 compilation of Japanese short stories
translated into Bulgarian. Also one of my favorite books.</p>

<p>If I'm not mistaken these are classic
Japanese authors, nothing modern or cutting edge. Most of the action happens
during the early 1900s as far as I can tell.
What impresses me most is the detailed description of nature and
surrounding details in all of the stories.</p>

<h2>The Singularity Is Near</h2>

<p>I've also started
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143037889/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143037889&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=BKMQ47NQEXNTDDRR">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0143037889" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Ray Kurzweil.</p>

<p>It's a bit hard to read because the book is full of so many technical details
about genetics, nanotechnology, robotics and AI.</p>

<p>Ray depicts a bright future where humans will transcend our biological
limitations and essentially become pure intelligence. Definitely a good
read and I will tell you more about it when I finish it.</p>

<hr />

<p>What have you been reading since January ? I'd love to see your book list
or connect on
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/16191345-alexander-todorov">Goodreads</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenSource.com article - 10 steps to migrate your closed software to open source]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/06/opensource-dot-com-article-10-steps-to-migrate-your-closed-software-to-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T16:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/06/opensource-dot-com-article-10-steps-to-migrate-your-closed-software-to-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Difio is a Django based application that keeps track of packages and tells you when they change.<br/>Difio was created as closed software, then I decided to migrate it to open source ....</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Read more at
<a href="http://opensource.com/business/14/5/10-steps-migrate-closed-to-open-source">OpenSource.com</a></p>

<p>Btw I'm wondering if Telerik will share their experience opening up
the core of their Kendo UI framework on the
<a href="http://www.telerik.com/campaigns/kendo-ui-build-free">webinar tomorrow</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Screen Magnifier and Smart Phone! Has Anyone Used It ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/04/screen-magnifier-and-smart-phone-has-anyone-used-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-04T10:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/04/screen-magnifier-and-smart-phone-has-anyone-used-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you remember I was going to
<a href="/blog/2013/08/01/laptop-vs-smartphone-part-one/">replace my laptop for a smartphone</a>.
There's the issue with a desk working environment and one solution is to buy an external
display. The other one is to use a
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=screen%20magnifier&linkCode=ur2&rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Ascreen%20magnifier&sprefix=screen%20magnifie%2Ccomputers%2C277&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Daps&linkId=KGF6F22QDNBRWAMP">screen magnifier</a><img src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
as shown on the picture
(source <a href="http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/2PC-Enlarger-Magnifier-for-Mobile-Screen-3-Times-for-All-Mobiles-Senior-2014-New-/181398272903?pt=UK_Holders_Mounts&amp;hash=item2a3c2dfb87">eBay</a>).</p>

<p><img src="/images/mobile_screen_magnifier.jpg" title="Mobile Screen Magnifier" alt="Mobile Screen Magnifier" /></p>

<p>Does anyone have experience with these? Ultimately it should be possible to use
any 3x Fresnel lens magnifier and make your 5" phone display into a 15" laptop size one.
The magnifiers used for reading,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001TLJXJ8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B001TLJXJ8&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=HS6EY4BELCHBZ6HC">this one</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B001TLJXJ8" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
are cheap and portable but don't look very well around the edges.</p>

<p>If anyone has such a device at hand I'd love to see if this works for you or not.
Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spoiler: How to Open Source Existing Proprietary Code in 10 Steps]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/23/how-to-open-source-existing-proprietary-code-in-10-steps/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T22:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/23/how-to-open-source-existing-proprietary-code-in-10-steps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We've heard about companies opening up their proprietary software products,
this is hardly news nowadays. But have you wondered what it is like to migrate
production software from closed to open source? I would like to share my own
experience about going open source as seen from behind the keyboard.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dif.io">Difio</a> was recently open sourced and the steps to go through
were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Simplify - remove everything that can be deleted</li>
<li>Create self contained modules aka re-organize the file structure</li>
<li>Separate internal from external modules</li>
<li>Refactor the existing code</li>
<li>Select license and update copyright</li>
<li>Update 3rd party dependencies to latest versions and add requirements.txt</li>
<li>Add README and verbose settings example</li>
<li>Split difio/ into its own git repository</li>
<li>Test stand alone deployments on fresh environment</li>
<li>Announce</li>
</ul>


<p>Do you want to know more? Use the comments and tell me what exactly!
I'm writing a longer version of this article so stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
