<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bugs | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/bugs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-20T14:58:31+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importing vCard Contacts To BlackBerry Z10 Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T21:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can honestly state that <a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a> sucks big
time when it comes to importing your contacts from another non-BlackBerry
device. I've been struggling to transfer my contacts from
<a href="http://amzn.to/10USRm2">Nokia 6303</a> to the Z10 for one day.</p>

<p>I tried a simple sync of the contacts from Nokia to Z10 over Bluetooth but
that failed miserably, telling me the Z10 doesn't support this functionality.
This is what to do:</p>

<ul>
<li>On Nokia - <code>Settings - Sync and backup - Create backup</code>;</li>
<li>Then navigate to <code>Apps - Extras - Memory card - Backup files</code>;</li>
<li>Select the most recent backup file, e.g. <code>Backup000.NBF</code> and
transfer it via Bluetooth (or USB cable) to my laptop;</li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: this is a ZIP file with different extension. I've tried also
to transfer it to the Z10 and open from File manager but to no avail.</p>

<ul>
<li>Just unzip the file on the computer;</li>
<li>When extracted it will create multiple directories with meaningless names.
Just find whatever you need - in my case this was the <code>contacts/</code> directory
containing hundreds of <code>.vcf</code> files;</li>
<li><p>Combine all the <code>.vcf</code> files into one. On Linux this is done with</p>

<pre><code>  cat *.vcf &gt; ../all.vcf
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: I've tried also sending all of these files to Z10. Via the
File manager individual vCards open just fine but you need to <code>Save</code> them one
by one. The combined vCard file didn't display correctly at all. Showed only one
contact.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Then go to Gmail (or any other CardDAV service) and import all your vCards.
Go to <code>Contacts - More - Import</code> - and select the combined vCard file since Gmail
doesn't support multi-file uploads;</p></li>
<li><p>On your BlackBerry go to <code>Settings - Accounts</code> and add your Gmail account.
By default this will create profiles for mail, calendar and contacts which will
be synchronized with the device.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>WARNING</strong> I had my Gmail previously configured on the Z10. Despite the account
was configured to re-sync every 15 minutes it took around 2 hours for phone numbers
to sync. And to make it worse there is no button for manual re-sync.</p>

<p>All of this done I have thousands of contacts on my Z10 spread across phone numbers,
emails, vCards and contacts from social networks. I've noticed some of them (my guess
those that had the same email or name) combined auto-magically. The rest can easily be
linked together using the Contacts app Link functionality.</p>

<p>For the record: It is also possible to send vCards one by one directly from Nokia to
Z10 via Bluetooth. The trouble is that for every entry you need to go through several
layers of menu options and confirmations. This makes it impractical.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Importing hundreds of contacts from Nokia to BlackBerry Z10 is MIA;</li>
<li>BB Contacts app (and BB Hub) is cool but has some bugs;</li>
<li>Needs manual contact re-sync button;</li>
<li>Gmail re-sync took longer than expected;</li>
<li><p>Contacts Link feature can be improved and made more easy to use, e.g.</p>

<ul>
<li>grid style display</li>
<li>multiple select and link</li>
<li>swipe and link, etc;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is sub-optimal</p>

<ul>
<li>select a contact</li>
<li>tap Links</li>
<li>tap Add Link</li>
<li>tap Search</li>
<li>type and find the entries you'd like to link;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is buggy - when searching contacts to add
as links it shows the currently opened contact too. Luckily it doesn't
crash when the same entry is selected :). I've tried.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This is with OS Version 10.0.10.261.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Even Facebook has Bugs]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/06/20/even-facebook-has-bugs/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T10:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/06/20/even-facebook-has-bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/facebook_ui_bug.png" alt="Faceook bug" style="float:left; margin-right: 10px;"/></p>

<p>Here's a small but very visible UI bug in Facebook. While selecting for which
applications to receive or not notifications there is a small progress bar image
that appears left of the checkbox element. The trouble is this image displaces the
checkbox and it appears to float right and left during the AJAX call. This is annoying.</p>

<p>There's an easy fix - either fix the progress image and checkbox positions so they don't move
or place the image to the right.</p>

<p>In my practice these types of bugs are common. I usually classify them with High priority,
because they tend to annoy the user and generate support calls or just look unprofessional.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SofiaValley UI bug]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/06/02/sofiavalley-ui-bug/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T21:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/06/02/sofiavalley-ui-bug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/bugs/sv-bug.png" alt="SV bug" style="clear:both;display:block;"/></p>

<p><a href="http://sofiavalley.com">SofiaValley</a> recently had a bug in their UI.
As seen above when clicking the Like button the widget would overlap with
other visual elements. At first this doesn't look like a big deal but it blocks
the user from sharing the page via Facebook which is important for a blog.</p>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/bugs/sv-bug-fixed.png" alt="SV bug fixed" style="clear:both;display:block;"/></p>

<p>I have reported the error and it was fixed very quickly. +1 for SofiaValley.</p>

<p>Have you spotted any other interesting bugs? Let me know and they will be published
here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring Anonymous FTP Uploads On Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/05/30/configuring-anonymous-ftp-uploads-on-red-hat-enterprise-linux-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T13:07:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/05/30/configuring-anonymous-ftp-uploads-on-red-hat-enterprise-linux-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Install related packages and make configuration changes:</p>

<pre><code>yum -y install vsftp policycoreutils-python
sed -i "s/#anon_upload_enable=YES/anon_upload_enable=YES/" /etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf
</code></pre>

<p>Configure writable directory for uploads:</p>

<pre><code>mkdir /var/ftp/pub/upload
chgrp ftp /var/ftp/pub/upload
chmod 730 /var/ftp/pub/upload
</code></pre>

<p>Configure SELinux - this is <strong><a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=968935">MISSING</a></strong>
from Red Hat's official docs:</p>

<pre><code>setsebool -P allow_ftpd_anon_write=1
semanage fcontext -a -t public_content_rw_t '/var/ftp/pub/upload(/.*)'
chcon -t public_content_rw_t /var/ftp/pub/upload
</code></pre>

<p>Start the service:</p>

<pre><code>chkconfig vsftpd on
service vsftpd start
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bug in the Fridge]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/29/bug-in-the-fridge/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-29T15:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/29/bug-in-the-fridge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/liebherr_kbgb_3864.jpg" alt="Liebherr KBGB 3864" style="float:left; margin-right: 20px;" /></p>

<p>Once you've been into
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=quality%20assurance&linkCode=ur2&rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Aquality%20assurance&sprefix=quality%20ass%2Caps%2C273&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Daps">Quality Assurance</a><img src="https://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
for 5+ years you start to notice <a href="/blog/categories/bugs/">bugs everywhere</a>
and develop a sixth sense for it. Today I found a bug in my
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=liebherr&linkCode=ur2&rh=n%3A2619525011%2Ck%3Aliebherr&sprefix=Liebherr%2Caps%2C273&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Dappliances">Liebherr</a><img src="https://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
KBGB 3864 refrigerator, caused by what looks like a race-condition.</p>

<p>This appliance starts beeping in case the door is left open for more than 60 seconds.
The alarm stops if door is closed or can be muted manually while the door is still open.</p>

<h2>The Bug</h2>

<p>It happened so that I had the door open for nearly one minute and as it was closing
I heard a beep. This time however the beeping didn't stop after the door had closed.
The alarm continued beeping with the door closed so I tried to re-open and close it again.
It didn't stop! I had to open the door and manually mute the alarm for it to stop.</p>

<div style="display:block; clear:both;">&nbsp;</div>


<h2>The Root Cause</h2>

<p>While not entirely sure, I think the reason for this malfunction
was a race-condition. The alarm went on at nearly the same time when the
controlling timer should have gone off (when closing the door).</p>

<h2>Steps To Reproduce</h2>

<p>I tried reproducing several times afterwards by opening and closing the door
at the last possible moment. I used a stop-watch to time my actions. However
I wasn't able to reproduce twice. Every time I tried, there was only one single
beep as the door was closing and no more.</p>

<p>I guess then, like we say in QE, <em>WORKS FOR ME</em>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
