<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nokia | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/nokia/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-03T18:59:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importing vCard Contacts To BlackBerry Z10 Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T21:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can honestly state that <a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a> sucks big
time when it comes to importing your contacts from another non-BlackBerry
device. I've been struggling to transfer my contacts from
<a href="http://amzn.to/10USRm2">Nokia 6303</a> to the Z10 for one day.</p>

<p>I tried a simple sync of the contacts from Nokia to Z10 over Bluetooth but
that failed miserably, telling me the Z10 doesn't support this functionality.
This is what to do:</p>

<ul>
<li>On Nokia - <code>Settings - Sync and backup - Create backup</code>;</li>
<li>Then navigate to <code>Apps - Extras - Memory card - Backup files</code>;</li>
<li>Select the most recent backup file, e.g. <code>Backup000.NBF</code> and
transfer it via Bluetooth (or USB cable) to my laptop;</li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: this is a ZIP file with different extension. I've tried also
to transfer it to the Z10 and open from File manager but to no avail.</p>

<ul>
<li>Just unzip the file on the computer;</li>
<li>When extracted it will create multiple directories with meaningless names.
Just find whatever you need - in my case this was the <code>contacts/</code> directory
containing hundreds of <code>.vcf</code> files;</li>
<li><p>Combine all the <code>.vcf</code> files into one. On Linux this is done with</p>

<pre><code>  cat *.vcf &gt; ../all.vcf
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: I've tried also sending all of these files to Z10. Via the
File manager individual vCards open just fine but you need to <code>Save</code> them one
by one. The combined vCard file didn't display correctly at all. Showed only one
contact.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Then go to Gmail (or any other CardDAV service) and import all your vCards.
Go to <code>Contacts - More - Import</code> - and select the combined vCard file since Gmail
doesn't support multi-file uploads;</p></li>
<li><p>On your BlackBerry go to <code>Settings - Accounts</code> and add your Gmail account.
By default this will create profiles for mail, calendar and contacts which will
be synchronized with the device.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>WARNING</strong> I had my Gmail previously configured on the Z10. Despite the account
was configured to re-sync every 15 minutes it took around 2 hours for phone numbers
to sync. And to make it worse there is no button for manual re-sync.</p>

<p>All of this done I have thousands of contacts on my Z10 spread across phone numbers,
emails, vCards and contacts from social networks. I've noticed some of them (my guess
those that had the same email or name) combined auto-magically. The rest can easily be
linked together using the Contacts app Link functionality.</p>

<p>For the record: It is also possible to send vCards one by one directly from Nokia to
Z10 via Bluetooth. The trouble is that for every entry you need to go through several
layers of menu options and confirmations. This makes it impractical.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Importing hundreds of contacts from Nokia to BlackBerry Z10 is MIA;</li>
<li>BB Contacts app (and BB Hub) is cool but has some bugs;</li>
<li>Needs manual contact re-sync button;</li>
<li>Gmail re-sync took longer than expected;</li>
<li><p>Contacts Link feature can be improved and made more easy to use, e.g.</p>

<ul>
<li>grid style display</li>
<li>multiple select and link</li>
<li>swipe and link, etc;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is sub-optimal</p>

<ul>
<li>select a contact</li>
<li>tap Links</li>
<li>tap Add Link</li>
<li>tap Search</li>
<li>type and find the entries you'd like to link;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is buggy - when searching contacts to add
as links it shows the currently opened contact too. Luckily it doesn't
crash when the same entry is selected :). I've tried.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This is with OS Version 10.0.10.261.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bug in Nokia software shows wrong caller ID]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/19/bug-in-nokia-software-shows-wrong-caller-id/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T09:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/19/bug-in-nokia-software-shows-wrong-caller-id</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the past month one of my cell phones,
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=Nokia&linkCode=ur2&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Daps">Nokia</a><img src="https://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001SEAOC6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B001SEAOC6&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">5800 XpressMusic</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B001SEAOC6" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
, was not showing the caller name when a friend was calling.
The number in the contacts list was correct but the name wasn't showing,
nor the custom assigned ringing tone. It turned out to be a bug!</p>

<p>The story behind this is that accidentally the same number was saved again
in the contacts list, but without a name assigned to it.
The software was matching the later one, so no custom ringing tone,
no name shown. Removing the duplicate entry fixed the issue. Software version of this
phone is</p>

<pre><code>v 21.0.025
RM-356
02-04-09
</code></pre>

<p>I wondered what will happen with multiple duplicates and if this was fixed in a later
software version so I tested with another phone,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002RXEI6U/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B002RXEI6U&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Nokia 6303</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B002RXEI6U" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />.
Software version is</p>

<pre><code>V 07.10
25-03-10
RM-638
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Step 0 - add the number to the contacts list, with name <code>Buddy 1</code></li>
<li>Step 1 - add the same number to the contacts, with <strong>empty name</strong>.
<strong>Result</strong>: You get a warning this number is already present for <code>Buddy 1</code>!
When receiving a call, <code>Buddy 1</code> is displayed.</li>
<li>Step 2 - edit the empty name contact and change the name to <code>Buddy 2</code>.
<strong>Result</strong>: when receiving a call <code>Buddy 2</code> is displayed.</li>
<li>Step 3 - add the same number again, with name <code>Buddy 0</code>. This is the latest entry
but it is sorted before the previous two (this is important).
<strong>Result</strong>: You get a warning that this number is already present for <code>Buddy 1</code> and <code>Buddy 2</code>.
When receiving a call <code>Buddy 0</code> is displayed.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Summary</strong>: so it looks like Nokia fixed the issue with empty names, by simply ignoring them
but when multiple duplicate contacts are available it displays the name of the last entered in the
contact list, independent of name sort order.</p>

<p><del>
Later today or tomorrow I will test on
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005MOW7S2/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B005MOW7S2&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Nokia 700</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B005MOW7S2" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
which runs Symbian OS and update this post with more results.
</del></p>

<p><strong>Updated on 2013-03-19 23:50</strong></p>

<p>Finally managed to test on
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005MOW7S2/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B005MOW7S2&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Nokia 700</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B005MOW7S2" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />.
Software version is:</p>

<pre><code>Release
Nokia Belle Feature pack 1
Software version
112.010.1404
Software version date
2012-03-30
Type
RM-670
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Result</strong>: If a duplicate contact entry is present it doesn't matter if the name is empty or not.
Both times no name was displayed when receiving a call. Looks like Nokia is not paying attention to
regressions at all.</p>

<h2>Android and iPhone</h2>

<p>I don't own any
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=Android&linkCode=ur2&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Delectronics">Android</a><img src="https://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
or
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=iPhone&linkCode=ur2&rh=n%3A172282%2Ck%3AiPhone&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Delectronics">iPhone</a><img src="https://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
devices so I'm not able to test on them. If you have one, please let me know if this bug is still present
and how does the software behave when multiple contacts share the same number or have empty names! Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
