<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>atodorov.org</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/windows/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://atodorov.org/</id><updated>2013-04-23T10:56:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>What Runs Your Start-up - Deed</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/23/what-runs-your-startup-deed/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-23T10:56:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-04-23:blog/2013/04/23/what-runs-your-startup-deed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/startup/deed.jpg" alt="Deed" style="float:left; margin-right: 15px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ideedit.com/"&gt;Deed&lt;/a&gt; is an action-provoking platform for challenging
yourself and others and also a business solution for improved engagement by the
corresponding communities. It solves the problem of passivity by converting people
who “Like” to people who “Act. The challenge format gives businesses an effective,
fresh and low-cost solution to maintain active connection with their communities
and measure engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emil Stoychev explains their technical background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main Technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deed is built around Microsoft technologies plus some open source libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their web application and API is built with ASP.NET MVC 3 using MS SQL 2008 database engine.
Deed is hosted on a single cloud server at Rackspace and uses Akamai CDN for static files
distribution. At the moment the team is testing Windows Azure cloud platform and plans
migrating there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A native Windows Phone application also exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of JavaScript and CSS frameworks come to play at the  web interface layer like
jQuery, &lt;a href="http://handlebarsjs.com/"&gt;Handlebars&lt;/a&gt; for templates and &lt;a href="http://lesscss.org/"&gt;Less CSS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IDE of choice is Microsoft Visual Studio 2012 for C# and Vim for everything else.
Source code revision control is managed with Mercurial and build scripts are written in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Not Something Else?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Deed team had experience with Microsoft technologies initially so it was natural
for us to choose this stack. While not perfect and costly in terms of hosting fees,
it serves its purpose for the moment. When you start a new project and you want to get
up and running fast your best choice is to use what you already mastered.
That in our case was the Microsoft stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emil Stoychev&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed I strongly support this! Always use technologies you are a master at and change and
adapt along the way if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Want More Info?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to hear more from &lt;em&gt;Deed&lt;/em&gt; please comment below.
I will ask them to follow this thread and reply to your questions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="what runs"></category><category term="start-up"></category><category term="Microsoft"></category><category term="Windows"></category><category term="Azure"></category></entry></feed>