<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: QA | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/qa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-07T01:01:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSDEM 2014 Report - Day #2 Testing and Automation]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T22:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/fosdem/2014/testing_automation.jpg" title="Testing and Automation" alt="Testing and Automation" /></p>

<p>FOSDEM was hosting the
<a href="https://fosdem.org/2014/schedule/track/testing_and_automation/">Testing and automation devroom</a>
for the second year and this was the very reason I attended the conference. I managed to get in
early and stayed until 15:00 when I had to leave to catch my flight (which was late :().</p>

<p>There were 3 talks given by Red Hat employees in the testing devroom which was a nice opportunity
to meet some of the folks I've been working on IRC with. Unfortunately I didn't meet anyone from
Fedora QA. Not sure if they were attending or not.</p>

<p>All the talks were interesting so see the official schedule and video for more details. I will
highlight only the items I saw as particularly interesting or have not heard of before.</p>

<h2>ANSTE</h2>

<p>ANSTE - Advanced Network Service Testing Environment is a test infrastructure controller,
something like our own <a href="http://beaker-project.org/">Beaker</a> but designed to create complex
networking environments. I think it lacks many of the provisioning features built in Beaker
and integration with various hypervisors and bare-metal provisioning. What it seems to do better
(as far as I can tell from the talk) is to deploy virtual systems and create more complex network
configuration between them. Not something I will need in the near future but definitely worth
a look at.</p>

<h2>cwrap</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>cwrap is...</p></p><p><p>a set of tools to create a fully isolated network environment to test client/server components on a single host.<br/>It provides synthetic account information, hostname resolution and support for privilege separation.<br/>The heart of cwrap consists of three libraries you can preload to any executable.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>That one was the coolest technology I've seen so far although I may not need to use it at all,
hmmm maybe testing DHCP fits the case.</p>

<p>It evolved from the Samba project and takes advantage of the order in which
libraries are searched when resolving functions. When you preload the project libraries
to any executable they will override standard libc functions for working with sockets,
user accounts and privilege escalation.</p>

<p>The socket_wrapper library redirects networking sockets through local UNIX sockets and
gives you the ability to test applications which need privileged ports with a local developer
account.</p>

<p>The nss_wrapper library provides artificial information for user and group accounts,
network name resolution using a hosts file and loading and testing of NSS modules.</p>

<p>The uid_wrapper library allows uid switching as a normal user (e.g. fake root) and
supports user/group changing in the local thread using the syscalls (like glibc).</p>

<p>All of these wrapper libraries are controlled via environment variables and definitely
makes testing of daemons and networking applications easier.</p>

<h2>Testing Documentation</h2>

<p>That one was just scratching the surface of an entire branch of testing which I've not
even considered before. The talk also explains why it is hard to test documentation and
what possible solutions there are.</p>

<p>If you write user guides and technical articles which need to
stay current with the software this is definitely the place to start.</p>

<h2>Automation in the Foreman Infrastructure</h2>

<p>The last talk I've listened to. Definitely the best one from a general testing approach
point of view. Greg talked about starting with Foreman unit tests, then testing the merged PR,
then integration tests, then moving on to test the package build and then the resulting packages themselves.</p>

<p>These guys try to even test their own infrastructure (infra as code) and the test suites
they use to test everything else. It's all about automation and the level of confidence
you have in the entire process.</p>

<p>I like the fact that no single testing approach can make you confident enough before shipping
the code and that they've taken into account changes which get introduced at various places
(e.g. 3rd party package upgrades, distro specific issues, infrastructure changes and such)</p>

<p>If I had to attend only one session it would have been this one. There are many things for me
to take back home and apply to my work on Fedora and RHEL.</p>

<p>If you find any of these topics remotely interesting I advise you to wait until FOSDEM video
team uploads the recordings and watch the entire session stream. I'm definitely missing a lot
of stuff which can't be easily reproduced in text form.</p>

<p>You can also find my report of the first FOSDEM'14 day on Saturday
<a href="/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-1-python-stands-lightning-talks/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upstream Test Suite Status of Fedora 20]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T08:01:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I've expressed my thoughts about the state of
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/test/2013-December/119637.html">upstream test suites in Fedora</a>
along with some other ideas. Following the response on this thread I'm starting
to analyze all SRPM packages in Fedora 20 in order to establish a baseline. Here are my initial findings.</p>

<h2>What's Inside</h2>

<p>I've found two source distributions for Fedora 20:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <code>Fedora-20-source-DVD.iso</code> file which to my knowledge contains the sources
of all packages that comprise the installation media;</li>
<li>The <code>Everything/source/SRPMS/</code> directory which appears to contain the sources
of everything else available in the Fedora 20 repositories.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are <strong>2574</strong> SRPM packages in Fedora-20 source DVD and <strong>14364</strong> SRPMs
in the Everything/ directory. 9,2G vs. 41G.</p>

<h2>Test Suite Execution In %check</h2>

<p><a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Packaging:Guidelines#Test_Suites">Fedora Packaging Guidelines</a>
state</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If the source code of the package provides a test suite,<br/>it should be executed in the %check section,<br/>whenever it is practical to do so.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>In my research I found <strong>738</strong> SRPMs on the DVD which have a %check
section and <strong>4838</strong> such packages under <code>Everything/</code>. This is <strong>28,6%</strong> and <strong>33,6%</strong>
respectively.</p>

<h2>Test Suite Existence</h2>

<p>A quick grep for either <code>test/</code> or <code>tests/</code> directories in the package sources revealed
<strong>870</strong> SRPM packages in the source DVD which are very likely to have a test suite.
This is <strong>33,8%</strong>. <strike>I wasn't able to inspect the <code>Everything/</code> directory with this script
because it takes too long to execute and my system crashed out of memory.
I will update this post later with that info.</strike></p>

<p><em>UPDATE 2014-01-02</em>:
In the <code>Everything/</code> directory only <strong>4481</strong> (<strong>31,2%</strong>) SRPM packages appear to have
test suites.</p>

<p>The scripts and raw output are available at <a href="https://github.com/atodorov/fedora-scripts">https://github.com/atodorov/fedora-scripts</a>.</p>

<p>So it looks like on average <strong>30%</strong> of the packages execute their test suites at build
time in the %check section and less than <strong>35%</strong> have test suites at all!
There's definitely room for improvement and I plan to focus on this during 2014!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Source Quality Assurance Infrastructure for Fedora QA]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/11/19/open-source-quality-assurance-infrastructure-for-fedora-qa/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T14:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/11/19/open-source-quality-assurance-infrastructure-for-fedora-qa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/fedora/beaker.png" title="Beaker test lab" alt="&quot;Beaker test lab&quot;" /></p>

<p>In the last few weeks I've been working together with
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Tflink">Tim Flink</a> and
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Kparal">Kamil Paral</a> from the Fedora QA
team on bringing some installation testing expertise to Fedora and establishing
an <a href="http://beaker.fedoraproject.org/bkr/">open source test lab</a>
to perform automated testing in. The infrastructure is
already in relatively usable condition so I've decided to share this information
with the community.</p>

<h2>Beaker is Running Our Test Lab</h2>

<p><a href="http://beaker-project.org/">Beaker</a> is the software suite that powers the test
lab infrastructure. It is quite complex, with many components and sometimes not
very straight-forward to set up. Tim has been working on that with me giving it
a try and reporting issues as they have been discovered and fixed.</p>

<p>In the process of working on this I've managed to create
<a href="http://gerrit.beaker-project.org/#/q/owner:%22Alexander+Todorov%22,n,z">couple of patches</a>
against Beaker and friends. They are still pending release in a future version
because of more urgent bug fixes which need to released first.</p>

<h2>SNAKE is The Kickstart Template Server</h2>

<p><a href="https://fedorahosted.org/snake/">SNAKE</a> is a client/server Python framework used
to support Anaconda installations. It supports plain text ks.cfg files, IIRC those
were static templates, no variable substitution.</p>

<p>The other possibility is Python templates based on Pykickstart:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">pykickstart.constants</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">KS_SCRIPT_POST</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">pykickstart.parser</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">Script</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">installdefaults</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">InstallKs</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">ks</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="n">context</span><span class="p">):</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="s">&#39;&#39;&#39;Anaconda autopart&#39;&#39;&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ks</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">InstallKs</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ks</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">packages</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="s">&#39;@base&#39;</span><span class="p">])</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ks</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">clearpart</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">initAll</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ks</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">autopart</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">autopart</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">script</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&#39;&#39;&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&lt;p&gt;cp /tmp/ks.cfg /mnt/sysimage/root/ks.cfg || </span><span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">cp /run/install/ks.cfg /mnt/sysimage/root/ks.cfg</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">&#39;&#39;&#39;</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">post</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Script</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">script</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">type</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">KS_SCRIPT_POST</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">inChroot</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">False</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ks</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">scripts</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">post</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">ks</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>At the moment SNAKE is essentially abandoned but feature complete.
I'm thinking about adopting the project just in case we need to make some fixes.
Will let you know more about this when it happens.</p>

<h2>Open Source Test Suite</h2>

<p>I have been working on opening up several test cases for what we (QE) call
a tier #1 installation test suite. They can be found in
<a href="http://taskbot.cloud.fedoraproject.org/cgit/fedora-beaker-tests/">git</a>.
The tests are base on <a href="https://fedorahosted.org/beakerlib/">beakerlib</a> and
the legacy RHTS framework which is now part of Beaker.</p>

<p>This effort has been coordinated with Kamil as part of a pilot
project he's responsible for. I've been executing the same test suite against
earlier Fedora 20 snapshots but using an internal environment. Now everything
is going out in the open.</p>

<h2>Executing The Tests</h2>

<p>Well you can't do that - YET! There are command line client tools for Fedora
but Beaker and SNAKE are not well suited for use outside a restricted network
like LAN or VPN. There are issues with authentication most notably for SNAKE.</p>

<p>At the moment I have to ssh through two different systems to get proper access.
However this is been worked on. I've read about a rewrite which will allow Beaker
to utilize a custom authentication framework like FAS for example. Hopefully that
will be implemented soon enough.</p>

<p>I will also like to see the test systems have direct access to the Internet for
various reasons but this is not without its risks either. This is still to be
decided.</p>

<p>If you are interested anyway see the <code>kick-tests.sh</code> file in the test suite for
examples and command line options.</p>

<h2>Test Results</h2>

<p>The first successfully completed
<a href="http://beaker.fedoraproject.org/bkr/jobs/">test jobs</a> are jobs 50 to 58.
There's a failure in one of the test cases, namely SELinux related
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1027148">RHBZ #1027148</a>.</p>

<p>From what I can tell the lab is now working as expected and we can start doing
some testing against Fedora development snapshots.</p>

<p>Ping me or join #fedora-qa on irc.freenode.net if you'd like to join Fedora QA!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keeping Backwards Compatibility for pykickstart]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/11/13/keeping-backwards-compatibility-for-pykickstart/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T23:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/11/13/keeping-backwards-compatibility-for-pykickstart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Consider the following scenario:</p>

<ul>
<li>I'm using <a href="https://fedorahosted.org/snake/">SNAKE</a> templates as part of my
installation testing work;</li>
<li>SNAKE has a dependency on pykickstart;</li>
<li>To test the latest and greatest kickstart features in Fedora we need the
latest version of pykickstart;</li>
<li>Latest pykickstart needs Python 2.7</li>
<li>Python 2.7 is not available on RHEL 6 which is used to host the test
infrastructure.</li>
</ul>


<p>Just yesterday I hit an issue with the above setup and figured Fedora QA is
in a kind of strange situation - we always need the latest but need it
conservative enough to run on RHEL 6. See the original thread at
<a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/kickstart-list/2013-November/msg00001.html">kickstart-list</a>.</p>

<p>In this particular case the solution will be to remove the offending code
and implement the same functionality in backward-compatible manner. Also add
more tests. I will be working on this tomorrow (there's an older patch already).</p>

<p>The BIG question remains though - how do you manage software evolution and still
keep it compatible with older execution stacks? Please share your experience in
the comments section.</p>

<hr />

<p>PP: Spoiler - this is part of an ongoing effort to bring open source installation
testing expertise (my domain) into Fedora world, plus establish a community supported
test infrastructure. More info TBA soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fedora 20 GNOME 3.10 Test Day Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/11/fedora-20-gnome-3-dot-10-test-day-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T12:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/11/fedora-20-gnome-3-dot-10-test-day-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/fedora/sausage-banner.png" title="Fedora sausage banner" alt="&quot;Fedora sausage banner&quot;" /></p>

<p>Here is my summary of the second Fedora Test Day hosted at
<a href="http://initlab.org">init Lab</a> yesterday.</p>

<p>Local attendance was a total disaster, in fact I was testing once again by my own.
This time
there were more people in the lab, all busy with their daily routines and tasks.
There were no people who came for the testing :(. I will have to try different
venues in the future and see if the situation improves.</p>

<p>On the testing front I managed to score 5 bugs against
<a href="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/buglist.cgi?bug_id=709797,709799,709806,709810">GNOME</a>
and <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1017807">Fedora</a>.
You can see the other test results and bugs on the
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Test_Day:2013-10-10_Gnome_3.10">wiki</a>.</p>

<p>There are two things I didn't like in particular</p>

<ul>
<li>GNOME 3 as well as its classic mode - simply not the environment I'm used to;</li>
<li>Having to record test results in the wiki! I'm
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/test/2013-October/118284.html">writing</a>
to the Fedora QA mailing list about that as we speak.</li>
</ul>


<p>At one time I was engaged in a discussion about which Bulgarian keyboard layout
should be the default in GNOME simply because of
<a href="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=709799">GNOME #709799</a>. The default
keyboard layout will be Bulgarian (traditional phonetic) aka bg+phonetic.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>(16,13,26) rtcm: atodorov: are you bulgarian and/or live in bulgaria?<br/>(16,14,20) rtcm: atodorov: if yes, I wanted to know which keyboard layout most people expect there to be the default<br/>(16,16,34) atodorov: rtcm: I'm a Bulgarian, however I can't tell which one. Both Phonetic and standard (BDS) are common<br/>(16,16,54) atodorov: a safe bet is to go with phonetic I guess.<br/>(16,19,46) rtcm: atodorov: can you tell me which one is it in XKB terms? is it "bg", "bg+bas_phonetic" or "bg+phonetic" ?<br/>(16,20,51) rtcm: they're labeled as "Bulgarian", "Bulgarian (new phonetic)" and "Bulgarian (traditional phonetic)"<br/>(16,21,30) atodorov: bg+phonetic is the traditional phonetic<br/>(16,22,04) atodorov: bg labeled as "Bulgarian" is the standard one I guess. Here we call it BDS after the standardization institute<br/>(16,22,34) atodorov: bg+bas_phonetic is created from the Bulgarian Academy of Science and is not very popular as far as I know. I've never seen it in use<br/>(16,23,15) rtcm: atodorov: all I want to know is what most people would expect? like what does windows do by default? that's a good bet<br/>(16,27,46) atodorov: rtcm: I'm just being told that new Windows releases use yet another layout by default, which is like phonetic but with some characters in new places and people don't like that<br/>(16,27,53) atodorov: my safe bet goes to bg+phonetic<br/>(16,29,05) rtcm: ok, thanks</p></blockquote></p>

<p>It is a rare occasion when you get to make a decision that affects a large group
of people and I hope you don't hate me for that!</p>

<p>Do you want to see more Fedora Test Days happening in Sofia? Join me and I will
organize some more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
