<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: QA | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/qa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T11:34:42+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lenovo Rants: Battery and Dock Flaws]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/15/lenovo-rants-battery-and-dock-flaws/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T10:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/15/lenovo-rants-battery-and-dock-flaws</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To all my readers - sorry for not being able to blog more frequently lately.
Here's an easy read about my favourite laptop brand Lenovo and some of their
design flaws I've found.</p>

<h2>X220 and T60 Batterries are ALMOST Identical</h2>

<p><img src="/images/lenovo_x220_t60_battery.jpg" title="X220 and T60 batteries" alt="&quot;X220 and T60 batteries&quot;" /></p>

<p>As you can see the <a href="http://amzn.to/12y5hwp">X220</a> and
<a href="http://amzn.to/183SgiR">T60</a> batteries are nearly identical with the notable
exception of the connector placement. The end result - I have to purchase yet another
battery as a backup for long travel/work on the go. Not what I want.</p>

<p>I wish all Lenovo models had the same batteries so people can swap them around
as they wish. Is this too much to ask for? Have you seen another brand which
got this right?</p>

<h2>ThinkPad Mini Dock Design Flaw</h2>

<p>Note: this section has previously been published
<a href="http://otb.bg/blog/2012/06/14/thinkpad-mini-dock-design-flaw/">here</a>.</p>

<p>I'm using a <a href="http://amzn.to/15tjUYi">ThinkPad Mini Dock Series 3</a> docking station
with my X220 laptop. Being a QA engineer for so long I immediately
noticed something that wasn't quite right. The buttons on the left and the mechanism
next to them are blocking the hot air exhaust from the CPU fan. This model of docking
station is made to fit several models of laptops and those which dock in position 2 are
less affected from those which dock in possition 1. Mine was not a lucky one.</p>

<p><img src="/images/dock/alone.jpg" title="docking station in position 2" alt="docking station in position 2" /></p>

<p>On the pictures below it is clearly visible that most of the hot air coming out of the CPU
fan is blocked.</p>

<p><img src="/images/dock/top.jpg" title="top view" alt="top view" />
<img src="/images/dock/back.jpg" title="back view" alt="back view" />
<img src="/images/dock/side.jpg" title="side view" alt="side view" /></p>

<p>In order to reduce laptop heating and provide better cooling I decided to remove the
1/2 position switch mechanism. To do that you have to unscrew all screws from the docking
station and carefully split the top and bottom halves. The offending piece of plastic is
screwed with two tiny screws at the bottom. Once they are removed everything comes off.</p>

<p><img src="/images/dock/removed.jpg" title="blocking part removed" alt="blocking part removed" /></p>

<p>Even with this piece removed my laptop still hets up too much! I guess 80 C is just
normal for the Core i7 processors :(.</p>

<p>Have you found something not quite right in your hardware design? Please share in the
comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming Talk: Fedora Test Days in Sofia]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T23:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On September 28th I will be giving a short talk about
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Test_Days">Fedora Test Days</a> at the regular
Linux for Bulgarians
<a href="http://www.linux-bg.org/cgi-bin/y/index.pl?page=news&amp;key=459487176">conference</a>.
I will explain what these are and how one can participate. I will also announce
my plans and schedule to organize some
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Fedora_20_test_days">Fedora 20 test days</a>
locally in Sofia. If you are a fan of Fedora and want to file bugs and kick
some developers' ass this is the way to do it!</p>

<p>Other talks include Alexander Shopov's „Oracle's take on NoSQL“ which I wanted
to hear since this summer and TBA talks about MicroTik routers.</p>

<p>The conference will take place on September 28th at the French Institute at
Sofia University
(see <a href="http://conf.linux-bg.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/su-2.png">map</a>).
It starts at 13:00 and my talk should be at the beginning. See you there!</p>

<p>PS: this post was initially written on my <a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a>
with Penzus Editor - another small step in
<a href="/blog/2013/08/01/laptop-vs-smartphone-part-one/">retiring my laptop</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bug Analysis Of RHBZ #1337]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/02/bug-analysis-of-rhbz-1337/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-02T16:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/02/bug-analysis-of-rhbz-1337</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/blog/2013/08/23/red-hats-ebugzilla-hits-one-million-bugs/">previous post</a>
I asked the readers of this blog to pick a bug number from Red Hat's Bugzilla
so I can analyze it later.</p>

<p><a href="http://radorado.me">Radoslav Georgiev</a> decided to step up and
selected the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leet">Leet</a> bug
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1337">https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1337</a></p>

<p>This is a rather old bug against kernel, in particular
against the token ring driver. There isn't much info on the bug but it seems
the issue is hardware dependent and doesn't reproduce reliably.</p>

<p>Looking at the bug status and history it looks like it was closed without
fixing it. Most likely the reason for this was there was no hardware
to test, bug was not reproduced and no customers were seeing the issue or
were willing to test and work with devel!</p>

<p>If you'd like to see my comments on other interesting bugs just post a link
to them in the comments section.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Red Hat's Bugzilla Hits One Million Bugs]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/23/red-hats-bugzilla-hits-one-million-bugs/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T12:21:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/23/red-hats-bugzilla-hits-one-million-bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/redhat_1mil_bugs.jpg" title="RHBZ 1 million" alt="&quot;RHBZ 1 million&quot;" /></p>

<p>Red Hat's Bugzilla passed the 1 million bugs milestone yesterday!
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1000000">RHBZ #1000000</a> has been
filed by Anton Arapov, a kernel engineer and a very nice guy (I know him btw).
I've filed several bugs yesterday but the last one was #999941. A bit too short!</p>

<p>To celebrate this event I dare you to pick some bugs from Bugzilla that you find
interesting or frustrating and I will try to analyze and explain them from a
QA engineer's point of view. Since I've reported over 1000 bugs and been involved in
another close to 5000 I think I will be able to answer almost any question.</p>

<p>Challenge accepted!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small But Annoying Twitter Bug]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/23/small-but-annoying-twitter-bug/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T12:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/23/small-but-annoying-twitter-bug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/twitter_embed_bug.png" title="Tweet Embed Bug" alt="&quot;Tweet Embed Bug&quot;" /></p>

<p>I've been having troubles with Twitter lately but this bug is just annoying!
Where on Earth is the "code below" ? I've already
<a href="https://twitter.com/atodorov_/status/370833992074809345">reported it</a>. Let's
see how long it takes for them to fix it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
