<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: QA | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/qa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-03T18:59:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Last Week in Fedora QA]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/03/03/last-week-in-fedora-qa/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T10:23:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/03/03/last-week-in-fedora-qa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some highlights from the past week discussions in Fedora which I found
interesting or participated in.</p>

<h2>Call to Action: Improving Overall Test Coverage in Fedora</h2>

<p>I can not stress enough how important it is to further
<a href="/blog/2014/02/28/action-improving-test-coverage-in-fedora/">improve test coverage in Fedora</a>!
You can help too. Here's how:</p>

<ul>
<li>Join upstream and create a test suite for a package you find interesting;</li>
<li>Provide patches - <a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/devel/2014-February/196035.html">first patch</a>
came in less than 30 minutes of initial announcement :);</li>
<li>Review packages in the wiki and help identify false negatives;</li>
<li>Forward to people who may be interested to work on these items;</li>
<li>Share and promote in your local open source and developer communities;</li>
</ul>


<h2>Auto BuildRequires</h2>

<p><a href="http://people.redhat.com/~rjones/auto-buildrequires/">Auto-BuildRequires</a>
is a simple set of scripts which compliments <code>rpmbuild</code> by
automatically suggesting BuildRequires lines for the just built package.</p>

<p>It would be interesting to have this integrated into Koji and/or
continuous integration environment and compare the output between every two
consecutive builds (iow older and newer package versions). It sounds like a
good way to identify newly added or removed dependencies and update the package
specs accordingly.</p>

<h2>How To Test Fonts Packages</h2>

<p>This is exactly what
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/test/2014-February/120570.html">Christopher Meng asked</a>
and frankly I have no idea.</p>

<p>I've come across a few fonts packages (<em>amiri-fonts</em>, <em>gnu-free-fonts</em> and <em>thai-scalable-fonts</em>)
which seem to have some sort of test suites but I don't know how they work or
what type of problems they test for. On top of that all three have a different
way of doing things (e.g. not using a standardized test framework or a variation of such).</p>

<p>I'll keep you posted on this once I manage to get more info from upstream developers.</p>

<h2>Is URL Field in RPM Useless</h2>

<p>So is it? Opinions here differ from totally useless to "don't remove it, I need it".
However I run a small test and from 2574 RPMs on the source DVD there is around
40% of "something different than HTTP 200 OK". This means <strong>40% potentially broken URLs</strong>!</p>

<p>The majority are responses in the 3XX range and only less than 10% are
actual errors (4XX, 5XX, missing URLs or connection errors).</p>

<p>It will be interesting to see if this can be removed from <code>rpm</code> altogether.
I don't think it will happen soon but if we don't use it why have it there?</p>

<p>My script for the test is
<a href="https://github.com/atodorov/fedora-scripts/blob/master/test-rpm-url-field.sh">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Call to Action: Improving Overall Test Coverage in Fedora]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/28/action-improving-test-coverage-in-fedora/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T14:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/28/action-improving-test-coverage-in-fedora</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Around Christmas 2013
<a href="/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20/">I said</a>
<blockquote><p>... it looks like on average 30% of the packages execute their test suites at<br/>build time in the %check section and less than 35% have test suites at all!<br/>There’s definitely room for improvement and I plan to focus on this during 2014!</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I've recently started working on this goal by first identifying potential offending
packages and discussing the idea on Fedora's
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/devel/2014-February/thread.html">devel</a>,
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/packaging/2014-February/thread.html">packaging</a>
and <a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/test/2014-February/thread.html">test</a>
mailing lists.</p>

<p>May I present you nearly <strong>2000 packages</strong> which need your love:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Testing_in_check">wiki/QA/Testing_in_check</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Missing_upstream_test_suites">wiki/QA/Missing_upstream_test_suites</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The intent for these pages is to serve as a source of working material for Fedora
volunteers.</p>

<h2>How Can I Help</h2>

<ul>
<li>Join upstream and create a test suite for a package you find interesting;</li>
<li>Provide patches - <a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/devel/2014-February/196035.html">first patch</a>
came in less than 30 minutes of initial announcement :);</li>
<li>Review packages in the wiki and help identify false negatives;</li>
<li>Forward to people who may be interested to work on these items;</li>
<li>Share and promote in your local open source and developer communities;</li>
</ul>


<h2>Important</h2>

<p>If you would like to gain some open source practice and QA experience I will
happily provide mentorship and general help so you can start working on Fedora.
Just ping me!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[7 Years and 1400 Bugs Later as Red Hat QA]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/19/7-years-1400-bugs-red-hat-qa/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-19T10:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/19/7-years-1400-bugs-red-hat-qa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I celebrate my 7th year working at Red Hat's Quality Engineering department.
Here's my story!</p>

<p><img src="/images/redhat_platform_qe.jpg" title="Platform QE" alt="Platform QE" /></p>

<p>On a cold winter Friday in 2007 I left my job as a software developer in Sofia,
packed my stuff together, purchased my <a href="http://amzn.to/1hlPuyr">first laptop</a> and
on Sunday jumped the train to Brno to join the Release Test Team at Red Hat.
Little did I know what it was all about. When I was offered the position
I was on a very noisy bus and had to pick between two positions. I didn't quite understood
what were the options and just picked the second one.
Luckily everything turned out great and continues to this day.</p>

<p>I'm sharing my experience and highlighting some bugs which I've found.
Hopefully you will find this interesting and amusing. If you are a QA engineer
I urge you to take a look at <a href="http://red.ht/1gbHElQ">my public bug portfolio</a>,
dive into details, read the comments and learn as much as you can.</p>

<h2>What do I do exactly</h2>

<p>From all QE teams in Red Hat, Release Test Team is the first one and
last one to test a release. The team has both technical function and a more managerial one.
Our focus is on the core Red Hat Enterprise Linux product.
Unfortunately I can't go into much details because this is not a public facing unit.
I will limit myself to <strong>public and/or non-sensitive information</strong>.</p>

<p>We are the first to test a new nightly build or a
snapshot of the upcoming RHEL release. If the tree is installable other teams take over
and do their magic. At the end when bits are published live we're the last to
verify that content is published where it is expected to be. In short this is
covering the work of the release engineering team which is to build a product and
publish the contents for consumption.</p>

<p>The same principles apply to Fedora although the engagement here is less demanding.</p>

<p>Personally I have been and continue to be responsible for Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5
family of releases. It's up to me to give the go ahead for further testing or request
a re-spin. This position
also has the power to block and delay the GA release if not happy with testing or
there is a considerable risk of failure until things are sorted out.</p>

<p>Like in other QA teams I create test plan documents, write test case scenarios,
implement test automation scripts (and sometimes tools), regularly execute said test
plans and test cases, find and report any new bugs and verify old ones are fixed.
Most importantly make sure RHEL installs and is usable for further testing :).</p>

<p>Sometimes I have to deal with capacity planning and as RHEL 5 installation
test lead I have to organize and manage the entire installation testing campaign
for that product.</p>

<p>My favorite testing technique is
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploratory_testing">exploratory testing</a>.</p>

<h2>Stats and Numbers</h2>

<p>It is hard (if not impossible) to <a href="https://github.com/atodorov/qe-metrics">measure QA work</a>
with numbers alone but here are some interesting facts about my experience so far.</p>

<ul>
<li>Nearly 1400 bugs filed (1390 at the time of writing);</li>
<li>Reported bugs across 32 different products. Top 3 being RHEL 6, RHEL 5 and Fedora (1000+ bugs);</li>
<li>Top 3 components for reporting bugs against: anaconda, releng, kernel;</li>
<li>Nearly 100 bugs filed in my first year 2007;</li>
<li>The 3 most productive years being 2010, 2009, 2011 (800 + bugs);</li>
<li>Filed 200 bugs/year which is about 1 bug/day considering holidays;</li>
<li>35th top bug reporter (excluding robot accounts). I was in top 10 a few years back;</li>
</ul>


<p>Many of <a href="http://red.ht/1gbHElQ">the bugs I report</a> are private so if you'd like
to know more stats just ask me and I'll see what I can do.</p>

<h2>2007</h2>

<p>My very first bug is <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=231860">RHBZ #231860</a>(private)
which is about the graphical update tool Pup which used to show the wrong number of available
updates.</p>

<p>Then I've played with adding <a href="https://fedorahosted.org/dogtail/">Dogtail</a> support to Anaconda.
While initially this was rejected (Fedora 6/7), it was <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Anaconda/Features/Dogtail">implemented</a>
few years later (Fedora 9) and then removed once again during the big Anaconda rewrite.</p>

<p>I've spent my time working extensively on RHEL 5 battling with multi-lib issues, SELinux denials and
generally making the 5 family less rough. Because I was still on-boarding I generally worked
on everything I could get my hands on and also did some work on RHEL3-U9 (latest release
before EOL) and some RHEL4-U6 testing.</p>

<p>With ia64 on RHEL3 I found a corner case
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=240782">kernel bug</a> which flooded the serial
console with messages and caused a multi-CPU system to freeze.</p>

<h2>In 2008 Time went backwards</h2>

<p>My first bug in 2008 is <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=428280">RHBZ #428280</a>.
glibc introduced SHA-256/512 hashes for hashing passwords with crypt but that wasn't documented.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE 2014-02-21</strong>
While testing 5.1 to 5.2 updates I found
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=435475">RHBZ #435475</a> - a severe
<strong>performance degradation</strong> in the package installation process. Upgrades
took almost twice as much time to complete, rising <strong>from 4 hours to 7 hours</strong>
depending on hardware and package set. This was a tough one to test and verify.
<strong>END UPDATE</strong></p>

<p>While dogfooding the 5.2 beta in March I hit
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=437252">RHBZ #437252</a> - kernel: Timer ISR/0: Time went backwards.
To this date this is one of my favorite bugs with a great error message!</p>

<p>Removal of a hack in RPM led to file conflicts under <code>/usr/share/doc</code> in several packages:
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448905">RHBZ #448905</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448906">RHBZ #448906</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448907">RHBZ #448907</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448909">RHBZ #448909</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448910">RHBZ #448910</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=448911">RHBZ #448911</a>
which is also the first time I happen to file several bugs in a row.</p>

<p>ia64 couldn't boot with encrypted partitions -
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=464769">RHBZ #464769</a>,
RHEL 5 introduced support for ext4 - <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=465248">RHBZ #465248</a>
and I've hit a fontconfig issue during upgrades - <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=469190">RHBZ #469190</a>
which continued to resurface occasionally during the next 5 years.</p>

<p>This is the year when I took over responsibility for the general installation
testing of RHEL 5 from James Laska and will continue to do so until it reaches end-of-life!</p>

<p>I've also worked on RHEL 4, Fedora and even the OLPC project. On the testing side of things
I've participated in testing
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/TestPlans/Networking">Fedora networking on the XO</a>
hardware and worked on translation and general issues.</p>

<h2>2009 - here comes RHEL 6</h2>

<p>This year starts my 3 most productive years period.</p>

<p>The second bug reported this
year is <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=481338">RHBZ #481338</a> which
also mentions one of my hobbies - wrist watches. While browsing a particular
website Xorg CPU usage rose to 100%. I've seen a number of these through the years
and I'm still not sure if its Xorg or Firefox or both to blame. And I still see my
CPU usage go to 100% just like that and drain my battery. I'm open to suggestions how
to test and debug what's going on as it doesn't happen in a reproducible fashion.</p>

<p>I happened to work on RHEL 4, RHEL 5, Fedora and the upcoming RHEL 6 releases and
managed to file bugs in a row not once but twice.
I wish I was paid per bug reported back then :).</p>

<p>The first series was about empty debuginfo packages with both empty packages which
shouldn't have existed at all
(e.g. <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=500628">redhat-release</a>)
and missing debuginfo information for binary packages
(e.g. <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=500612">nmap</a>).</p>

<p>The second series is around 100 bugs which had to do with the texinfo
documentation of packages when installed with --excludedocs. The first one
is <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=515909">RHBZ #515909</a> and the
last one <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=516014">RHBZ #516014</a>.
While this works great for bumping up your bug count it made lots of developers
unhappy and not all bugs were fixed. Still the use case is valid and these
were proper software errors. It is also the first time I've used a script to
file the bugs automatically and not by hand.</p>

<p>Near the end of the year I've started testing installation on new hardware
by the likes of Intel and AMD before they hit the market. I had the pleasure to work
with the latest chipsets and CPUs, even sometime pre-release versions and make sure
Red Hat Enterprise Linux installed and worked properly on them. I've stopped doing
this last year to free up time for other tasks.</p>

<h2>2010 - one bug a day keeps developers at bay :)</h2>

<p>My most productive year with 1+ bugs per day.</p>

<p>2010 starts with a bug about file conflicts (private one) and continues with the same
narrative throughout the year.
As a matter of fact I did a small experiment and found around <strong>50000</strong>
(you read that right, fifty thousand) potentially
conflicting files, mostly between multi-lib packages, which were being ignored by RPM
due to its multi-lib policies. However these were primarily man pages or documentation
and most of them didn't get fixed. The proper fix would have been to introduce a
-docs sub-package and split these files from the actual binaries. Fortunately the world
migrated to 64bit only and this isn't an issue anymore.</p>

<p>By that time RHEL 6 development was running at its peak capacity and there were Beta
versions available. Almost the entire year I've been working on internal RHEL 6 snapshots
and discovering the many new bugs introduced with tons of new features in the installer.
Some of the new features included better IPv6 support, dracut and KVM.</p>

<p>An interesting set of bugs from September are the rpmlint errors and warnings ones,
for example <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=634931">RHBZ #634931</a>. I just
run the most basic test tool against some packages. It generated lots of false negatives
but also revealed bugs which were fixed.</p>

<p>Although there were many bugs filed this year I don't see any particularly interesting ones.
It's been more like lots of work to improve the overall quality than exploring
edge cases and finding interesting failures. If you find a bug from this period that you
think is interesting I will comment on it.</p>

<h2>2011 - Your system may be seriously compromised</h2>

<p>This is the last year of my 3 year top cycle.</p>

<p>It starts with <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=666687">RHBZ #666687</a> -
a patch for my crappy printer-scanner-coffee maker which I've been carrying around
since <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=498228">2009</a> when I bought it.</p>

<p>I was still working primarily on RHEL 6 but helped test the latest RHEL 4 release
before it went end-of-life. The interesting thing about it was that unlike other
released RHEL4-U9 was not available on installation media but only as an update from
RHEL4-U8. This was a great experience which you happen to see
<a href="https://access.redhat.com/site/support/policy/updates/errata/">every 4 to 5 years</a> or so.</p>

<p>Btw I've also led the installation testing effort and RTT team through the last few
RHEL 4 releases but given the product was approaching EOL there weren't many changes
and things went smoothly.</p>

<p>A minor side activity was me playing around with
<a href="/blog/2011/03/14/usb-multi-seat-on-red-hat-enterprise-linux-6/">USB Multi-seat</a>
and finding a few bugs here and there along the way.</p>

<p>Another interesting activity in 2011 was proof-reading the entire product documentation
before its release which I can now relate to the
<a href="/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/">Testing Documentation</a>
talk at FOSDEM 2014.</p>

<p>In 2011 I've started using the cloud and most notably Red Hat's OpenShift PaaS service.
First internally as an early adopter and later externally after the product was announced
to the public. There are a few interesting bugs here but they are private and I'm not
at liberty to share although they've all been fixed since then.</p>

<p>An interesting bug with NUMA, Xen and ia64
(<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=696599">RHBZ #696599</a> - private) had
me and devel banging our heads against the wall until we figured out that on this
particular system the NUMA configuration was not suitable for running Xen virtualization.</p>

<p>Can you spot the problem here ?
<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="k">try</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">kickstartGui</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">except</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">print</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Could not open display because no X server is running.&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">print</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Try running &#39;system-config-kickstart --help&#39; for a list of options.&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">sys</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">exit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Be honest and use the comments form to tell me what you've found. If you struggled
then see <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=703085">RHBZ #703085</a> and come
back again to comment. I'd love to hear from you.</p>

<p>What do you do when you see an error message saying:
<strong>Your system may be seriously compromised! /usr/sbin/NetworkManager tried to load a kernel module.</strong>
This is the scariest error message I've ever seen. Luckily its just
SELinux overreacting, see <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=704090">RHBZ #704090</a>.</p>

<h2>2012 is in the red zone</h2>

<p>While the number of reported bugs dropped significantly compared to previous
years this is the year when I've reported almost exclusively high priority and
urgent bugs, the first one being
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=771901">RHBZ #771901</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=799384">RHBZ #799384</a>(against Fedora)
is one of the rare cases when I was able to contribute
(although just by raising awareness) to localization and improved support for
Bulgarian and Cyrillic.
The other one case was <a href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/11/fedora-20-gnome-3-dot-10-test-day-post-mortem/">last year</a>.
Btw I find it strange that although
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyrillic_script">Cyrillic was invented by Bulgarians</a>
we didn't (or still don't) have a native font co-maintainer.
Somebody please step up!</p>

<p>The red zone bugs continue to span till the end of the year across RHEL 5, 6 and
early cuts of RHEL 7 with a pinch of OpenShift and some internal and external test tools.</p>

<h2>In 2013 Bugzilla hit 1 million bugs</h2>

<p>The year starts with a very annoying and still not fixed bug against ABRT.
It's very frustrating when the tool which is supposed to help you file bugs
doesn't work properly, see <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=903591">RHBZ #903591</a>.
It's a known fact that
<a href="/2012/07/13/mission-impossible-abrt-bugzilla-plugin-on-rhel6/">ABRT has problems</a>
and for this scenario I may have a
<a href="/blog/2013/10/12/tip-installing-missing-debuginfo-packages-for-abrt/">tip</a> for you.</p>

<p><a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=923416">RHBZ #923416</a> - another one of these
100% CPU bugs. As I said they happen from time to time and mostly go by unfixed or
partially fixed because of their nature. Btw as I'm writing this post and have
a few tabs open in Firefox it keeps using between 15% and 20% CPU and the CPU
temperature is over 90 degrees C. And all I'm doing is writing text in the console.
Help!</p>

<p><a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=967229">RHBZ #967229</a> - a minor one but
reveals an important thing - your output (and input for that matter) methods may
be producing different results. Worth testing if your software supports more than one.</p>

<p>This year I did some odd jobs working on several of Red Hat's layered products mainly
Developer Toolset. It wasn't a tough job and was a refreshing break away from the mundane
installation testing.</p>

<p>While I stopped working actively on the various RHEL families which are under development
or still supported I happened to be one of top 10 bug reporters for high/urgent priority bugs
for RHEL 7. In appreciation Red Hat sent me lots of corporate gifts and the Platform QE hoodie
pictured at the top of the page. Many thanks!</p>

<p>In the summer Red Hat's
<a href="/blog/2013/08/23/red-hats-bugzilla-hits-one-million-bugs/">Bugzilla hit One Million bugs</a>.
The closest I come to this milestone is
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=999941">RHBZ #999941</a>.</p>

<p>I finally managed to transfer most of my responsibilities to co-workers and joined
the Fedora QA team as a part-time contributor. I had some highs and lows with
<a href="/blog/2013/10/07/fedora-20-virtualization-and-gnome-test-days-at-init-lab-this-week/">Fedora test days in Sofia</a>
as well. Good thing is I scored another 15 bugs across the
<a href="/blog/2013/10/08/fedora-20-virtualization-test-day-post-mortem/">virtualization stack</a>
and <a href="/blog/2013/10/11/fedora-20-gnome-3-dot-10-test-day-post-mortem/">GNOME 3.10</a>.</p>

<p>The year wraps up with another series of identical bugs,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1024729">RHBZ #1024729</a> and
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1025289">RHBZ #1025289</a> for example.
As it <a href="/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20/">turned out</a>
lots of packages don't have any test suites at all and those
which do don't always execute them automatically in %check. I've promised myself
to improve this but still haven't had time to work on it. Hopefully by
March I will have something in the works.</p>

<h2>2014 - Fedora QA improvement</h2>

<p>Last two months I've been working on some internal projects and looking
a little bit into improving processes, test coverage and QA infrastructure -
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1064895">RHBZ #1064895</a>.
And Rawhide (upcoming Fedora 21) isn't behaving -
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1063245">RHBZ #1063245</a>.</p>

<p>My goal for this year is to do more work on improving the overall test coverage
of Fedora and together with the Fedora QA team bring an
<a href="/blog/2013/11/19/open-source-quality-assurance-infrastructure-for-fedora-qa/">open testing infrastructure</a>
to the community.</p>

<p>Let's see how well that plays out!</p>

<h2>What do I do now</h2>

<p>During the last year I have gradually changed my responsibilities to work more on Fedora.
As a volunteer in the Fedora QA I'm regularly testing installation
of Rawhide trees and try to work closely with the community. I still have to
manage RHEL 5 test cycles where I don't expect nothing disruptive at this stage in the
product life-cycle!</p>

<p>I'm open to any ideas and help which can improve test coverage and quality of software
in Fedora. If you're just joining the open source world this is an excellent
opportunity to do some good, get noticed and even maybe get a job. I will definitely
help you get through the process if you're willing to commit your time to this.</p>

<p>I hope this long post has been useful and fun to read. Please use the comments form to tell
me if I'm missing something or you'd like to know more.</p>

<p><em>Looking forward to the next 7 years!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSDEM 2014 Report - Day #2 Testing and Automation]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T22:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/fosdem/2014/testing_automation.jpg" title="Testing and Automation" alt="Testing and Automation" /></p>

<p>FOSDEM was hosting the
<a href="https://fosdem.org/2014/schedule/track/testing_and_automation/">Testing and automation devroom</a>
for the second year and this was the very reason I attended the conference. I managed to get in
early and stayed until 15:00 when I had to leave to catch my flight (which was late :().</p>

<p>There were 3 talks given by Red Hat employees in the testing devroom which was a nice opportunity
to meet some of the folks I've been working on IRC with. Unfortunately I didn't meet anyone from
Fedora QA. Not sure if they were attending or not.</p>

<p>All the talks were interesting so see the official schedule and video for more details. I will
highlight only the items I saw as particularly interesting or have not heard of before.</p>

<h2>ANSTE</h2>

<p>ANSTE - Advanced Network Service Testing Environment is a test infrastructure controller,
something like our own <a href="http://beaker-project.org/">Beaker</a> but designed to create complex
networking environments. I think it lacks many of the provisioning features built in Beaker
and integration with various hypervisors and bare-metal provisioning. What it seems to do better
(as far as I can tell from the talk) is to deploy virtual systems and create more complex network
configuration between them. Not something I will need in the near future but definitely worth
a look at.</p>

<h2>cwrap</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>cwrap is...</p></p><p><p>a set of tools to create a fully isolated network environment to test client/server components on a single host.<br/>It provides synthetic account information, hostname resolution and support for privilege separation.<br/>The heart of cwrap consists of three libraries you can preload to any executable.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>That one was the coolest technology I've seen so far although I may not need to use it at all,
hmmm maybe testing DHCP fits the case.</p>

<p>It evolved from the Samba project and takes advantage of the order in which
libraries are searched when resolving functions. When you preload the project libraries
to any executable they will override standard libc functions for working with sockets,
user accounts and privilege escalation.</p>

<p>The socket_wrapper library redirects networking sockets through local UNIX sockets and
gives you the ability to test applications which need privileged ports with a local developer
account.</p>

<p>The nss_wrapper library provides artificial information for user and group accounts,
network name resolution using a hosts file and loading and testing of NSS modules.</p>

<p>The uid_wrapper library allows uid switching as a normal user (e.g. fake root) and
supports user/group changing in the local thread using the syscalls (like glibc).</p>

<p>All of these wrapper libraries are controlled via environment variables and definitely
makes testing of daemons and networking applications easier.</p>

<h2>Testing Documentation</h2>

<p>That one was just scratching the surface of an entire branch of testing which I've not
even considered before. The talk also explains why it is hard to test documentation and
what possible solutions there are.</p>

<p>If you write user guides and technical articles which need to
stay current with the software this is definitely the place to start.</p>

<h2>Automation in the Foreman Infrastructure</h2>

<p>The last talk I've listened to. Definitely the best one from a general testing approach
point of view. Greg talked about starting with Foreman unit tests, then testing the merged PR,
then integration tests, then moving on to test the package build and then the resulting packages themselves.</p>

<p>These guys try to even test their own infrastructure (infra as code) and the test suites
they use to test everything else. It's all about automation and the level of confidence
you have in the entire process.</p>

<p>I like the fact that no single testing approach can make you confident enough before shipping
the code and that they've taken into account changes which get introduced at various places
(e.g. 3rd party package upgrades, distro specific issues, infrastructure changes and such)</p>

<p>If I had to attend only one session it would have been this one. There are many things for me
to take back home and apply to my work on Fedora and RHEL.</p>

<p>If you find any of these topics remotely interesting I advise you to wait until FOSDEM video
team uploads the recordings and watch the entire session stream. I'm definitely missing a lot
of stuff which can't be easily reproduced in text form.</p>

<p>You can also find my report of the first FOSDEM'14 day on Saturday
<a href="/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-1-python-stands-lightning-talks/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upstream Test Suite Status of Fedora 20]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T08:01:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/24/upstream-test-suite-status-of-fedora-20</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I've expressed my thoughts about the state of
<a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/test/2013-December/119637.html">upstream test suites in Fedora</a>
along with some other ideas. Following the response on this thread I'm starting
to analyze all SRPM packages in Fedora 20 in order to establish a baseline. Here are my initial findings.</p>

<h2>What's Inside</h2>

<p>I've found two source distributions for Fedora 20:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <code>Fedora-20-source-DVD.iso</code> file which to my knowledge contains the sources
of all packages that comprise the installation media;</li>
<li>The <code>Everything/source/SRPMS/</code> directory which appears to contain the sources
of everything else available in the Fedora 20 repositories.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are <strong>2574</strong> SRPM packages in Fedora-20 source DVD and <strong>14364</strong> SRPMs
in the Everything/ directory. 9,2G vs. 41G.</p>

<h2>Test Suite Execution In %check</h2>

<p><a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Packaging:Guidelines#Test_Suites">Fedora Packaging Guidelines</a>
state</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If the source code of the package provides a test suite,<br/>it should be executed in the %check section,<br/>whenever it is practical to do so.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>In my research I found <strong>738</strong> SRPMs on the DVD which have a %check
section and <strong>4838</strong> such packages under <code>Everything/</code>. This is <strong>28,6%</strong> and <strong>33,6%</strong>
respectively.</p>

<h2>Test Suite Existence</h2>

<p>A quick grep for either <code>test/</code> or <code>tests/</code> directories in the package sources revealed
<strong>870</strong> SRPM packages in the source DVD which are very likely to have a test suite.
This is <strong>33,8%</strong>. <strike>I wasn't able to inspect the <code>Everything/</code> directory with this script
because it takes too long to execute and my system crashed out of memory.
I will update this post later with that info.</strike></p>

<p><em>UPDATE 2014-01-02</em>:
In the <code>Everything/</code> directory only <strong>4481</strong> (<strong>31,2%</strong>) SRPM packages appear to have
test suites.</p>

<p>The scripts and raw output are available at <a href="https://github.com/atodorov/fedora-scripts">https://github.com/atodorov/fedora-scripts</a>.</p>

<p>So it looks like on average <strong>30%</strong> of the packages execute their test suites at build
time in the %check section and less than <strong>35%</strong> have test suites at all!
There's definitely room for improvement and I plan to focus on this during 2014!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
