<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RHEL | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/rhel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-24T22:05:37+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[python-libs in RHEL 7.2 broke SSL verification in s3cmd]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/11/24/python-libs-in-rhel-7.2-broke-ssl-verification-in-s3cmd/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-24T21:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/11/24/python-libs-in-rhel-7.2-broke-ssl-verification-in-s3cmd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today started with <a href="http://planet.sofiavalley.com">Planet Sofia Valley</a> being
broken again. Indeed it's been broken since last Friday when I've upgraded to
the latest RHEL 7.2. I quickly identified that I was hitting
<a href="https://github.com/s3tools/s3cmd/issues/647">Issue #647</a>. Then I tried the
git checkout without any luck. This is when I started to suspect that python-libs
has been updated in an incompatible way.</p>

<p>After series of reported bugs,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1284916">rhbz#1284916</a>,
<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1284930">rhbz#1284930</a>,
<a href="http://bugs.python.org/issue25722">Python#25722</a>, it was clear that
<code>ssl.py</code> was working according to RFC6125, that Amazon S3 was not playing
nicely with this same RFC and that my patch proposal was wrong.
This immediately had me looking upper in the stack at <code>httplib.py</code> and <code>s3cmd</code>.</p>

<p>Indeed there was a change in <code>httplib.py</code> which introduced two parameters,
<em>context</em> and <em>check_hostname</em>, to <code>HTTPSConnection.__init__</code>. The change
also supplied the logic which performs SSL hostname validation.</p>

<pre><code>if not self._context.check_hostname and self._check_hostname:
    try:
        ssl.match_hostname(self.sock.getpeercert(), server_hostname)
    except Exception:
        self.sock.shutdown(socket.SHUT_RDWR)
        self.sock.close()
        raise
</code></pre>

<p>This looks a bit doggy as I don't quite understand the intention behind
<em>not PREDICATE and PREDICATE</em>. Anyway to disable the validation you need
both parameters set to False, which is
<a href="https://github.com/s3tools/s3cmd/pull/668">PR #668</a>.</p>

<p>Notice the two try-except blocks. This is in case we're running with a
version that has a context but not the check_hostname parameter. I've found
the <em>inspect.getmembers</em> function which can be used to figure out what
parameters are there for the init method but a solution based on it
doesn't appear to be more elegant. I will describe this in more details in
my next post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated MacBook Air Drivers for RHEL 7.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/11/21/updated-macbook-air-drivers-for-rhel-7.2/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-21T11:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/11/21/updated-macbook-air-drivers-for-rhel-7.2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I've upgraded to
<a href="https://access.redhat.com/announcements/2058583">Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7.2</a>
on my MacBook Air and I decided to rebuild the wifi and backlight drivers.
Wifi broke immediately but I was able to fix the build with a
<a href="https://github.com/atodorov/wl-kmod-for-rhel7/commit/88d678a25eb702ce36f7c39471edefb65de57ad5">simple patch</a>.
I'm now using the newly built <em>kmod-wl-3.10.0-327.el7.x86_64-6.30.223.248-7.el7.x86_64</em>
and it appears to work as expected.</p>

<p>The <em>mba6x_bl</em> driver built without problems however I'm having problems when
closing the laptop lid. The screen stays on and (I think) the computer doesn't
suspend. My battery was drained as I left the computer as-is overnight. Suspending
from the Desktop menu however appears to work. See
<a href="https://github.com/patjak/mba6x_bl/issues/41">Issue #41</a>. I'd love to get some
help in debugging what's going wrong and trying to fix it. At this point I have
no idea where to look and if it's the driver to blame or something else on the system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thunderbolt to VGA adapter on Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/09/30/thunderbolt-to-vga-adapter-on-linux/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-30T11:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/09/30/thunderbolt-to-vga-adapter-on-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've previously written about my
<a href="blog/2015/05/04/thunderbolt-to-ethernet-adapter-on-linux/">Thunderbolt to Ethernet adapter working on Linux</a>
despite claims that it should not. Recently I've used my MacBook to do a presentation
and the Thunderbolt to VGA adapter worked well enough.</p>

<p>It was an Acer adapter but I have no more details b/c it wasn't mine.</p>

<p>Before the event I've tested it and it worked so on the day of the event I've
freshly rebooted my laptop to be sure no crashed processes or anything like that
was running and gave it a go.</p>

<p>First time I plugged in the MacBook everything worked like a charm. Then my computer was
unplugged and the lid closed, causing it to suspend. The second time I've plugged it in
I was told there was nothing showing on the projector so I quickly plugged the adapter out
and then back in. It worked more or less.</p>

<p>At the time I had LibreOffice Impress in presentation
mode but I did see ABRT detecting a kernel problem. When my slides popped up the text
on the first one was mostly missing but the rest were ok!</p>

<p>Mind you I'm still running <a href="/blog/categories/mac/">RHEL 7 on my MacBook Air</a>. The above is
with kernel-3.10.0-229.14.1.el7.x86_64.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip: Try F10 When Editing grub2 Menu in EFI Mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/08/14/tip-try-f10-when-editing-grub2-menu-in-efi-mode/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-14T14:06:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/08/14/tip-try-f10-when-editing-grub2-menu-in-efi-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When editing the grub2 menu (especially in EFI mode) it tells you to
press Ctrl-x to save your changes and continue the boot process.
However this doesn't work on Apple hardware
(<a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1253637">rhbz#1253637</a>)
and maybe some other platforms. If this is the case try pressing <strong>F10</strong>
instead. It works for me!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using USB to VGA Adapter on MacBook Air with Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/05/using-usb-to-vga-adapter-on-macbook-air-with-linux/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T14:02:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/05/using-usb-to-vga-adapter-on-macbook-air-with-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A quick solution for MacBook Air users running Linux who want to
use external projector is to use a USB to VGA adapter. Mine is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004AIJE9G/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B004AIJE9G&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=74W7KWXBGC7SZ5QH">Plugable UGA-165</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B004AIJE9G" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
and it works great with Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7.1.</p>

<p>After the device is plugged in the <em>udl</em> kernel module is loaded
and a new framebuffer device is created (/dev/fb1 in my case). Using
<em>mate-display-properties</em> I'm able to configure the 2nd monitor attached
to the USB video card. I was able to succeffully display an OpenOffice
presentation on the 2nd monitor and play YouTube video.</p>

<p>All USB 2.0 devices from Plugable should be well supported on Linux.
For USB 3.0 David Airlie from Red Hat is doing some reverse engineering
but I have no idea what the status is. For more info see:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://plugable.com/2012/06/21/displaylink-usb-devices-on-linux-kernel-3-4-0">http://plugable.com/2012/06/21/displaylink-usb-devices-on-linux-kernel-3-4-0</a></li>
<li><a href="http://airlied.livejournal.com/80307.html">http://airlied.livejournal.com/80307.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://airlied.livejournal.com/80516.html">http://airlied.livejournal.com/80516.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://airlied.livejournal.com/80797.html">http://airlied.livejournal.com/80797.html</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
