<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: what runs | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/what-runs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-30T13:18:50+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - Deed]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/23/what-runs-your-startup-deed/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-23T10:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/23/what-runs-your-startup-deed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/deed.jpg" alt="Deed" style="float:left; margin-right: 15px;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ideedit.com/">Deed</a> is an action-provoking platform for challenging
yourself and others and also a business solution for improved engagement by the
corresponding communities. It solves the problem of passivity by converting people
who “Like” to people who “Act. The challenge format gives businesses an effective,
fresh and low-cost solution to maintain active connection with their communities
and measure engagement.</p>

<p>Emil Stoychev explains their technical background.</p>

<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>Deed is built around Microsoft technologies plus some open source libraries.</p>

<p>Their web application and API is built with ASP.NET MVC 3 using MS SQL 2008 database engine.
Deed is hosted on a single cloud server at Rackspace and uses Akamai CDN for static files
distribution. At the moment the team is testing Windows Azure cloud platform and plans
migrating there.</p>

<p>A native Windows Phone application also exists.</p>

<p>Lots of JavaScript and CSS frameworks come to play at the  web interface layer like
jQuery, <a href="http://handlebarsjs.com/">Handlebars</a> for templates and <a href="http://lesscss.org/">Less CSS</a>.</p>

<p>IDE of choice is Microsoft Visual Studio 2012 for C# and Vim for everything else.
Source code revision control is managed with Mercurial and build scripts are written in Python.</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else?</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>The Deed team had experience with Microsoft technologies initially so it was natural<br/>for us to choose this stack. While not perfect and costly in terms of hosting fees,<br/>it serves its purpose for the moment. When you start a new project and you want to get<br/>up and running fast your best choice is to use what you already mastered.<br/>That in our case was the Microsoft stack.</p><footer><strong>Emil Stoychev</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Indeed I strongly support this! Always use technologies you are a master at and change and
adapt along the way if necessary.</p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>If you’d like to hear more from <em>Deed</em> please comment below.
I will ask them to follow this thread and reply to your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - MaistorPlus]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/08/what-runs-your-startup-maistorplus/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T12:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/08/what-runs-your-startup-maistorplus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/maistorplus.jpg" alt="MaistorPlus logo" style="float:left; margin-right: 15px;"/></p>

<p><a href="http://www.meisterplus.com/%D0%BC%D0%B0%D0%B9%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B8">MaistorPlus</a>
solves the common problem of finding a reliable builder or handyman.
An online platform that brings master craftsmen and homeowners together.</p>

<p>The process is really easy. Homeowners post jobs on the website and receive
offers from relevant tradesmen. After the job is done homeowners leave feedback
and recommendations. With this feature homeowners can compare tradesmen profiles,
offers and ratings and confidently choose who they want to hire.</p>

<p>The team is also runner up at the Start IT Smart
<a href="http://www.3challenge.com/startups/season-3/">3Challenge</a>.
<a href="http://meisterplus.com/about/team">Boris Sanchez</a> shared their technical mojo.</p>

<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>Main technologies used are PHP, Symfony 2.1 and PostgreSQL.</p>

<p>MaistorPlus is a traditional web platform developed with the
<a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony framework</a>. Web pages are rendered by Twig -
a straightforward, flexible and easy to extend templating engine, which is
integrated into the Symfony framework by default and works server-side with PHP
in order to generate dynamic content, based on data stored in the database.
Web pages also use jQuery and <a href="http://sizzlejs.com/">Sizzle.js</a> and feature modern graphics.
Everything is beautifully styled with CSS.</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>The original development team already had experience with Symfony, Zend, Spring and<br/>some other web application development frameworks. We opted for Symfony for two<br/>main reasons. First, Symfony is constantly improving, and has a strong and<br/>continuously growing community that offers 3rd party add-on components for free.<br/>Second, PHP is a bit easier to "learn as you go" then Java. The members of our<br/>design team didn't have a lot of prior programming experience, so we wanted to<br/>make sure we set a low barrier of entry for them, as we didn't have the enough<br/>development staff to have a distinct separation between design creation and design<br/>integration in our team.</p></p><p><p>For the initial prototype we used the MySQL database management system. After a<br/>while we wanted to add spatial features to the business logic, and discovered that<br/>MySQL does not have proper support for spatial indexing. We therefore decided to<br/>migrate to PostgreSQL, which supports spatial data with add-ons like PostGIS.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Boris Sanchez</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>MaistorPlus is going to organize a Beta Testing next month. You are welcome to
<a href="http://meisterplus.com/blog">subscribe</a> to their monthly newsletter or follow them on
<a href="https://www.facebook.com/MaistorPlus">Facebook</a> / <a href="https://twitter.com/MaistorPlus">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p>If you’d like to hear more from <em>MaistorPlus</em> please comment below.
I will ask them to follow this thread and reply to your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - Ucha.se]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/03/what-runs-your-startup-ucha.se/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-03T10:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/03/what-runs-your-startup-ucha.se</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/uchase.jpg" alt="Ucha.se logo" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"/></p>

<p><a href="http://ucha.se/">Ucha.se</a> makes learning fun. It is an online platform,
on which pupils and students learn and prepare for school. Pupils learn faster,
improve their results and get inspired. The platform allows students to watch
videos, take tests, ask questions and share comments. Learning is represented
with gamification components like drawings, playful narration, dashboards with
the best students, etc. It is available on the web and is extending to mobile.
Ucha.se is well recognized by the parents and teachers in Bulgaria.
In November 2012 Ucha.se was awarded as the best website in Bulgaria in the
field of Education and Science.</p>

<p>Nikolay Zheynov is leading the IT team which maintains and expands the web platform.
He shared with me some of the internals.</p>

<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>Main technologies used are PHP, MySQL, Nginx, jQuery and jQueryUI.</p>

<p>Server-side development is done with PHP 5. The main reason for choosing PHP is
that the IT team working on the platform had long experience with the language.
Ucha.se has developed their own PHP framework which is constantly expanding.
This allows flexible programming and easier application maintenance.
Nginx is the web server of choice.</p>

<p>MySQL 5 is used for the database because PHP + MySQL is like bread and butter.
While the site usage was growing the team had to optimize their DB layer and switched
from MyISAM storage engine to InnoDB.</p>

<p>On the client-side standard web technologies are used - HTML5, CSS3 and JavaScript.
The main goal when doing the website design was to match expectation from different
user groups - pupils, teachers, parents and students.
jQuery and jQueryUI are widely used on the client side.</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else?</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>True to our agile approach to incrementally enhance the product and the technology<br/>that goes along with it, we strongly believe in the scaling on demand practices.<br/>Ucha.se's own framework reflects exactly to that. It allows us to meet our growing<br/>user demands and provides at the same time, the dev-team with enough flexibility to<br/>quickly react on new business opportunities and technological (r)evolutions.</p><footer><strong>Nikolay Zheynov</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>If you’d like to hear more from <em>Ucha.se</em> please comment below.
I will ask them to follow this thread and reply to your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - Useful at Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/27/what-runs-your-startup-useful-at-night/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-27T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/27/what-runs-your-startup-useful-at-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img style="float: left; margin-right: 10px;" src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/usefulatnight.png" alt="Useful at Night logo" /></p>

<p><a href="http://usefulatnight.com/">Useful at Night</a> is a mobile guide for nightlife
empowering real time discovery of cool locations, allowing nightlife players
to identify opinion leaders. Through geo-location and data aggregation
capabilities, the application allows useful exploration of cities, places and
parties.</p>

<p><a href="http://about.me/velev">Evelin Velev</a> was kind enough to share what technologies
his team uses to run their star-up.</p>

<br/>


<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>Main technologies used are Node.js, HTML 5 and NoSQL.</p>

<p>Back-end application servers are written in Node.js and hosted at Heroku,
coupled with <a href="http://www.redistogo.com/">RedisToGo</a> for caching and
CouchDB served by <a href="https://cloudant.com/">Cloudant</a> for storage.</p>

<p>Their mobile front-end supports both iOS and Android platforms and is built using
HTML5 and a homemade UI framework called RAPID. There are some native parts developed
in Objective-C and Java respectively.</p>

<p>In addition <em>Useful at Night</em> uses MongoDB for metrics data with a custom metrics solution
written in Node.js; Amazon S3 for storing different assets; and a custom storage solution
called Divan (simple CouchDB like).</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else?</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>We chose Node.js for our application servers, because it enables us to build efficient<br/>distributed systems while sharing significant amounts of code between client and server.<br/>Things get really interesting when you couple Node.js with Redis for data structure<br/>sharing and message passing, as the two technologies play very well together.</p></p><p><p>We chose CouchDB as our main back-end because it is the most schema-less data-store that<br/>supports secondary indexing. Once you get fluent with its map-reduce views, you can<br/>compute an index out of practically anything. For comparison, even MongoDB requires<br/>that you design your documents as to enable certain indexing patterns. Put otherwise,<br/>we'd say CouchDB is a data-store that enables truly lean engineering - we have never had<br/>to re-bake or migrate our data since day one, while we're constantly experimenting with<br/>new ways to index, aggregate and query it.</p></p><p><p>We chose HTML5 as our front-end technology, because it's cross-platform and because we<br/>believe it's ... almost ready. Things are still really problematic on Android, but iOS<br/>boasts a gorgeous web presentation platform, and Windows 8 is also joining the game with<br/>a very good web engine. Obviously we're constantly running into issues and limitations,<br/>mostly related to the unfortunate fact that in spite of some recent developments,<br/>a web app is still mostly single threaded. However, we're getting there, and we're proud<br/>to say we're running a pretty graphically complex hybrid app with near-native GUI performance<br/>on the iPhone 4S and above.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>If you'd like to hear more from <em>Useful at Night</em> please comment below. I will ask them
to follow this thread and reply to your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/27/what-runs-your-startup/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-27T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/27/what-runs-your-startup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am starting a new section called
<a href="/blog/categories/what-runs/">What Runs Your Start-up</a> where I will
write about the technologies running behind some interesting
start-up companies and why they made their technological choices.
The articles will be short and to the point. Interested readers
can engage in discussion with start-up owners in the comments later.</p>

<p>I am starting with a dozen companies from the Bulgarian start-up eco-system
and will present one or two start-ups per week.
If you'd like to read about a company which is not listed here or want to
promote your own just let me know.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
