<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-24T17:18:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Software Testing Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/20/free-software-testing-books/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-20T11:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/20/free-software-testing-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There's a huge list of
<a href="https://github.com/ligurio/free-software-testing-books/blob/master/free-software-testing-books.md">free books</a>
on the topic of software testing. This will definitely be my summer reading list.
I hope you find it helpful.</p>

<h2>200 Graduation Theses About Software Testing</h2>

<p>The guys from <a href="http://qahelp.net">QAHelp</a> have compiled a list of 200
graduation theses from various universities which are freely accessible
online. The list can be found
<a href="http://qahelp.net/200-dissertatsij-po-testirovaniyu-v-svobodnoj-dostupe/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Traction: A Startup Guide to Getting Customers]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/09/30/traction-a-startup-guide-to-getting-customers/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-30T10:43:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/09/30/traction-a-startup-guide-to-getting-customers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Many entrepreneurs who build great products simply don't have a good distribution strategy.</p><footer><strong>Mark Andreessen</strong> <cite>Venture Capitalist</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00N06Y2DW/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00N06Y2DW&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=4GDHEYN66CPL7L72">Traction: A Startup Guide to Getting Customers</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00N06Y2DW" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
introduces startup founders and employees to the "Bullseye Framework,"
a five-step process successful companies use to get traction.
This framework helps founders find the marketing channel that will be key to unlocking the next stage of growth.</p>

<p>Too often, startups building a product struggle with traction once they launch.
This struggle has startups trying random tactics - some ads, a blog post or two - in an unstructured way that leads to failure.
Traction shows readers how to systematically approach marketing, and covers how successful businesses have grown through each of
the following 19 channels:</p>

<ul>
<li>Viral Marketing</li>
<li>Public Relations (PR)</li>
<li>Unconventional PR</li>
<li>Search Engine Marketing (SEM)</li>
<li>Social and Display Ads</li>
<li>Offline Ads</li>
<li>Search Engine Optimization (SEO)</li>
<li>Content Marketing</li>
<li>Email Marketing</li>
<li>Engineering as Marketing</li>
<li>Target Market Blogs</li>
<li>Business Development (BD)</li>
<li>Sales</li>
<li>Affiliate Programs</li>
<li>Existing Platforms</li>
<li>Trade Shows</li>
<li>Offline Events</li>
<li>Speaking Engagements</li>
<li>Community Building</li>
</ul>


<p>The book is very easy to read and full of practical advice which should serve as a starting point and give you
more ideas how to approach a particular distribution channel. It took me two days to read and
I already had some ideas to test even before reading the whole of it. My next steps are to apply the principles
to my current startup <a href="http://obuvki41plus.com">Obuvki 41 Plus</a> and a future one I have in mind.</p>

<p>To anyone building a startup of any kind I would recommend the following selection of books:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1591847788/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1591847788&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=IR465SOS3KA4BJLF">Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1591847788" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /> -
to learn how to make products (especially mobile apps) that customers keep using on their own without
additional external marketing (<a href="/blog/2014/01/28/book-review-january-2014/">review here</a>)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449334911/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1449334911&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=MHLGJPMJDO4FJDQB">UX for Lean Startups</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1449334911" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /> -
lean product development (<a href="/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/">review here</a>)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00N06Y2DW/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00N06Y2DW&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=AYMPCBH4MP5PC6G5">Traction: A Startup Guide to Getting Customers</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00N06Y2DW" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /> -
customer growth development</li>
</ul>


<p>Start reading right now (and also support this blog) by following the links below:</p>

<iframe style="width:120px;height:240px;" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" src="http://atodorov.org//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?ServiceVersion=20070822&OneJS=1&Operation=GetAdHtml&MarketPlace=US&source=ss&ref=ss_til&ad_type=product_link&tracking_id=atodorovorg-20&marketplace=amazon&region=US&placement=1591847788&asins=1591847788&linkId=SXJNPAOV2J4SKU4G&show_border=true&link_opens_in_new_window=true">
</iframe>




<iframe style="width:120px;height:240px;" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" src="http://atodorov.org//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?ServiceVersion=20070822&OneJS=1&Operation=GetAdHtml&MarketPlace=US&source=ss&ref=ss_til&ad_type=product_link&tracking_id=atodorovorg-20&marketplace=amazon&region=US&placement=1449334911&asins=1449334911&linkId=7UM2YUNUK5UNVPSI&show_border=true&link_opens_in_new_window=true">
</iframe>




<iframe style="width:120px;height:240px;" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" src="http://atodorov.org//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?ServiceVersion=20070822&OneJS=1&Operation=GetAdHtml&MarketPlace=US&source=ss&ref=ss_til&ad_type=product_link&tracking_id=atodorovorg-20&marketplace=amazon&region=US&placement=B00N06Y2DW&asins=B00N06Y2DW&linkId=WS2AWWLBNFAFA5PO&show_border=true&link_opens_in_new_window=true">
</iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: The 4-Hour Workweek]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/08/03/book-review-4-hour-workweek/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T11:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/08/03/book-review-4-hour-workweek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307465357/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0307465357&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=MNAE55VHLT2NVN2Z">The 4-Hour Workweek: Escape 9-5, Live Anywhere, and Join the New Rich</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0307465357" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Timothy Ferriss is one of my all time favorite books.
The basic idea is to ditch the traditional working environment
and work less utilizing more automation.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Whenever you find yourself on the side of the majority, it is time to pause and reflect.</p><footer><strong>MARK TWAIN</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The book starts with a story about the Tango World Championship semifinals in
Argentina and poses the question
<em>“What on earth would I be doing right now, if I hadn’t left my job and the U.S. over a year ago?”</em>
Can you answer this? Keep reading!</p>

<h2>Step 1: Definition</h2>

<p>Tim defines two groups of people. The Deferrers, those who save it all for the
end only to find that life has passed them by and the New Rich.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>* The employee who rearranges his schedule and negotiates a remote work agreement<br/>  to achieve 90% of the results in one-tenth of the time, which frees him to<br/>  practice cross-country skiing and take road trips with his family two weeks per<br/>  month.</p></p><p><ul><br/><li><p>The business owner who eliminates the least profitable customers and projects,<br/>outsources all operations entirely, and travels the world collecting rare<br/>documents, all while working remotely on a website to showcase her own<br/>illustration work.</p></li><br/><li><p>The student who elects to risk it all—which is nothing—to establish an online<br/>video rental service that delivers $5,000 per month in income from a small niche<br/>of Blu-ray aficionados, a two-hour-per-week side project that allows him to work<br/>full-time as an animal rights lobbyist.</p></blockquote></p></li>
</ul>


<p>The possibilities are endless. What defines the New Rich is their unrestricted mobility
and availability of free time! Money alone doesn't count anymore. Its practical value is
multiplied by the <em>what</em>, <em>when</em>, <em>where</em> and with <em>whom</em> you do what you do.</p>

<p>From that point of view earning less money but spending far less time on that is
much more powerful than working 80 hours per week for a million dollars.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Elimination</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>One does not accumulate but eliminate.<br/>It is not daily increase but daily decrease.<br/>The height of cultivation always runs to simplicity.</p><footer><strong>BRUCE LEE</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>In this chapter Tim talks about developing selective ignorance of information,
the 80-20 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">Pareto principle</a>,
gives tips for faster reading and battling interruption like checking your e-mail
and smart phone.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Automation</h2>

<p>Outsourcing and technical automation are the keys here but there is more.
Tim talks about income autopilot - designing your income sources in such a way
so that they don't consume much of your time and continue to produce income
even after the initial time investment.</p>

<p>Think about the following: working a 9-to-5 job yields an income only during
office hours. Having written a book yields income whenever a copy is sold, which
is while you're asleep and long after the initial time investment required to
write the book.</p>

<p>Then you can diversify your income streams and voila - you're making money
automatically :)</p>

<p>Tim also refers to the business management side of things. Why become the
manager when you can be the owner of the business ? It's kind of hard to
let virtual assistants run your business and resolve issues for you but that
frees up your time which is more valuable.</p>

<p>In between he also mentions why as a business you should keep prices high!
Counter intuitive, isn't it?</p>

<p>This is easier said than done but I've been working on it for the last couple
of years and its starting to take shape nicely so there's truth to it.</p>

<h2>Step 4: Liberation</h2>

<p>This is the chapter which helps you escape the 9-5 office hours through some
interesting techniques. This is not only for freelancers like myself but also
for the regular employee. One of the principles is to ask for forgiveness,
not a permission (which will be denied anyway).</p>

<p>Another one boils down to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Increase company investment into you so that the loss is greater if you quit,
e.g. corporate training;</li>
<li>Prove increased output offsite - call in sick Tuesday to Thursday but continue
working. Produce more and leave some sort of digital trail, emails, etc;</li>
<li>Prepare the quantifiable business benefit - you need to present remote working
as a good business decision and not a personal perk, for example you've managed to
bill more hours to your company's customers. As explanation use removal of commute
and fewer distractions from the office noise;</li>
<li>Propose a revocable trial period - plan everything that will be said but play it
cool and casual. You want to avoid the impression that remote working will be something
permanent (for now). Find a relaxed afternoon and give it a shot!</li>
<li>Expand remote time by making sure you're most productive on your days out of the
office and if need be lower the productivity inside the office a bit. Then give it
a shot for a longer trial period or more days working remotely;</li>
</ul>


<p>There's also another one called the hourglass approach, so named because you use a
long proof-of-concept up front to get a short remote agreement and then negotiate
back up to full-time out of the office.</p>

<p>I personally had it easier in terms of remote working. Before I became a contractor
I've been working with folks in the US to whom it doesn't really matter whether I was
based in Czech Republic or in Bulgaria. Also I've been sick at that time and had an
important project to manage which all just played nicely in proving that I
can be productive in any location.</p>

<p>Then comes one of my favorite sections <em>Killing Your Job</em>. Boy you just have to read
this. Lots of people need to read this! Everything you are afraid of and keeps you from
quitting your job is total bulshit. There are always options. It might be emotionally
difficult, but you won’t starve!</p>

<h2>Extended edition</h2>

<p>This extended edition of the book completes with blog articles and bonus sections
like <em>Killing Your BlackBerry</em>.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I’m a 37-year-old Subway franchisee owning and operating 13 stores.<br/>Been doing this for seven years. Prior to reading 4HWW I was KING at W4W<br/>(translate: work for work’s sake)<br/>...<br/>Crunched my “always open” workweek into four days and 20 hours. I immediately<br/>began taking Mondays OFF, giving me a nice three-day weekend.<br/>Tuesday to Friday I work 11 A.M.–4 P.M. (20 hours per week).<br/>...<br/>I was forced to appraise everything through the 80/20 filter and found that<br/>50% of the 80% was pure crap and the other 50% of the 80% could be done by someone<br/>on my payroll.<br/>...<br/>I still carry portable e-mail but I’ve killed “auto-sync”.<br/>Now it’s on a Tues–Fri, 11 A.M.–4 P.M. schedule.<br/>...<br/>My e-mail autoresponder eliminated 50% of my e-mail within two weeks as people sending<br/>me meaningless crap got fed up looking at my autoresponder and stopped including me.</p><footer><strong>ANDREW</strong> <cite>Self-employed in the UK</cite></footer></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: How to Win Friends]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/07/19/book-review-how-to-win-friends/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T18:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/07/19/book-review-how-to-win-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0091906350/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0091906350&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=Q2DBNO4UJBZ6HQX2">How to Win Friends &amp; Influence People</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0091906350" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Dale Carnegie teaches you how to deal with people. The book briefly explains
some easy to use principles, why and how they work and then provides tons of
real life examples behind those principles. This book is a must for everyone but
especially parents and teachers and folks in sales, management or business leaders.</p>

<p>I will only highlight the key points. What follows are direct quotes from the book.</p>

<h2>Part One: Fundamental Techniques in Handling People</h2>

<p><em>'If You Want to Gather Honey, Don't Kick Over the Beehive'</em> - PRINCIPLE 1: Don't criticise, condemn or complain.</p>

<p><em>The Big Secret of Dealing with People</em> - PRINCIPLE 2: Give honest and sincere appreciation.</p>

<p><em>'He Who Can Do This Has the Whole World with Him. He Who Cannot Walks a Lonely Way'</em> -
PRINCIPLE 3: Arouse in the other person an eager want.</p>

<h2>Part Two: Six Ways to Make People Like You</h2>

<p><em>Do This and You'll Be Welcome Anywhere</em> - PRINCIPLE 1: Become genuinely interested in other people.</p>

<p><em>A Simple Way to Make a Good First Impression</em> - PRINCIPLE 2: Smile.</p>

<p><em>If You Don't Do This, You Are Headed for Trouble</em> - PRINCIPLE 3:
Remember that a person's name is to that person the sweetest and most important sound in any language.</p>

<p><em>An Easy Way to Become a Good Conversationalist</em> - PRINCIPLE 4: Be a good listener.
Encourage others to talk about themselves.</p>

<p><em>How to Interest People</em> - PRINCIPLE 5: Talk in terms of the other person's interests.</p>

<p><em>How to Make People Like You Instantly</em> - PRINCIPLE 6: Make the other person feel important – and do it sincerely.</p>

<h2>Part Three: How to Win People to Your Way of Thinking</h2>

<p><em>You Can't Win an Argument</em> - PRINCIPLE 1: The only way to get the best of an argument is to avoid it.</p>

<p><em>A Sure Way of Making Enemies – and How to Avoid It</em> - PRINCIPLE 2: Show respect for the other person's opinions.
Never say, 'You're wrong'.</p>

<p><em>If You're Wrong, Admit It</em> - PRINCIPLE 3: If you are wrong, admit it quickly and emphatically.</p>

<p><em>A Drop of Honey</em> - PRINCIPLE 4: Begin in a friendly way.</p>

<p><em>The Secret of Socrates</em> - PRINCIPLE 5: Get the other person saying 'yes, yes' immediately.</p>

<p><em>The Safety Valve in Handling Complaints</em> - PRINCIPLE 6: Let the other person do a great deal of the talking.</p>

<p><em>How to Get Cooperation</em> - PRINCIPLE 7: Let the other person feel that the idea is his or hers.</p>

<p><em>A Formula That Will Work Wonders for You</em> - PRINCIPLE 8: Try honestly to see things from the other person's point of view.</p>

<p><em>What Everybody Wants</em> - PRINCIPLE 9: Be sympathetic with the other person's ideas and desires.</p>

<p><em>An Appeal That Everybody Likes</em> - PRINCIPLE 10: Appeal to the nobler motives.</p>

<p><em>The Movies Do It. TV Does It. Why Don't You Do It?</em> - PRINCIPLE 11: Dramatise your ideas.</p>

<p><em>When Nothing Else Works, Try This</em> - PRINCIPLE 12: Throw down a challenge.</p>

<h2>Part Four: Be a Leader: How to Change People Without Giving Offense or Arousing Resentment</h2>

<p><em>If You Must Find Fault, This Is the Way to Begin</em> - PRINCIPLE 1: Begin with praise and honest appreciation.</p>

<p><em>How to Criticise – and Not Be Hated for It</em> - PRINCIPLE 2: Call attention to people's mistakes indirectly.</p>

<p><em>Talk About Your Own Mistakes First</em> - PRINCIPLE 3: Talk about your own mistakes before criticising the other person.</p>

<p><em>No One Likes to Take Orders</em> - PRINCIPLE 4: Ask questions instead of giving direct orders.</p>

<p><em>Let the Other Person Save Face</em> - PRINCIPLE 5: Let the other person save face.</p>

<p><em>How to Spur People On to Success</em> - PRINCIPLE 6: Praise the slightest improvement and
praise every improvement. Be 'hearty in your approbation and lavish in your praise'.</p>

<p><em>Give a Dog a Good Name</em> - PRINCIPLE 7: Give the other person a fine reputation to live up to.</p>

<p><em>Make the Fault Seem Easy to Correct</em> - PRINCIPLE 8: Use encouragement. Make the fault seem easy to correct.</p>

<p><em>Making People Glad to Do What You Want</em> - PRINCIPLE 9: Make the other person happy about doing the thing you suggest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Want to Be a Robot - Book Review: The Singularity Is Near]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/19/i-want-to-be-a-robot-book-review-the-singularity-is-near/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T21:43:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/19/i-want-to-be-a-robot-book-review-the-singularity-is-near</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've just finished reading
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000QCSA7C/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B000QCSA7C&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=PY5X54XVJXYLZBIH">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B000QCSA7C" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
and all I have to say is "I want to be a robot"!</p>

<p>This is one of the books that took me the longest time to read. It's a hard
to read book because it is full of technical and scientific details, quotes
a great deal of facts and research and leads your mind into fields which
deserve a separate books for themselves.</p>

<p>The purely technical side of the book makes it a bit hard to follow as you need
to have a good deal of understanding of computing technology and concepts and
keep in mind what's been said in previous chapters.</p>

<p>Ray Kurzweil starts with historical data about evolution and technological
progress. He postulates his theory of technology evolution called
"The Law of Accelerating Returns" and lists a great deal of examples to prove
that evolutionary processes are indeed not linear but exponential.</p>

<p>The next two chapters explain how much is the computational capacity of the
human brain, how to achieve that and how to reverse engineer the brain itself.
Think about 3-D molecular computing, quantum computing, brain imaging and scanning :)</p>

<p>Increased computing capacity and understanding of the human brain
(and general progress of science and technology in the mean time)
will lead to the three revolutions which will make the Singularity possible:
Genetics, Nanotechnology and Robotics (Strong AI). Ray gives a lot of
examples and current research which is well under way currently or
will become a reality in the next 10 to 30 years.</p>

<p>Following in the book is a list of impacts caused by the advancement of
technology and the Singularity itself. On the human body and brain, on
longevity, on warfare, on work and learning and play, on the Cosmos.</p>

<p>Because the Singularity is not a single event but rather many events which
happen in parallel and gradually over time we will have a hard time defining
what a human means. What is human, what is consciousness and where the line is
are questions which need to be taken into consideration. Ultimately the human
race will become (predominantly) non-biological.</p>

<p>How do you deal with dangers and shortcomings in technology? I myself as a QA
engineer have seen software fail in spectacular ways. How about machine failures?
Now how about nanobots in your blood stream or strong AI gone wild? Ray explains
some of the possible threats and proposals to overcome them. His point is
that benefits from advanced technology will be far greater than dangers and
we will be able to first design our defense systems before anything else that
may threaten our existence.</p>

<p>The last chapter contains examples of criticism and explanations why they
are incorrect which is the first of its kind I've seen in a book.</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Human Centrality. A common view is that science has consistently been correcting our overly inflated view of our<br/>own significance. Stephen Jay Gould said, "The most important scientific revolutions all include, as their only<br/>common feature, the dethronement of human arrogance from one pedestal after another of previous convictions about<br/>our centrality in the cosmos."</p></p><p><p>But it turns out that we are central, after all. Our ability to create models-virtual realities-in our brains, combined<br/>with our modest-looking thumbs, has been sufficient to usher in another form of evolution: technology. That<br/>development enabled the persistence of the accelerating pace that started with biological evolution. It will continue<br/>until the entire universe is at our fingertips.</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
