<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-18T23:56:11+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: UX for Lean Startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T10:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I've finished reading <a href="http://amzn.to/1fi1KeE">UX for Lean Startups</a>
and strongly recommend this book to anyone who is <strong>OR</strong> wants to be an
entrepreneur. Here is a short review of the book.</p>

<p>This book is for anyone who is creating a product/service or is considering the
idea of doing so. It talks about validation, interaction design and subsequent
product measurement and iteration. The book demonstrates some techniques and tools
to validate, design and measure your business ideas and products.
Its goal is to teach you how to design products that deliver fantastic user
experience, e.g. ones that are intuitive and easy to use.
It has nothing to do with visual design.</p>

<p>The author Laura Klein summarizes the book as follows:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>User research</p></p><p><pre><code>Listen to your users. All the time. I mean it.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>Validation</p></p><p><pre><code>When you make assumptions or create hypotheses,<br/>test them before spending lots of time building products around them.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>Design</p></p><p><pre><code>Iterate. Iterate. Iterate.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Early Validation</h2>

<p>This chapter helped me a lot to understand what exactly is validation and how
to go about it. The flow is validating the problem you are trying to solve,
then the market and then the product.</p>

<p>I will also add that by using some of these research techniques around a
vague idea/area of interest you may come around a particular trend/pattern or problem
and develop your business from there.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>You’ll know that you’ve validated a problem when you start to hear<br/>particular groups of people complaining about something specific.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Your goal in validating your market is to begin to narrow down the<br/>group of people who will want their problems solved badly enough to buy<br/>your product. Your secondary goal is to understand exactly why they’re<br/>interested so you can find other markets that might be similarly motivated.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>You’ll know that you’ve successfully validated your market when you can<br/>accurately predict that a particular type of person will have a specific<br/>problem and that the problem will be severe enough that that person is<br/>interested in purchasing a solution.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Just because you have discovered a real problem and have a group of people<br/>willing to pay you to solve their problem, that doesn’t necessarily mean that<br/>your product is the right solution.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>You’ll know that you’ve validated your product when a large percentage of<br/>your target market offers to pay you money to solve their problem.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>User Research</h2>

<p>Next few chapters talk about user research, the various kinds of it and when/how
to perform it. It talks how to properly run surveys, how to ask good questions,
etc.</p>

<h2>Qualitative vs. Quantitative Research</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Quantitative research is about measuring what real people are actually<br/>doing with your product. It doesn’t involve speaking with specific humans.<br/>It’s about the data in aggregate. It should always be statistically significant.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Quantitative research tells you <strong>what</strong> your problem is. Qualitative<br/>research tells you <strong>why</strong> you have that problem.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>If you want to measure something that exists, like traffic or revenue or how<br/>many people click on a particular button, then you want quantitative data.<br/>If you want to know why you lose people out of your purchase funnel or<br/>why people all leave once they hit a specific page, or why people seem not<br/>to click that button, then you need qualitative.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Part Two: Design</h2>

<p>The second part of this book talks about design - everything from building a
prototype to figuring out when you don’t want one. It assumes you have validated
the initial idea and now move on to designing the product and validating that
design before you start building it. It talks about diagrams, sketches, wireframes,
prototypes and of course MVPs.</p>

<p>I think you can safely skip some of these steps when it comes to small applications
because it may be easier/faster to build the application instead of a prototype.
Definitely not to be skipped if you're building a more complex product!</p>

<h2>Part Three: Product</h2>

<p>This section talks about metrics and measuring the product once it is out of the door.
Supposedly based on these metrics you will refine your design and update the product
accordingly.  Most of the time it focuses on A/B testing and which metrics are
important and which are so called "vanity metrics".</p>

<p>I particularly liked the examples of A/B testing and explanations what it is good for
and what it does poorly. Definitely a mistake I've happened to made myself. I'm sure you too.</p>

<p>Let me know if you have read this book and what your thoughts are. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tip: Save Money on Amazon - Buy Used Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/01/31/tip-save-money-on-amazon-buy-used-books/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-31T22:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/01/31/tip-save-money-on-amazon-buy-used-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like to buy books, the real ones, printed on paper. This however comes at
a certain price when buying from Amazon. The book price itself is
usually bearable but many times shipping costs to Bulgaria
will double the price. Especially if you are making a single book order.</p>

<p>To save money I started buying used books when available. For books that are
not so popular I look for items that have been owned by a library.</p>

<p>This is how I got a hardcover 1984 edition of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/190676820X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=190676820X&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">The Gentlemen's Clubs of London</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=190676820X" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Anthony Lejeune for $10. This is my best deal so far.
The book was brand new I dare to say. There was no edge wear, no damaged pages,
with nice and vibrant colors. The second page had the library sign and no other marks.</p>

<p>Let me know if you had an experience buying used books online? Did you score a great
deal like I did?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[StartUP Talk#5 - book list]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/01/30/startup-talk-5-book-list/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T16:14:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/01/30/startup-talk-5-book-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I have visited an interesting talk by
<a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/tpanayotov">Teodor Panayotov</a> held at
<a href="http://www.betahaus.bg/">betahaus Sofia</a>. He was talking about his
path to success and all the companies he had worked in or founded.</p>

<p>I'm writing this post as a personal note to not forget all the good books
Teodor mentioned in his presentation.</p>

<p>I intend to read the these four as a start:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307465357/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0307465357&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">The 4-Hour Workweek: Escape 9-5, Live Anywhere, and Join the New Rich (Expanded and Updated)</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0307465357" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0887307280/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0887307280&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">The E-Myth Revisited: Why Most Small Businesses Don't Work and What to Do About It</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0887307280" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1422121100/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1422121100&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Mastering the Hype Cycle: How to Choose the Right Innovation at the Right Time (Gartner)</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1422121100" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1599180413/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1599180413&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Business Models Made Easy</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1599180413" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p>The rest he recommended are:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1591842719/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1591842719&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">How to Get Rich: One of the World's Greatest Entrepreneurs Shares His Secrets</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1591842719" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451614217/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1451614217&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Abundance: The Future Is Better Than You Think</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1451614217" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143037889/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143037889&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0143037889" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1440428433/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1440428433&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">The Law Of Success: Napoleon Hill</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1440428433" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>

<p>If you happen to read any of these <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/review/list/16191345-alexander-todorov?shelf=to-read">before me</a>,
please share your thoughts on the book.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
