<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-12T23:37:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Want to Be a Robot - Book Review: The Singularity Is Near]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/19/i-want-to-be-a-robot-book-review-the-singularity-is-near/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T21:43:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/19/i-want-to-be-a-robot-book-review-the-singularity-is-near</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've just finished reading
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000QCSA7C/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B000QCSA7C&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=PY5X54XVJXYLZBIH">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B000QCSA7C" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
and all I have to say is "I want to be a robot"!</p>

<p>This is one of the books that took me the longest time to read. It's a hard
to read book because it is full of technical and scientific details, quotes
a great deal of facts and research and leads your mind into fields which
deserve a separate books for themselves.</p>

<p>The purely technical side of the book makes it a bit hard to follow as you need
to have a good deal of understanding of computing technology and concepts and
keep in mind what's been said in previous chapters.</p>

<p>Ray Kurzweil starts with historical data about evolution and technological
progress. He postulates his theory of technology evolution called
"The Law of Accelerating Returns" and lists a great deal of examples to prove
that evolutionary processes are indeed not linear but exponential.</p>

<p>The next two chapters explain how much is the computational capacity of the
human brain, how to achieve that and how to reverse engineer the brain itself.
Think about 3-D molecular computing, quantum computing, brain imaging and scanning :)</p>

<p>Increased computing capacity and understanding of the human brain
(and general progress of science and technology in the mean time)
will lead to the three revolutions which will make the Singularity possible:
Genetics, Nanotechnology and Robotics (Strong AI). Ray gives a lot of
examples and current research which is well under way currently or
will become a reality in the next 10 to 30 years.</p>

<p>Following in the book is a list of impacts caused by the advancement of
technology and the Singularity itself. On the human body and brain, on
longevity, on warfare, on work and learning and play, on the Cosmos.</p>

<p>Because the Singularity is not a single event but rather many events which
happen in parallel and gradually over time we will have a hard time defining
what a human means. What is human, what is consciousness and where the line is
are questions which need to be taken into consideration. Ultimately the human
race will become (predominantly) non-biological.</p>

<p>How do you deal with dangers and shortcomings in technology? I myself as a QA
engineer have seen software fail in spectacular ways. How about machine failures?
Now how about nanobots in your blood stream or strong AI gone wild? Ray explains
some of the possible threats and proposals to overcome them. His point is
that benefits from advanced technology will be far greater than dangers and
we will be able to first design our defense systems before anything else that
may threaten our existence.</p>

<p>The last chapter contains examples of criticism and explanations why they
are incorrect which is the first of its kind I've seen in a book.</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Human Centrality. A common view is that science has consistently been correcting our overly inflated view of our<br/>own significance. Stephen Jay Gould said, "The most important scientific revolutions all include, as their only<br/>common feature, the dethronement of human arrogance from one pedestal after another of previous convictions about<br/>our centrality in the cosmos."</p></p><p><p>But it turns out that we are central, after all. Our ability to create models-virtual realities-in our brains, combined<br/>with our modest-looking thumbs, has been sufficient to usher in another form of evolution: technology. That<br/>development enabled the persistence of the accelerating pace that started with biological evolution. It will continue<br/>until the entire universe is at our fingertips.</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Last 3 Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/13/book-review-last-3-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello folks, this is my book list for the past 3 months. It ranges from
tech and start-up related to Japanese and kid stories. Here's my quick review.</p>

<h2>Lean UX</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449311652/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1449311652&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=JNQIKHJJXU3KJ33H">Lean UX: Applying Lean Principles to Improve User Experience</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=1449311652" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
is the second book I read on the subject after first reading
<a href="/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/">UX for Lean Startups</a>.</p>

<p>It is published before <em>UX for Lean Startups</em> and is much more about principles than
any practical methods. Honestly I'm not sure if I took any real value out of it.
Maybe if I had read these two books in reverse order it would have been better.</p>

<h2>The Hacienda - How Not to Run a Club</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00DEKLESK/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00DEKLESK&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FOMGYFQW4BHGPPOL">The Hacienda: How Not to Run a Club</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00DEKLESK" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Peter Hook is one of my favorites. It covers a great deal of music and clubland history,
depicts crazy parties and describes the adventure of owning one of the most
popular nightclubs in the world. All of that while struggling to make a buck and
pouring countless pounds into a black hole.</p>

<p>The irony is The Hacienda became a legendary place only after it had closed down
and later on being demolished.</p>

<p>A must read for anyone who is considering business in the entertainment industry
or wants to read a piece of history. My favorite quote of the book:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Years after, Tony Wilson found himself sitting opposite Madonna at dinner.</p></p><p><p>‘I eventually plucked up the courage to look across the table to Madonna and ask,<br/>“Are you aware that the first place you appeared outside of New York was our club in Manchester?”</p></p><p><p>‘She gave me an ice-cold stare and said, “My memory seems to have wiped that.”’</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Simple Science Experiments</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0713428945/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0713428945&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=HU6TVCNR6DG67EFG">Simple Science Experiments</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0713428945" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Hans Jürgen Press is a very old book listing 200 experiments which you can
do at home using household materials. It is great for teaching basic science
to children. The book is very popular and is available in many languages
and editions - just search for it.</p>

<p>I used to have this as a kid and was able to purchase the 1987 Bulgarian edition
at an antique bookstore in Varna two months ago.</p>

<h2>Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</h2>

<p>Decided to experiment a little bit and found
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0140317201/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0140317201&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=FDHOPXQCZPMYCAA2">Ronia, the Robber's Daughter</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0140317201" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />.
It's a child's book telling the story of two kids whose fathers are rival
robbers. The book is an easy read (2-3 hrs before bed time) with stories
of magic woods, dwarfs and scary creatures mixed with human emotions
and the good vs. bad theme.</p>

<h2>Japanese Short Stories</h2>

<p>I've managed to find a 1973 compilation of Japanese short stories
translated into Bulgarian. Also one of my favorite books.</p>

<p>If I'm not mistaken these are classic
Japanese authors, nothing modern or cutting edge. Most of the action happens
during the early 1900s as far as I can tell.
What impresses me most is the detailed description of nature and
surrounding details in all of the stories.</p>

<h2>The Singularity Is Near</h2>

<p>I've also started
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143037889/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143037889&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20&linkId=BKMQ47NQEXNTDDRR">The Singularity Is Near: When Humans Transcend Biology</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0143037889" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
by Ray Kurzweil.</p>

<p>It's a bit hard to read because the book is full of so many technical details
about genetics, nanotechnology, robotics and AI.</p>

<p>Ray depicts a bright future where humans will transcend our biological
limitations and essentially become pure intelligence. Definitely a good
read and I will tell you more about it when I finish it.</p>

<hr />

<p>What have you been reading since January ? I'd love to see your book list
or connect on
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/16191345-alexander-todorov">Goodreads</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - January 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/01/28/book-review-january-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T23:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/01/28/book-review-january-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sorry for not being able to write anything this month. I've been very sick
and hardly even touched a computer in the last few weeks. I promise to make
it up to you next month. Until then here's the books I've managed to read in
January.</p>

<h2>Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1erRrnb">Hooked</a> is an ebook for Kindle which I luckily got for
free on NYE (it's paid now). The book describes the so called "Hook Model"
which is a guide to building products people can’t put down.</p>

<p>The book goes through a cycle of <strong>trigger</strong>, <strong>action</strong>, <strong>variable reward</strong> and
<strong>investment</strong> to describe how one can design a product which users keep using
without you doing anything (pretty much). There are plenty of examples with products
like Instagram and Pinterest.</p>

<p>I really find the book interesting and will strongly recommend it as a must read
to anyone who is building a product. If you're thinking about a mobile app or an
online service this book is definitely for you.</p>

<h2>CyberJoly Drim</h2>

<p><a href="http://hell.pl/nina/carramba.htm">CyberJoly Drim</a> is a 1998 cyber punk story by
Polish writer Antonina Liedtke. One I've heard about through the years but found
just recently. It's about a love story although everything else is fiction. PDF format
is around 30 pages.</p>

<p>I found it hard to read especially b/c my Polish is totally rusty (not to mention I hardly
understand it) and Google translate didn't manage well neither. Anyway, not a bad read
before bed time if you like this kind of stuff.</p>

<h2>The First in Bulgarian Internet</h2>

<p>Last a book about
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13398350">Bulgarian Internet pioneers</a>. The book
compiles a great deal with historical data as well as interviews and web site descriptions.
It's said to mention about 400 persons.</p>

<p>The events start around 1989 with the BBS systems at the time and the first one to appear in
the country with accounts of first time logging into the network and pretty much seeing a
computer. Then it goes to tell the story of first companies and Internet providers, how they
started business, how they grew and formed the country's backbone infrastructure. There's
lots of personal memories and stories as well. This goes to about 2002 when the book
was written.</p>

<p>The second part of the book mostly describes various websites, some of the first ones and
some milestone or famous ones. It's organized by date of website launch but isn't that much
interesting. I find the local contents at the time a bit boring.</p>

<p>The book isn't what I initially expected - I wanted more personal stories and more news from
the kitchen. It's not that, it looks to me the people who were interviewed had chosen their
words very carefully and didn't reveal any sensational stories.</p>

<p>The nice thing about all of that is I've started using the web in early 1998 and remember
most of the events and websites described in the book. It's good to remember the history.
I own the book and can give it to you if you like. It's on the <a href="/give-away/">Give Away</a>
list.</p>

<p>I hope you find something interesting to read in my library. If not please share what did you
read this month.</p>

<hr />

<p>PS: I'm currently in Milan and will be visiting FOSDEM at the end of the week. Catch
you there if you're coming.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review of 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/01/02/book-review-of-2013/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T10:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/01/02/book-review-of-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy New Year everyone! I was able to complete reading a few books in the last
days so this first post will be a quick review of
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/16191345-alexander-todorov?read_at=2013&amp;view=covers">all twelve books I've read in 2013</a>.</p>

<h2>Technical Blogging</h2>

<p>I've started the year with
<a href="http://amzn.to/1a2QySD">Technical Blogging: Turn Your Expertise into a Remarkable Online Presence</a>
by Antonio Cangiano. This is the book which prompted me to start this blog. It is
targeted primarily at technical blogging but could be useful to non-tech bloggers as well.
I strongly recommend this book to anyone who is writing for the web.</p>

<h2>The 4-Hour Workweek</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1ivu2q4">The 4-Hour Workweek: Escape 9-5, Live Anywhere, and Join the New Rich</a>
by Timothy Ferriss. This book I found at a local
<a href="/blog/2013/01/30/startup-talk-5-book-list/">start-up event</a> and is one of my
all time favorites. The basic idea is to ditch the traditional working space and
work less utilizing more automation. This is something I've been doing to an extent
during the last 5+ years and I am still changing my life and working habits to
reach the moment where I work only a few hours a week.</p>

<p>A must read for any entrepreneur, freelancer or work from home folks.</p>

<h2>The E-Myth Revisited</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1d0j5ee">The E-Myth Revisited: Why Most Small Businesses Don't Work and What to Do About It</a>
by Michael Gerber is the second book I've found at the same start-up event mentioned
previously. I found this one particularly hard to read. What I took from it was
that you should think about your business as a franchise and document processes
so that others can do it for you in the same way you would do it yourself.</p>

<h2>Culture and Wine</h2>

<p>Next two books are in Bulgarian and can be found at my
<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/16191345-alexander-todorov?read_at=2013&amp;view=covers">Goodreads list</a>.
They are about culture and religion and wine tasting 101.</p>

<h2>Accelerando</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/19Ctnk8">Accelerando (Singularity)</a> by Charles Stross is also one
of my favorites. I've heard about it at a local CloudFoundry conference a few years
back and finally had the time to read it. This is a fiction book where events start
in the near future and drive forward to dismantling the planets in the Solar system,
uploading lobsters minds on the Internet, space travel, aliens and family
relationships. I will definitely recommend it, the book is a very relaxing read.</p>

<h2>DevOps</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1eXk3JN">What Is DevOps?</a> by Mike Loukides and
<a href="http://amzn.to/19KobFn">Building a DevOps Culture</a> by Mandi Walls are two short
free books for Kindle. They just touch base on the topic of DevOps and what it
takes to create a DevOps organization. Definitely worth reading even if you're
not deeply interested in this topic.</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1dVvQmE">DevOps for Developers</a> by Michael Huttermann is a
practical books about DevOps. It talks about processes and tools and lists
lots of examples. The tools part is Ruby centric though.
I found it a bit hard to read at times and it took me a while
to complete it. I'm not sure if the book is really helpful if one decides to
change an exiting organization to a DevOps like structure but it is definitely
a starting point.</p>

<p>The days of waterfall software development are gone and knowingly or not most of
us work in a DevOps like environment these days. I think it's worth at least skimming
through this book and taking some essentials from it.</p>

<h2>UX For Lean Startups</h2>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1fi1KeE">UX for Lean Startups</a> by Laura Klein is a very good book
about designing user experience and validation which I've
<a href="/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/">reviewed previously</a>.
I strongly recommend this book to everyone who is building a product of some sort.</p>

<h2>Bulgarian Comics</h2>

<p>At the end of the year I've managed to read two comics books, both in Bulgarian.
The first one is a brief history of the comics arts in the country in the past 150
years with lots of references to good old stories which I've read when I was a kid.</p>

<p>The second one is a special edition (ebook only, print edition is out of stock) of
the popular Daga (Rainbow) magazine which ceased to exist 20 years ago. There are
some new episodes of the old stories drawn by the original artists.</p>

<p>Both books seem to be a turning point in Bulgarian comics art and market. Hopefully
we'll see more cool stuff in the future. These books are not available on Amazon
but there are some <a href="http://amzn.to/19Cw6tV">free comics books for Kindle</a> which
you may give a try.</p>

<p>I hope you find something interesting to read in my list. Also feel free to comment
and share your favorite books in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: UX for Lean Startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T10:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/12/09/book-review-ux-for-lean-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I've finished reading <a href="http://amzn.to/1fi1KeE">UX for Lean Startups</a>
and strongly recommend this book to anyone who is <strong>OR</strong> wants to be an
entrepreneur. Here is a short review of the book.</p>

<p>This book is for anyone who is creating a product/service or is considering the
idea of doing so. It talks about validation, interaction design and subsequent
product measurement and iteration. The book demonstrates some techniques and tools
to validate, design and measure your business ideas and products.
Its goal is to teach you how to design products that deliver fantastic user
experience, e.g. ones that are intuitive and easy to use.
It has nothing to do with visual design.</p>

<p>The author Laura Klein summarizes the book as follows:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>User research</p></p><p><pre><code>Listen to your users. All the time. I mean it.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>Validation</p></p><p><pre><code>When you make assumptions or create hypotheses,<br/>test them before spending lots of time building products around them.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>Design</p></p><p><pre><code>Iterate. Iterate. Iterate.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Early Validation</h2>

<p>This chapter helped me a lot to understand what exactly is validation and how
to go about it. The flow is validating the problem you are trying to solve,
then the market and then the product.</p>

<p>I will also add that by using some of these research techniques around a
vague idea/area of interest you may come around a particular trend/pattern or problem
and develop your business from there.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>You’ll know that you’ve validated a problem when you start to hear<br/>particular groups of people complaining about something specific.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Your goal in validating your market is to begin to narrow down the<br/>group of people who will want their problems solved badly enough to buy<br/>your product. Your secondary goal is to understand exactly why they’re<br/>interested so you can find other markets that might be similarly motivated.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>You’ll know that you’ve successfully validated your market when you can<br/>accurately predict that a particular type of person will have a specific<br/>problem and that the problem will be severe enough that that person is<br/>interested in purchasing a solution.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Just because you have discovered a real problem and have a group of people<br/>willing to pay you to solve their problem, that doesn’t necessarily mean that<br/>your product is the right solution.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>You’ll know that you’ve validated your product when a large percentage of<br/>your target market offers to pay you money to solve their problem.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>User Research</h2>

<p>Next few chapters talk about user research, the various kinds of it and when/how
to perform it. It talks how to properly run surveys, how to ask good questions,
etc.</p>

<h2>Qualitative vs. Quantitative Research</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Quantitative research is about measuring what real people are actually<br/>doing with your product. It doesn’t involve speaking with specific humans.<br/>It’s about the data in aggregate. It should always be statistically significant.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>Quantitative research tells you <strong>what</strong> your problem is. Qualitative<br/>research tells you <strong>why</strong> you have that problem.</p></p><p><p>...</p></p><p><p>If you want to measure something that exists, like traffic or revenue or how<br/>many people click on a particular button, then you want quantitative data.<br/>If you want to know why you lose people out of your purchase funnel or<br/>why people all leave once they hit a specific page, or why people seem not<br/>to click that button, then you need qualitative.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Part Two: Design</h2>

<p>The second part of this book talks about design - everything from building a
prototype to figuring out when you don’t want one. It assumes you have validated
the initial idea and now move on to designing the product and validating that
design before you start building it. It talks about diagrams, sketches, wireframes,
prototypes and of course MVPs.</p>

<p>I think you can safely skip some of these steps when it comes to small applications
because it may be easier/faster to build the application instead of a prototype.
Definitely not to be skipped if you're building a more complex product!</p>

<h2>Part Three: Product</h2>

<p>This section talks about metrics and measuring the product once it is out of the door.
Supposedly based on these metrics you will refine your design and update the product
accordingly.  Most of the time it focuses on A/B testing and which metrics are
important and which are so called "vanity metrics".</p>

<p>I particularly liked the examples of A/B testing and explanations what it is good for
and what it does poorly. Definitely a mistake I've happened to made myself. I'm sure you too.</p>

<p>Let me know if you have read this book and what your thoughts are. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
