<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: BlackBerry | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/blackberry/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T21:56:56+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importing vCard Contacts To BlackBerry Z10 Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T21:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/14/importing-vcard-contacts-to-blackberry-z10-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can honestly state that <a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a> sucks big
time when it comes to importing your contacts from another non-BlackBerry
device. I've been struggling to transfer my contacts from
<a href="http://amzn.to/10USRm2">Nokia 6303</a> to the Z10 for one day.</p>

<p>I tried a simple sync of the contacts from Nokia to Z10 over Bluetooth but
that failed miserably, telling me the Z10 doesn't support this functionality.
This is what to do:</p>

<ul>
<li>On Nokia - <code>Settings - Sync and backup - Create backup</code>;</li>
<li>Then navigate to <code>Apps - Extras - Memory card - Backup files</code>;</li>
<li>Select the most recent backup file, e.g. <code>Backup000.NBF</code> and
transfer it via Bluetooth (or USB cable) to my laptop;</li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: this is a ZIP file with different extension. I've tried also
to transfer it to the Z10 and open from File manager but to no avail.</p>

<ul>
<li>Just unzip the file on the computer;</li>
<li>When extracted it will create multiple directories with meaningless names.
Just find whatever you need - in my case this was the <code>contacts/</code> directory
containing hundreds of <code>.vcf</code> files;</li>
<li><p>Combine all the <code>.vcf</code> files into one. On Linux this is done with</p>

<pre><code>  cat *.vcf &gt; ../all.vcf
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<p>For the record: I've tried also sending all of these files to Z10. Via the
File manager individual vCards open just fine but you need to <code>Save</code> them one
by one. The combined vCard file didn't display correctly at all. Showed only one
contact.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Then go to Gmail (or any other CardDAV service) and import all your vCards.
Go to <code>Contacts - More - Import</code> - and select the combined vCard file since Gmail
doesn't support multi-file uploads;</p></li>
<li><p>On your BlackBerry go to <code>Settings - Accounts</code> and add your Gmail account.
By default this will create profiles for mail, calendar and contacts which will
be synchronized with the device.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>WARNING</strong> I had my Gmail previously configured on the Z10. Despite the account
was configured to re-sync every 15 minutes it took around 2 hours for phone numbers
to sync. And to make it worse there is no button for manual re-sync.</p>

<p>All of this done I have thousands of contacts on my Z10 spread across phone numbers,
emails, vCards and contacts from social networks. I've noticed some of them (my guess
those that had the same email or name) combined auto-magically. The rest can easily be
linked together using the Contacts app Link functionality.</p>

<p>For the record: It is also possible to send vCards one by one directly from Nokia to
Z10 via Bluetooth. The trouble is that for every entry you need to go through several
layers of menu options and confirmations. This makes it impractical.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Importing hundreds of contacts from Nokia to BlackBerry Z10 is MIA;</li>
<li>BB Contacts app (and BB Hub) is cool but has some bugs;</li>
<li>Needs manual contact re-sync button;</li>
<li>Gmail re-sync took longer than expected;</li>
<li><p>Contacts Link feature can be improved and made more easy to use, e.g.</p>

<ul>
<li>grid style display</li>
<li>multiple select and link</li>
<li>swipe and link, etc;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is sub-optimal</p>

<ul>
<li>select a contact</li>
<li>tap Links</li>
<li>tap Add Link</li>
<li>tap Search</li>
<li>type and find the entries you'd like to link;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>The current Link interface is buggy - when searching contacts to add
as links it shows the currently opened contact too. Luckily it doesn't
crash when the same entry is selected :). I've tried.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This is with OS Version 10.0.10.261.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Get a Free BlackBerry Z10]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/13/how-to-get-a-free-blackberry-z10/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-13T11:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/13/how-to-get-a-free-blackberry-z10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you want to have the latest and greatest devices on the market? For free?
No problem if you are a software developer! Over the years I've got several
devices for free and I will tell you how I did it.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Find a hardware vendor that has<br/>launched new products, is behind competitors in terms of software eco-system<br/>and present them with a great application which you will code on their device.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/bbz10_tshirt.jpg" alt="BlackBerry Z10 T-Shirt" style="display:block;clear:both;" /></p>

<p>This week I've been at the BlackBerry 10 Mini Jam in Sofia and I got a
<a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a> Dev Alpha B smart-phone.</p>

<p>BlackBerry 10 OS is different from previous versions. It has a QNX kernel and is
largely incompatible with previous software. This means all apps need to be rewritten.</p>

<p>Another thing to note is that BlackBerry is behind Android, iPhone and probably Windows Phone
in terms of applications. It is in their interest to lower the barrier to entry for developers
and boost their software eco-system. Which in turn makes customers happy because they can
find all sorts of applications. It's that simple.</p>

<p>Being a Linux guy
my idea is to trade my <a href="http://amzn.to/12y5hwp">Lenovo X220</a> for a smart-phone.
The only thing(s) I need is all the command line tools which I use: bash, vim, coreutils
and most notably Python. So I've decided to try and port all of these to the BlackBerry 10 OS.
It should be doable because QNX is POSIX compliant and the OS itself comes with C/C++ and
Qt/QML native development stack.</p>

<p>I have a few other ideas which are still taking shape in my head and are mostly towards
mobile development.</p>

<p>I've heard <a href="http://www.bbdevbalkan.com">BlackBerry Developer Group Balkan</a> may
have some devices to give away to developers so I simply asked. They liked my ideas and
agreed to give me a developer device.</p>

<p>In addition
they've given away the real product (not dev alpha devices) for free at Twitter contests
held during couple of events so far. Several guys I know were lucky enough to win the prizes.</p>

<h2>The OLPC XO laptop</h2>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/olpc_xo.jpg" alt="OLPC XO laptop" style="float:left;margin-right:10px" /></p>

<p>In the past I've taken part in testing <a href="http://fedoraproject.org">Fedora</a> onto
the XO laptop produced by the <a href="http://laptop.org">One Laptop Per Child</a> project.</p>

<p>It is cool and innovative device with its software especially adapted to
child education. The general public wanted to have a standard Linux distro
running on the same hardware. Fedora being the original foundation on which the XO
Linux distro was built was a good choice (among others).</p>

<p>I have received for free the XO laptop shown here and mainly tested networking
related stuff. After the test initiative was completed (and also the upstream OLPC
project ceased to exist closely after that) I got to keep the device for myself.</p>

<h2>Which device to get ?</h2>

<p>I'll keep my eyes open for a Firefox OS or Ubuntu Phone devices. As they come into stores
they will have to compete with already established vendors.</p>

<p>Let me and everyone else know if you got a device for free being a developer! Share your
story and tips into the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
