<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: start-up | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/start-up/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-14T23:20:25+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Taking Orders By Phone Works for My Start-up]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/01/why-taking-orders-by-phone-works-for-my-start-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-01T09:48:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/01/why-taking-orders-by-phone-works-for-my-start-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I've
<a href="/blog/2013/07/31/how-i-created-a-website-in-two-days-without-coding/">mentioned</a>
a start-up project called
<a href="http://obuvki41plus.com">obuvki41plus.com</a> and that it accepts phone orders
instead of online electronic orders like everyone else. I will tell you why.</p>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/phone_order.jpg" alt="Taking phone orders" style="clear:both;display:block;" />
<em>Image CC-BY <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/southernfoodwaysalliance/3291060837/">Southern Foodways Alliance</a></em></p>

<p><a href="http://obuvki41plus.com/">obuvki41plus.com</a> is a
re-seller business my spouse runs. It specializes in large size, elegant
ladies shoes - Europe size 41 plus, which are hard to find in Bulgaria.
There is a shopping cart component on the website which at the end redirects to
a simple page with instructions how to order via phone. Why not online
orders like everyone else? Several reasons!</p>

<p>The business target group is very limited - women who wear large shoe size
and like the proposed shoe style and can afford the higher price (quality shoes
only, sorry). On top of
that the business model is <strong>online only</strong>. The rule of thumb is to <strong>make
everything possible to lower barrier to entry for customers</strong>!
Also don't make our lives harder in doing so.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Phone ordering is the easiest way for customers in Bulgaria.
I myself often prefer it because of the too many steps and too many fields
to fill-in when ordering online. The reality is that most local websites
are horribly made with respect to user experience and many users are not
that fluent with Internet as it may seem. No need to get people frustrated
if they are about to spend their money with you!</p></li>
<li><p>Phone ordering, especially in the early business stage lets you know
your customers. This is invaluable feedback for you as the owner and you
can't get that from an online ordering system. It just doesn't work,
I've tried!</p></li>
<li><p>A phone ordering system is just so easy to implement. Later that can
be scaled with some automated IVR system and a call center; Or just
migrate it to online ordering system;</p></li>
<li><p>The website in question is supposed to be no-maintenance as much
as possible. It is static HTML and no database at all. Introducing
online ordering is just too much of a technological overhead in this case;</p></li>
<li><p>Last but probably most important is customer care - not only we want to
make it easy for them to order but want to prevent frequent returns
caused by wrong product expectations or incorrect size. After all shoes
need to be tried first.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So to summarize - the orders are taken in person via phone
including objection handling and questions answering. An order may consist
of up to 3 pairs of shoes which are shipped to the customer with the option
to try them out upon delivery! Buy all or just a pair - it's a customer call!
Small return fee is imposed to prevent abuse!</p>

<p>For that kind of business this seems to be the best solution so far.
I'd love to hear other owners experience and decision logic. Please use
the comments to tell us how you've organized the sales/ordering/delivery
process in your company and why so. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - Imagga]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/29/what-runs-your-startup-imagga/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-29T12:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/29/what-runs-your-startup-imagga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/imagga.png" alt="Imagga" style="float:left; margin-right:10px;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://imagga.com/">Imagga</a> is a cloud platform that helps businesses and
individuals organize their images in a fast and cost-effective way. They
develop a range of advanced proprietary image recognition and image processing
technologies, which are built into several services such as smart image
cropping, color extraction and multi-color search, visual similarity search and
auto-tagging.</p>

<p>During
<a href="/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/">Balkan Venture Forum</a>
in Sofia I sat down with Georgi Kadrev to talk about technology.
Surprisingly this hi-tech service is built on top of standard low-tech components
and lots of hard work.</p>

<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>Core functionality is developed in C and C++ with the OpenCV library.
Imagga relies heavily on own image processing algorithms for their core
features. These were built as a combination of their own research activities
and publications from other researchers.</p>

<p>Image processing is executed by worker nodes configured with their own
software stack. Nodes are distributed among Amazon EC2 and other data centers.</p>

<p>Client libraries to access Imagga API are available in PHP, Ruby and Java.</p>

<p>Imagga has built several websites to showcase their technology.
<a href="http://cropp.me/">Cropp.me</a>, <a href="http://colorslike.me/">ColorsLike.me</a>,
<a href="http://www.stockpodium.com">StockPodium</a> and <a href="http://autotag.me/">AutoTag.me</a>
were built with PHP, JavaScript and jQuery above a standard LAMP stack.</p>

<p>Recently Imagga also started using GPU computing with nVidia Tesla cards.
They use C++ and Python bindings for
<a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/what-cuda">CUDA</a>.</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else?</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>As an initially bootstrapping start-up we chose something that is basically free,<br/>reliable and popular - that's why started with the LAMP stack. It proved to be<br/>stable and convenient for our web needs and we preserved it.<br/>The use of C++ is a natural choice for computational intensive tasks that we<br/>need to perform for the purpose of our core expertise - image processing.<br/>Though we initially wrote the whole core technology code from scratch, we later<br/>switched to OpenCV for some of the building blocks as it is very well optimized<br/>and continuously extended image processing library.</p></p><p><p>With the raise of affordable high-performance GPU processors and their availability<br/>in server instances, we decided it's time to take advantage of this highly parallel<br/>architecture, perfectly suitable for image processing tasks.</p><footer><strong>Georgi Kadrev</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>If you’d like to hear more from Imagga please comment below.
I will ask them to follow this thread and reply to your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Runs Your Start-up - RETiDoc]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/29/what-runs-your-startup-retidoc/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-29T12:13:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/29/what-runs-your-startup-retidoc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/retidoc.gif" alt="RETiDoc" style="float:left; margin-right: 15px;" /></p>

<p><a href="http://retidoc.com/">RETiDoc</a> automates personal ID data entry, speeding up
customer service and eliminating costly errors. The product is based on OCR
algorithms and could be used on hardware devices scanning the ID card or
through a compact scanner box specially designed for the need. The main problem
tackled by RETiDoc is manual data entry at service providers,
which is a time consuming, low-customer satisfaction process, filled with
expensive typos and low productivity at provider’s front offices.</p>

<p>Co-founder Martin Kulov takes us behind the scenes.</p>

<h2>Main Technologies</h2>

<p>RETiDoc is the second start-up featured on this blog to rely heavily on
Microsoft technologies. Software development is done in C# using
Visual Studio and <a href="https://tfs.visualstudio.com/">Team Foundation Service</a>.</p>

<p>Microsoft Test Manager is used to organize the test process!</p>

<h2>Why Not Something Else?</h2>

<p>Unfortunately this section is missing. The original format of this blog
is for the start-up founders or head of IT to tell the readers what factors
led to selection of the named technologies. RETiDoc team is busy at the moment,
working on their product launch and don't have the time to fill-in the details.</p>

<p>Hopefully they will do so in the future.</p>

<h2>Want More Info?</h2>

<p>If you’d like to hear more from <em>RETiDoc</em> please comment below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Text To Speech for Bulgarian]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/20/text-to-speech-for-bulgarian/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-20T14:06:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/20/text-to-speech-for-bulgarian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been exploring text-to-speech synthesizers for Bulgarian in the past
few weeks. I found only three. Here is my review and opinion about
two competitive companies, one of which lost me as a client.</p>

<h2>eSpeak</h2>

<p><a href="http://espeak.sourceforge.net/">eSpeak</a> is a compact open source software
speech synthesizer for English and other languages, for Linux and Windows.</p>

<p>I'm using espeak-1.47.11-1, from Fedora - the src.rpm rebuilt on Red Hat
Enterprise Linux 6. Earlier versions do not support Bulgarian.</p>

<p>There is only one available voice for Bulgarian, which seems to have reasonably
good pronunciation. There are some errors though, it's not perfect. The voice
however is horrible. It's the worst computer generated voice of all solutions
I've found so far.</p>

<p>Good for initial testing since it requires virtually no setup and can be used
from the command line.</p>

<h2>SpeechLab 2.0</h2>

<p>SpeechLab is developed by the
<a href="http://www.bacl.org/speechlab.html">Bulgarian Association for Computational Linguistics</a>.
There's a sample of only one voice but I was told others can be added as well. Not sure about that.</p>

<p>Listening to <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=4s2UgwYgbkM">the sample</a>
I think this is the most correct synthesizer of all. The voice still sounds computerized
but better compared to eSpeak. The same voice is used by local TV channels when showing
news related to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymous_%28group%29">Anonymous</a> and
one could probably say it will be accepted by the general public if used into
a software product.</p>

<p>BACL has transferred the sales rights to a company called
<a href="http://aquasyst-eco.com/speechlab_2_0_server.html">Aquasyst-Eco</a> which claims to have
a desktop and a server product. The server version is supposed to work on Linux too.
There is also a <a href="http://slideme.org/application/speechlab-2-0">version for Android</a>.</p>

<p>Initially I thought to use SpeechLab but BACL and the trading vendor didn't make it
easy on me. There's virtually no documentation, all links to samples from the
official product pages are broken, they didn't reply to any of my emails
nor phone calls.</p>

<p>As much as I prefer working/using locally developed products (not only software)
I will never use SpeechLab because its creators don't give a fuck about customers.
Why should I give a fuck about the product then?</p>

<h2>Innoetics' SpeakVolumes</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.innoetics.com">Innoetics</a> is a Greek company, a spin-off of the
Institute of Language &amp; Speech Processing (ILSP) of ‘Athena’ Research Centre.
Something like BACL I suppose but a bit more commercially oriented.</p>

<p>Initially I though to use their TTS Batch product to produce audio samples
and asked for a demo. They were very quick in their response and gave me
an FTP download of the software, plus demo activation key and documentation.
Via email they've sent me tons of info plus pricing and additional proposals.
I didn't even try this demo because it runs on Windows which I don't have.</p>

<p>It turned out Innoetics has built the <a href="http://www.speakvolumes.eu/">SpeakVolumes</a>
web service which has two modes of operation - on-the-fly audio generation
using a SOAP based API and offline generation via the web site.
Pricing for SpeakVolumes (per words) was much more competitive than their Windows products
for my use case.</p>

<p>I've created an account at SpeakVolumes and they've bumped up my initial words
credit so I can give it a try. Works like a charm.</p>

<p>There is only one voice for Bulgarian called Irina
(<a href="http://www.innoetics.com/media/tts_irinademo_bg.mp3">sample</a>).
The voice is very soft, female voice, speaks slower compared to eSpeak
and SpeechLab and sounds very natural. It makes a few mistakes but
from a 250 words sample that I used only a couple were pronounced with
minor mistakes.</p>

<p>The web service generates a Base64 encoded MP3 file and returns it as
response to the client.
<a href="https://gist.github.com/atodorov/6044724">See example Python script here</a>.</p>

<p>The fact that Innoetics involved with me very quickly and provided me with
demo accounts and all sorts of information about their products and the
web API makes SpeakVolumes my choice for Text-To-Speech conversion for Bulgarian.</p>

<h2>Ivona</h2>

<p>Andre Polykanine from the eSpeak mailing list told me about
<a href="http://www.ivona.com/en/">Ivona</a>. It is a Polish company and seems to
have been acquired by Amazon now. Andre told me Ivona had planned Bulgarian
support some time ago, but now rejected it for some reason. They didn't
reply to my email though.</p>

<p>Have you seen other text-to-speech synthesizers for Bulgarian? Let me know
what are they and if you have tried them out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Give a Book, Get a Laptop With Discount]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/04/give-a-book-get-a-laptop-with-discount/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T11:44:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/04/give-a-book-get-a-laptop-with-discount</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/startup/timeheroes.png" alt="Time Heroes" style="float:left; margin-right:10px;"/></p>

<p>Bulgarian start-up TimeHeroes.org is helping a non-profit organization to
<a href="http://timeheroes.org/podaretekniga/264">collect used computers and books for children in foster care</a>.
They are helping more children get access to the Internet.</p>

<p>I will donate an
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&field-keywords=asus&linkCode=ur2&sprefix=asus%2Caps%2C398&tag=atodorovorg-20&url=search-alias%3Dcomputers">Asus</a><img src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
eeePC and a
<a target="_blank" href="http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&keywords=fujitsu%20laptop&linkCode=ur2&qid=1372944368&rh=i%3Acomputers%2Ck%3Afujitsu%20laptop&tag=atodorovorg-20">Fujitsu</a><img src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=ur2&o=1" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
laptop plus all books
from my <a href="/give-away/">Give Away List</a>, which are not currently taken.
Because this is not much I have an offer for everyone else, who would like to help.</p>

<div style="clear:both"></div>


<h2>What is the offer</h2>

<p><strong>Give a book or your old laptop and get a new one with discount!</strong>.</p>

<p>My company
<a href="http://otb.bg">Open Technologies Bulgaria, Ltd.</a> is an authorized reseller of Vali Computers and
Fujitsu. Hardware reselling is not the main company activity but a backup in case a customer
wants to purchase entire solution from one vendor.</p>

<p>I will not charge the standard reseller's discount (between 5% and 10%) if you drop-off your books
or old laptops with me and agree to donated them to children.
The offer is valid as long as the donation campaign is (I don't know how long but looks like ongoing).</p>

<p>You can select anything from <a href="http://www.vali.bg">http://www.vali.bg</a> with the reseller's discount off!
Delivery or pick-up is on you though.</p>

<p>If you want to participate use the comments below and I will get in touch with you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
