<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-18T23:56:11+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HackFMI 2013 Hacker Gifts]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/25/hackfmi-2013-hacker-gifts/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T16:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/25/hackfmi-2013-hacker-gifts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://hackfmi.com">HackFMI</a> starts tonight!
<a href="/blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/">During the previous edition</a> of the hackathon
I gave one team a special personal gift based on my estimation of their hacker level!
Thanks to <a href="http://blog.ganev.bg">Vihren Ganev</a> (one of the gift winners) for reminding
me about that!</p>

<p>This year I have even bigger items to give to those who think out of the box, who hack
their way around and are brave enough to try and change the world through software!
I have one
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001AWCS52/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B001AWCS52&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Lenovo Thinkpad Business Backpack</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B001AWCS52" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
and one
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00004TX7H/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00004TX7H&linkCode=as2&tag=atodorovorg-20">Lowepro D-Res 20 AW Digital Camera Bag</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B00004TX7H" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
(a bit bigger than the one on Amazon, easily fits a BlackBerry Z10) as seen on the pictures below.
Plus some small Red Hat branded items.</p>

<p><img src="/images/hackfmi/lenovo_bagpack.jpg" title="Lenovo bagpack" alt="Lenovo bagpack" />
<img src="/images/hackfmi/lowepro_case.jpg" title="Lowepro case" alt="Lowepro case" /></p>

<h2>How To Get The Gifts</h2>

<p>There are no rules, I will make a decision as I go along.
I can give away all items or none. It's up to you! Surprise me!</p>

<p>Tomorrow I will be mentoring the teams who decided to work with Django but
I'm happy to talk to anyone who needs help or just wants to grab the
cool stuff! See you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming Talk: Fedora Test Days in Sofia]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T23:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On September 28th I will be giving a short talk about
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Test_Days">Fedora Test Days</a> at the regular
Linux for Bulgarians
<a href="http://www.linux-bg.org/cgi-bin/y/index.pl?page=news&amp;key=459487176">conference</a>.
I will explain what these are and how one can participate. I will also announce
my plans and schedule to organize some
<a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Fedora_20_test_days">Fedora 20 test days</a>
locally in Sofia. If you are a fan of Fedora and want to file bugs and kick
some developers' ass this is the way to do it!</p>

<p>Other talks include Alexander Shopov's „Oracle's take on NoSQL“ which I wanted
to hear since this summer and TBA talks about MicroTik routers.</p>

<p>The conference will take place on September 28th at the French Institute at
Sofia University
(see <a href="http://conf.linux-bg.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/su-2.png">map</a>).
It starts at 13:00 and my talk should be at the beginning. See you there!</p>

<p>PS: this post was initially written on my <a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ">BlackBerry Z10</a>
with Penzus Editor - another small step in
<a href="/blog/2013/08/01/laptop-vs-smartphone-part-one/">retiring my laptop</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes From Two Interesting GUADEC Talks]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T14:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As this year's <a href="https://www.guadec.org/">GUADEC</a> is coming to an end
I'm publishing an interesting update from
<a href="cz.linkedin.com/in/mullerpetr">Petr Muller</a> for
those who were not able to attend.
Petr is a Senior Quality Engineer at Red Hat. His notes were
sent to an internal QE mailing list and re-published with permission.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>As this year's GUADEC happened in the same building where I have my<br/>other office, I decided to attend. I'm sharing my notes from the two<br/>sessions I consider to be especially interesting for the audience of<br/>this mailing list:</p></p><p><p>== How to not report your UX bug ==<br/>Speaker:    Fabiana Simões<br/>Blog:       http://fabianapsimoes.wordpress.com/<br/>Twitter:    https://twitter.com/fabianapsimoes</p></p><p><p>Do not do this stuff:<br/>* Do not simply present a preferred solution, but describe a problem (a<br/>difficulty you are having, etc.)<br/>* Do not use "This sucks" idiom, not even hidden in false niceties like<br/>"It's not user friendly"<br/>* Do not talk for majority, when you are not entitled to ("most users<br/>would like")<br/>* Do not consider all UX issues as minor: an inability to do stuff is<br/>not a minor issue</p></p><p><p>What is actually interesting for the designer in a report?<br/>* What were you trying to do?<br/>* Why did you want to do it?<br/>* What did you do?<br/>* What happened?<br/>* What were your expectations?</p></p><p><p>More notes<br/>* Write as much as needed<br/>* Describe what you see, did and <em>how you felt</em><br/>* Print screen is your friend!<br/>* <em>Give praise</em></p></p><p><p>== Extreme containment measures: keeping bug reports under control ==<br/>Speaker:  Jean-Francois Fortin Tam<br/>Homepage: http://jeff.ecchi.ca<br/>Twitter:  https://twitter.com/nekohayo</p></p><p><p>Discussed the problem lot of OS projects are having: lot of useless<br/>(old, irrelevant, waiting for decision no one wants to make) bug/rfe<br/>reports in their bug tracking systems. Lots of food for thought about<br/>our own projects, internal or external. Clever applications of<br/>principles from personal productivity systems such as GTD and Inbox Zero<br/>for bug tracking.</p></p><p><p>The talk was mostly an applied version of this blog post, which is worth<br/>reading:<br/>http://jeff.ecchi.ca/blog/2012/10/08/reducing-our-core-apps-software-inventory/</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Petr Muller</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I particularly like the UX bug reporting guide lines. Need to take those into
account when reporting UI issues.</p>

<p>I still haven't read the second blog post which also looks interesting although
not very applicable to me. After all I'm the person reporting bugs not the one
who decides what and when gets fixed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T12:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two hours ago I've heard on the radio about
<a href="http://acl2013.org/site/">the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</a>
which is held at the moment in Sofia
According to the guest speaker (a professor from Bulgarian Academy of Science) the official
program will be over today but the next two days will feature workshops and tutorials.</p>

<p>Definitely not to be missed if you are in Sofia. I'm not unfortunately :(.
If you can please visit and share what you saw with me. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer Hackathon in Sofia]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T14:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/hackfmi/Logo_SummerHackFMI.png" alt="Summer HackFMI" style="display:block;clear:both" /></p>

<p>A <a href="http://hackfmi.com/spontanen-leten-hachathon/">summer hackathon</a>
will be held in Sofia between 16th and 22nd of August. The week prior to the
event (12th to 15th) will be full of lectures and workshops to prepare the students
for their task.</p>

<p>The goal this time is to create a new system for the Student Council organization
which will host their new website and also provide more transparency into the
organization and the work they do. The idea is initiated by the chairman of the
council which is quite surprising for me to hear. You can read his motivation
(in Bulgarian) <a href="https://github.com/Hackfmi/SummerHackathon/blob/master/motivation.md">here</a>.</p>

<p>At the moment it is agreed that the system will be written in Python and Django
and this is where I join. Together with Kiril Vladimirov I will be leading the
Python/Django lecture and workshop in one of the days, likely 14th of August.</p>

<p>The program is not yet finalized so I can't share more info. Please watch this
space for more details when they are available.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
