<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>atodorov.org</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://atodorov.org/</id><updated>2015-11-11T15:16:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>OpenFest 2015 Impressions</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/11/11/openfest-2015-impressions/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-11T15:16:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2015-11-11:blog/2015/11/11/openfest-2015-impressions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I've attended &lt;a href="http://openfest.org"&gt;OpenFest&lt;/a&gt; in Sofia. I have
mixed feelings about this year's event. Although I was so tired that I slept
through the entire Monday I find some of the presentations not so interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first day I've tried to attend the talk about &lt;em&gt;The Yocto Project&lt;/em&gt; by
&lt;a href="http://anavi.org"&gt;Leon Anavi&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://kolev.info"&gt;Radoslav Kolev&lt;/a&gt;.
The room was full and I couldn't get in so I watched some of it outside
using the live streaming. Next was &lt;em&gt;Building Universal Applications with Angular 2&lt;/em&gt; by
&lt;a href="http://blog.mgechev.com"&gt;Minko Gechev&lt;/a&gt; followed by
&lt;em&gt;Free And Open Source Software In European Public Administrations&lt;/em&gt; by
&lt;a href="http://hillenius.com/"&gt;Gijs Hillenius&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall impression from these talks was good. They were interesting to me
and I liked the way they were presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards I've spend a good hour and more talking to Gijs, catching up on
a long overdue email thread about FOSS usage in Bulgarian public administrations.
It's always nice to put a face on the email address :). The outcome of this
is that I'll have to forward him quite a lot of local contacts. Also my
previous article
&lt;a href="https://joinup.ec.europa.eu/community/osor/news/10-steps-migrate-your-closed-software-open-source"&gt;10 steps to migrate your closed software to open source&lt;/a&gt;
is now available at OSOR's website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day two I had quite a few people to talk to but managed to attend couple of
presentations. In the main room &lt;em&gt;First Lessons in Control Theory&lt;/em&gt; by
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hiro_asari"&gt;Hiro Asari&lt;/a&gt; and at the end
&lt;em&gt;Collaboration In Open Source - How Does It Really Work?&lt;/em&gt; by
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ottokekalainen"&gt;Otto Kekäläinen&lt;/a&gt;. I am quite disappointed
by both, the challenge level wasn't the one I've expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiro's subject is interesting but IMO he merely scratched the surface.
The first half of the presentation was an introduction in the field
and as far as I could tell most of the people left in the room
didn't need it. The most interesting part was probably the last 5-10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Otto's presentation I had the expectation it would be interesting stories
and failures from working with the community. Instead it was an introduction
why and how open source communities work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said both presentations are suitable for inexperienced public, folks
who are new to open source or IT in general. For folks like me, who have
been working for 10 years in the open they weren't so interesting.
I'm not against entry-level presentations but at least they have to
be properly annotated as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other presentation I've attended on day two was &lt;em&gt;Education 3.0&lt;/em&gt; by
Ivan Gospodinov. This was a non-technical talk which conflicted with
the lightning talks and I've missed 
&lt;a href="/blog/2015/05/20/free-software-testing-books/"&gt;mine&lt;/a&gt;. I liked this one
though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;General&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the event was held at a new venue which was a pleasant change.
I've heard there were more people attending since previous years yet
it seemed there is less seating capacity at the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The after-party however was very good and just before leaving something
amazing happened to me. A guy comes to me and asks if I'm atodorov.
Obviously I am. Then he says he's my co-worker Vladimir Ralev from Red Hat.
Mind you we've talked many times on IRC but not once seen in person.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Open Data Event Coming to Sofia</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/07/01/open-data-event-coming-to-sofia/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T11:58:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2015-07-01:blog/2015/07/01/open-data-event-coming-to-sofia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/17565601186"&gt;Open Data and Intelligent Government&lt;/a&gt;
is the name of upcoming event organized by &lt;a href="http://sofiatech.bg/en/"&gt;Sofia Tech Park&lt;/a&gt;
on July 14th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The (preliminary) topics for this event are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government vision for opening data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation of national platform for open data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legal aspects of open data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation of &lt;a href="http://opendata.government.bg/"&gt;Bulgarian open data portal&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Europe and open data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open, coordinated e-government for citizens and business;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What has already been done by municipalities in Bulgaria;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategy of Sofia municipality for open data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upcoming open data programming contest organized by Sofia municipality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will also be participating in this event by covering two topics I'm close to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurship and open data - sharing my limited experience with Difio
and processing open data; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical tips for successful open data hackathon - sharing my observations as
a mentor at &lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt; and giving some recommendations which will
help the alleged open data contest make a difference not being just another dull event
organized by governmental agencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far other confirmed speakers are Rado from &lt;a href="http://hackbulgaria.com"&gt;HackBulgaria&lt;/a&gt;/
&lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.obshtestvo.bg/"&gt;Obshtestvo.bg&lt;/a&gt; which are
working in the field of open government and open data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also in touch with the event organizers and helping a little bit with the program.
If you're interested in speaking please get in touch with me ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>DEVit Conf 2015 Impressions</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/22/devit-conf-2015-impressions/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-22T12:01:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2015-05-22:blog/2015/05/22/devit-conf-2015-impressions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been a busy week after &lt;a href="http://devitconf.org/"&gt;DEVit conf&lt;/a&gt; took place in
Thessaloniki. Here are my impressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crack, Train, Fix, Release" src="/images/devit2015.jpg" title="Crack, Train, Fix, Release" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've started the day with the session called "Crack, Train, Fix, Release" by 
Chris Heilmann. While it was very interesting for some unknown reason I
was expecting a talk more closely related to software testing. Unfortunately at the
same time in the other room was a talk called "Integration Testing from the Trenches"
by Nicolas Frankel which I missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end Chris answered the question "What to do about old versions of IE ?".
And the answer pretty much was "Don't try to support everything, leave them with
basic functionality so that users can achieve what they came for on your website.
Don't put nice buttons b/c IE 6 users are not used to nice things and they get confused."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you remember I had a similar question to Jeremy Keith at 
&lt;a href="/blog/2015/04/20/videos-from-bulgaria-web-summit-2015/"&gt;Bulgaria Web Summit&lt;/a&gt; last month
and the answer was similar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Which one is Jeremy's favorite device/browser to develop for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Your approach is wrong and instead we should be thinking in terms of what features are 
essential or non-essential for our websites and develop around features
(if supported, if not supported) not around browsers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Btw I did ask Chris if he knows Jeremy and he does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the coffee break there was "JavaScript ♥ Unicode" by Mathias Bynens which
I saw last year at &lt;a href="http://how.camp/"&gt;How Camp&lt;/a&gt; in Veliko Tarnovo so I just stopped by
to say hi and went to listen to 
"The future of responsive web design: web component queries" by Nikos Zinas.
As far as I understood Nikos is a local rock-star developer. I'm not much into web
development but the opportunity to create your own HTML components (tags) looks
very promising. I guess there will be more business coming for
&lt;a href="http://telerik.com"&gt;Telerik&lt;/a&gt; :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to listen to "Live Productive Coder" by Heinz Kabutz but that one started
in Greek so I switched the room for 
"iOS real time content modifications using websockets" by  Benny Weingarten-Gabbay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch I went straight for
"Introduction to Docker: What is it and why should I care?" by Ian Miell
which IMO was the most interesting talk of the day. It wasn't very technical but
managed to clear some of the mysticism around Docker and what it actually is.
I tried to grab a few minutes of Ian's time and we found topics of common interest
to talk about (&lt;a href="http://www.projectatomic.io/"&gt;Project Atomic&lt;/a&gt; anyone?) but later
failed to find him and continue the talk. I guess I'll have to follow online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Perry with "Your Web Stack Would Betray You In An Instant" made a great show.
The room was packed, I myself was actually standing the whole time. He described a series
of failures across the entire web development stack which gave developers hard times
patching and upgrading their services. The lesson: everything fails, be prepared!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last talk I visited was "GitHub Automation" by Forbes Lindesay. It was more of an
inspirational talk, rather than technical one. GitHub provides cool API so why not use it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DEVit team" src="/images/devit2015team.jpg" title="DEVit team" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I know this is the first year of DEVit. For a first timer the team did great!
I particularly liked the two coffee breaks before lunch and in the early afternoon and the
sponsors pitches in between the main talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All talks were recorded but I have no idea what's happening with the videos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will definitely make a point of visiting Thessaloniki more often and follow the local
IT and start-up scenes there. And tonight is Silicon Drinkabout which will be the official
after party of &lt;a href="http://digitalk.bg/"&gt;DigitalK&lt;/a&gt; in Sofia.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fedora.planet"></category><category term="Django"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Summary of Evolve Digital</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-11T22:29:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-06-11:blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" src="/images/evolve_digital.jpg" title="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I've visited an event organized by the 
&lt;a href="http://www.atlantic-club.org/index.php?en"&gt;Atlantic Club of Bulgaria&lt;/a&gt; which
officially marked the launch of a digital national alliance in Bulgaria. This is
part of an initiative of the European Commission, called 
&lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/grand-coalition-digital-jobs"&gt;Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs&lt;/a&gt;,
which aims to address the lack of
sufficient amount and quality professionals in Europe working in the
field of Information and Communication technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part was few short keynotes, including one from deputy prime minister
and memorandum signing and group photo. In the keynotes (and afterwards)
the stress was on the lack of relevant ICT skills and the need of an estimated
1 million digital workers by 2020 in EU alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next two sessions were panel discussions. The first one presenting the local 
chapter of the Digital Coalition in Bulgaria. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of the coalition are to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;help more people master more digital skills (not only as developers but also
proper usage of social media, how to create content, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enable more people to choose digital jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;help local talents present themselves on the global scene&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How it (is supposed to) works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;initiate own ideas and propose them for implementation (to the ICT industry and broad public I guess)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stimulate learning through doing, learning by example using real use cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;help (and possibly sponsor) outside projects and ideas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the various companies supporting the coalition pledged how they are going to
help. The most interesting news from this panel was the announcement of a new HP
data center in Sofia which will be used as a training lab with access available to
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second panel was about education and how to bridge the gap! The interesting points were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Education and Science admits they have finally realized that our educational
system and programs are behind current tendencies and need concrete steps in order to boost
education and science research;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samsung will open their innovation lab at Sofia University to outside students as well;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to pay more attention to content and training of teachers because they also have
a skills gap while young children do not;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly liked what Prof. Petar Kenderov from the Institute of Mathematics and Informatics
at Bulgarian Academy of Sciences said - in the outside world children are constantly sharing
and communicating with each other while at school (also to some extent in universities) they
are expected to not communicate, not share and keep quiet. He emphasized the value of learning through
experimentation vs. learning through reading and writing, e.g. the current way things work
and the old way of teaching. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that was obvious was that otherwise competing companies (e.g. Microsoft, Oracle, SAP,
VMware) were working together to fix some of the problems mentioned. However I'm a bit skeptical
that large multi-national companies will be flexible enough to make a positive change.
I'd bet on the independent organizations like &lt;a href="https://hackbulgaria.com/"&gt;HackBulgaria&lt;/a&gt; and
Svetlin Nakov's &lt;a href="https://softuni.bg/"&gt;Software University&lt;/a&gt; or initiatives by local Bulgarian companies
like the already proven &lt;a href="http://academy.telerik.com/"&gt;Telerik Academy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the entire program of the event, for anyone interested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“EVOLVE DIGITAL”
10th June 2014 (Tuesday)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:00 – 10:10 Opening: Gergana Passy, Digital Champion Bulgaria&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:10 – 10:20 Daniela Bobeva, Deputy Prime-Minister of the Republic of Bulgaria&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:20 – 10:30 Constantijn van Oranje, Head of Cabinet of Vice-President of EC Neelie Kroes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:30 – 10:40 Jonathan Murray, Director, Digital Europe
      Special guest: Sandi Češko, Founder &amp;amp; President, Studio Moderna&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:40 – 10:50 Memorandum Signing and Group Photo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:50 – 11:00 Pause&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11:00 – 12:15 Digital Coalition Bulgaria
      Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li
      Rennie Popcheva, CEO, Digital Coalition Bulgaria
      Boyko Iaramov, Co-founder &amp;amp; Chief Process Officer, Telerik
      Marta Poslad, Senior Policy Advisor, CEE Google
      Petar Ivanov, General Manager, Microsoft Bulgaria
      Iravan Hira, General Manager, Hewlett-Packard Bulgaria
      Atanas Dobrev, CEO, VIVACOM
      Danny Gooris, Senior Manager, Oracle Academy
      Dimitar Dimitrov, Relationship Business Development, Lenovo
      Stamen Kochkov, Vice-president, SAP Labs Bulgaria, Chairman of BASSCOM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:15 – 12:30 Coffee Break&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:30 – 13:45 Education in the Digital Era
      Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li
      Ivan Krastev, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Education and Science, Republic of Bulgaria
      George Stoytchev, Executive Director, Open Society Institute Sofia
      Sabina Stirb, Public Affairs &amp;amp; Corporate Citizenship Manager, Samsung
      Prof. Petar Kenderov, Institute of Mathematics and Informatics, Bulgarian
      Academy of Sciences
      Dr. George Sharkov, Director, European Software Institute - Center Eastern
      Europe
      Elena Marinova, President, Musala Soft, Chair of the Educational Commission,
      Bulgarian Association of Information Technologies
      Svetlin Nakov, Founder, Software University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13:45 – Lunch in Restaurant “At the Eagles”
      11 Dyakon Ygnatiy str., in the building of Ministry of transport, 18th Floor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Bulgaria Web Summit Report</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-02T09:02:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-06-02:blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week ended up with &lt;a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.com/"&gt;Bulgaria Web Summit&lt;/a&gt;.
The event was very big this year, with 4 halls and 600 visitors.
I was moderating the so called &lt;em&gt;JavaScript&lt;/em&gt; hall and will concentrate on
what happened there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" src="/images/bgws2014.jpg" title="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" /&gt;
This is what my hall looked like at around 10:00 and stayed pretty much the same
during the entire day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers at hall Rhodopi were (in order of appearance)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/delian"&gt;Delian Delchev&lt;/a&gt; talking about the JavaScript
revolution taking over the world and how this language has become the most
widely used programming language in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hkdobrev"&gt;Haralan Dobrev&lt;/a&gt; with some tips about development
workflows, git, continuous integration and unit testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yoga for Geeks during the lunch break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boyan Dzhumakov with topics about home automation and Internet of things, who
demonstrated his bed side lamp controlled via a light sensor and Arduino.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.boyanov.org/"&gt;Neven Boyanov&lt;/a&gt; continuing on the hardware topics with
comparison of ATmel, Arduino and Raspberry Pi and showing more examples of
small programmable devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/attodorov"&gt;Angel Todorov&lt;/a&gt; from Infragistics with a very
interesting talk about JavaScript instrumentation for performance analysis.
A very cool presentation and you should definitely check out his
&lt;a href="https://github.com/attodorov/cheetah.js"&gt;cheetah.js&lt;/a&gt; framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KrasimirTsonev"&gt;Krasimir Tsonev&lt;/a&gt; with 
&lt;a href="http://absurdjs.com/"&gt;AbsurdJS&lt;/a&gt; - a JavaScript library with superpowers.
Teaser: Krasimir is also publishing a book caled
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/atodorov_/status/472723298053537792"&gt;Node.js Blueprints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/krokodilerian"&gt;Vasil Kolev&lt;/a&gt; with a talk about security
and web service design and how most of the web is doing it wrong :).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately there is no video or audio recording available. If you find
some of the talks interesting and would like to get more info about it let
me know. I will ask the presenters to share their slides or give more details
where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't worry if you've missed the Web Summit in Sofia. There will be another one
in the autumn, held at Veliko Tarnovo. For more info please subscribe to the
&lt;a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.us6.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=44058a4036fe9516b0ea2004c&amp;amp;id=e768a8c09a"&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>DigitalK Day 2 Report</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-01T20:38:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-06-01:blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing to report on the last few events that took place in Sofia this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day #2 of DigitalK started with the presentation of Piotr Jas of BlaBla Car.
What I really liked about it (picture TBA) was one particular graph depicting
the various types of travel (time before travel vs. cost of travel) and
visualizing different industries (e.g. air travel) or competitor companies.
The image clearly exhibited a blank space which is the exact market segment
where BlaBla Car have positioned themselves in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very practical and easy to use tool for entrepreneurs in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the rest of the keynotes I can outline two in particular:
Ivan Hernandez' &lt;em&gt;Disruptive Innovation and the future of Digital Transformation&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;The future of Tech and Communities&lt;/em&gt; by Tim Röhrich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked them because both were very inspirational although not telling you
something which you haven't heard before. They were basically reinforcing
the spirit of the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the small hall there was a workshop called 
&lt;em&gt;How to turn a good idea into a successful start-up&lt;/em&gt; led by Daniela Neumann,
which didn't turn out to be what I expected. She was talking about the early
cycle of idea/customer validation and I don't remember any particular example
being shown. Frankly most of the people have heard about this before (myself included)
and were quite bored. Not many of them stayed till the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening continued with the already traditional Silicon Drinkabout in Sofia
which hosted many of the conference attendees. I did a quick visit only
because I had to prepare myself for Bulgaria Web Summit on the next day!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Twilio meetup and DigitalK 2014 Day 1</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/29/twilio-meetup-and-digitalk-2014-day-1/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-29T22:31:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-05-29:blog/2014/05/29/twilio-meetup-and-digitalk-2014-day-1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The conference season (this week) is officially open! So here's my report about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started by accident last evening with a
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/629009950539772/"&gt;warm-up event&lt;/a&gt;
sponsored by Twilio at betahaus Sofia. I had the pleasure to have a long chat
with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lilaineurope"&gt;Lisa from Twilio&lt;/a&gt; over a few beers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was Day #1 of &lt;a href="http://digitalk.bg/"&gt;DigitalK&lt;/a&gt; which is the leading SEE
technology event. I've also visited the event last year and must say that this
time it is bigger. The main hall was totally packed. The WiFi connectivity has been
improved since last year but still sucked. I had more success using my 3G instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting part of Day #1 was the mini Seedcamp session which presented
10 startups. In order of appearance they are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.adtapsy.com/"&gt;AdTapsy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bitcoini.com/"&gt;Bitcoini.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ikollect.net/"&gt;iKollect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.rocketads.co/"&gt;RocketAds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scalewhale.eu/"&gt;ScaleWhale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://angel.co/smartoken"&gt;Smartoken&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stepsss.co/"&gt;Stepsss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=co.talkie_kids.talkie"&gt;Talkie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://viblast.com/"&gt;Viblast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wiziva.com"&gt;Wiziva&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viblast, Stepsss and Talkie were the 3 finalists who also presented at the main hall.
Needless to say the coolest one from technology point of view is Viblast, which is
a peer-to-peer video streaming platform, utilizing WebRTC. They were also strong at the
presentation and look very strong at the business level as well. I wish them good luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stepsss is essentially a shoe sole with sensors paired with smart-phone apps to
give runners more info and feedback. I like it because they are a hardware company
although there's lots of competition in this space. I'd like to beta test their product
and see what happens when I go dancing all night long :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talkie is an educational app for children which helps them learn new languages. I had the
pleasure to see it in action before the actual presentation. The design is very cool
and the app does seem usable and complete. However I don't see much of a technological
challenge here and I'm not sure how will they deal with the strong competition in the ed-tech
space. We'll have to wait and see. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the rest ScaleWhale and Smartoken do seem interesting but I really failed to get how things
will be organized on the technology side. Both ideas are run by a single person team, which
is a recipe for disaster (judging from my own experience).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is Day #2 of DigitalK and on Saturday I'm moderating one of the rooms at
&lt;a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.com/"&gt;Bulgaria Web Summit&lt;/a&gt;. Expect more reports soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>HackFMI 3.0 Post-mortem</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/30/hackfmi-post-mortem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-30T00:03:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-04-30:blog/2014/04/30/hackfmi-post-mortem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hackfmi/hackfmi_beer.jpg" alt="HackFMI" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth &lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com/hackfmi3-winners/"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt;,
now traditional, hackathon was held this weekend.
It is over and I still can't wrap my head around what happened during these 3 nights. Here's
bits of code, beer, energy drinks and fun as I saw it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big thanks goes to Lilly and Misha who were running around like
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uL6e3co4Qqc"&gt;robots&lt;/a&gt; managing the day-to-day activities.
Kudos to the rest of the team as well because they've established HackFMI as a tradition
and people already ask when is going to be the next event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the topic was &lt;em&gt;Hack for charity&lt;/em&gt; and immediate goal of raising money for
a sick kid. Most of the teams got to work to meet these goals. Only a few had worked
on slightly different charity (broadly defined) ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite two apps were Blago-darenie and SMShelp although they were not
developed with Django.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blago-darenie.outernetnotes.com/"&gt;Blago-darenie&lt;/a&gt; is a simple WordPress
site listing donation campaigns. Instead of directly donating money one needs to
promise something (an action, an object, etc) and put a price tag on it. When the
promise is claimed the two parties donate the money to that particular campaign
and exchange the promised goods or services. I've promised to cook dinner
involving tasty meatballs from horse meat and serve one of my wine bottles to whoever
decides to donate 25 EUR. (disclaimer: I'm a good cook and love wine more than code).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ganev.bg/project-8/"&gt;SMShelp&lt;/a&gt; is an aggregator of donation campaigns via SMS
which are very popular in the country but lack a central repository for all of them.
A simple web site, live Android app and wonderful design secured the team the first place!
BTW Team 8 was &lt;a href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/"&gt;Adrian and Vihren&lt;/a&gt;
who took part in all previous editions as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TODO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm glad both organizers and teams had listened to some of my feedback but there are
still things to improve. The most obvious one was that a quick communication channel
to all the teams is needed. Facebook and email just didn't cut it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have couple of quick ideas involving Django and Twilio's cloud services.
Let me take a few more days to get it clear before going any further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;/me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found myself mentoring as much as I could helping folks with Django or just
with general ideal or concepts, serving cake provided by &lt;a href="http://www.chaosgroup.com"&gt;Chaos Group&lt;/a&gt;
and opening stacks of energy drinks, going door to door and letting teams know deployment and presentation
details for the last day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What surprised me a bit was that there were many new teams (some involving previous contestants)
who were very diverse in their technological background. This presented a challenge to
some of them as they had to use a technology which nobody on the team knew very well
and had to make a working app with that. One team even changed from Python to PHP in the
middle of day 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I was pretty much helping the HackFMI team with whatever I can,
checking on my favorite teams from time to time and giving access to cloud servers
left and right to people who needed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I missed the Grand Finale due to unexpected hardware problems involving
big iron and 150 litters of loose water :(. See you next time!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="hackfmi"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>FOSDEM 2014 Report - Day #2 Testing and Automation</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-03T22:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-02-03:blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Testing and Automation" src="/images/fosdem/2014/testing_automation.jpg" title="Testing and Automation" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM was hosting the
&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2014/schedule/track/testing_and_automation/"&gt;Testing and automation devroom&lt;/a&gt;
for the second year and this was the very reason I attended the conference. I managed to get in
early and stayed until 15:00 when I had to leave to catch my flight (which was late :(). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were 3 talks given by Red Hat employees in the testing devroom which was a nice opportunity
to meet some of the folks I've been working on IRC with. Unfortunately I didn't meet anyone from
Fedora QA. Not sure if they were attending or not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the talks were interesting so see the official schedule and video for more details. I will
highlight only the items I saw as particularly interesting or have not heard of before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ANSTE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANSTE - Advanced Network Service Testing Environment is a test infrastructure controller,
something like our own &lt;a href="http://beaker-project.org/"&gt;Beaker&lt;/a&gt; but designed to create complex
networking environments. I think it lacks many of the provisioning features built in Beaker
and integration with various hypervisors and bare-metal provisioning. What it seems to do better
(as far as I can tell from the talk) is to deploy virtual systems and create more complex network
configuration between them. Not something I will need in the near future but definitely worth
a look at. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;cwrap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cwrap is...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a set of tools to create a fully isolated network environment to test client/server components on a single host.
It provides synthetic account information, hostname resolution and support for privilege separation.
The heart of cwrap consists of three libraries you can preload to any executable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one was the coolest technology I've seen so far although I may not need to use it at all,
hmmm maybe testing DHCP fits the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It evolved from the Samba project and takes advantage of the order in which
libraries are searched when resolving functions. When you preload the project libraries
to any executable they will override standard libc functions for working with sockets,
user accounts and privilege escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The socket_wrapper library redirects networking sockets through local UNIX sockets and
gives you the ability to test applications which need privileged ports with a local developer
account. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nss_wrapper library provides artificial information for user and group accounts,
network name resolution using a hosts file and loading and testing of NSS modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uid_wrapper library allows uid switching as a normal user (e.g. fake root) and
supports user/group changing in the local thread using the syscalls (like glibc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these wrapper libraries are controlled via environment variables and definitely
makes testing of daemons and networking applications easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one was just scratching the surface of an entire branch of testing which I've not
even considered before. The talk also explains why it is hard to test documentation and
what possible solutions there are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you write user guides and technical articles which need to
stay current with the software this is definitely the place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automation in the Foreman Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last &lt;a href="http://ftp.osuosl.org/pub/fosdem//2014/previews/fosdem/fosdem_2014/dv/UD2218A/2014-02-02/12_51_36.ogv"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;
I've listened to. Definitely the best one from a general testing approach
point of view. Greg talked about starting with Foreman unit tests, then testing the merged PR,
then integration tests, then moving on to test the package build and then the resulting packages themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guys try to even test their own infrastructure (infra as code) and the test suites
they use to test everything else. It's all about automation and the level of confidence
you have in the entire process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the fact that no single testing approach can make you confident enough before shipping
the code and that they've taken into account changes which get introduced at various places
(e.g. 3rd party package upgrades, distro specific issues, infrastructure changes and such) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to attend only one session it would have been this one. There are many things for me
to take back home and apply to my work on Fedora and RHEL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find any of these topics remotely interesting I advise you to wait until FOSDEM video
team uploads the recordings and watch the entire session stream. I'm definitely missing a lot
of stuff which can't be easily reproduced in text form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also find my report of the first FOSDEM'14 day on Saturday
&lt;a href="/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-1-python-stands-lightning-talks/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category><category term="Fedora"></category><category term="QA"></category></entry><entry><title>FOSDEM 2014 Report - Day #1 Python, Stands and Lightning Talks</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-1-python-stands-lightning-talks/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-03T21:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2014-02-03:blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-1-python-stands-lightning-talks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As promised I'm starting catching up on blogging after being sick and traveling.
Here's my report of what I saw and found interesting at this year's
&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2014/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; which was held the last weekend in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening I've tried to attend the FOSDEM beer event at Delirium Cafe but
had a bad luck. At 21:30 the place was already packed with people. I managed to get
access to only one of the rooms but it looked like the wrong one :(. I think the space
is definitely small for all who are willing to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Saturday morning I did a quick sight-seeing most notably 
&lt;a href="www.migsworldwines.be/"&gt;Mig's wine shop&lt;/a&gt; and the area around it since I've never
been to this part of the city before. Then I took off to FOSDEM arriving at noon
(IOW not too late).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've spent most of my day at building K where project stands were and I stayed quite
a long time around the Python and Perl stands meeting new people and talking to them
about their upgrade practices and how they manage package dependencies
(aka promoting &lt;a href="http://www.dif.io"&gt;Difio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fedora Octopus" src="/images/fosdem/2014/fedora_octopus.jpg" title="Fedora Octopus" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fedora stand was busy with 3D printing this year. I've seen 3D printing
before but here I was amazed of the fine-grained quality of the pieces produced.
This is definitely something to have in mind if you are building physical products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Hat's presence was very strong this year. In addition to the numerous talks they
gave there were also oVirt and OpenShift Origin stands which were packed with people.
I couldn't even get close to say hi or take a picture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/fosdem/2014/doudou_linux.png" alt="DoudouLinux" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near the end of the day I went to listen to some of the lightning talks. The ones that
I liked the most were MATE Desktop and DoudouLinux. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing about MATE which I liked
is that they have a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mate-desktop/mate-university"&gt;MATE University&lt;/a&gt;
initiative which is targeting developers who want to learn how to develop MATE extensions.
This is pretty cool with respect to community and developers on-boarding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.doudoulinux.org"&gt;DoudouLinux&lt;/a&gt; is a Debian based distribution targeted at
small children (2 or 3 years old) based on simple desktop and educational activities.
I've met project leader and founder Jean-Michel Philippe who gave the talk. We chatted for
a while when Alejandro Simon from &lt;a href="http://www.kano.me/"&gt;Kano&lt;/a&gt; came around and showed us a prototype
of their computer for children. I will definitely give DoudouLinux a try and maybe pre-order Kano as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening there was a Python beer event at Delirium and after that dinner at
Chez Leon where I had snails and rabbit with cherries in cherry beer sauce.
I've had a few beers with Marc-Andre from &lt;a href="http://egenix.com"&gt;eGenix&lt;/a&gt;
and Charlie from &lt;a href="http://www.clark-consulting.eu/"&gt;Clark Consulting&lt;/a&gt; and the talk
was mostly about non-technical stuff which was nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that we went back to Delirium and
re-united with &lt;a href="http://akurtakov.blogspot.com"&gt;Alexander Kurtakov&lt;/a&gt; and other folks from
Red Hat for more cherry beer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Report of the second day of FOSDEM'14 on Sunday is
&lt;a href="/blog/2014/02/03/fosdem-2014-report-day-2-testing-and-automation/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category><category term="Fedora"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>HackFMI 2013 Hacker Gifts</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/10/25/hackfmi-2013-hacker-gifts/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-25T16:33:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-10-25:blog/2013/10/25/hackfmi-2013-hacker-gifts/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt; starts tonight!
&lt;a href="/blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/"&gt;During the previous edition&lt;/a&gt; of the hackathon
I gave one team a special personal gift based on my estimation of their hacker level!
Thanks to &lt;a href="http://blog.ganev.bg"&gt;Vihren Ganev&lt;/a&gt; (one of the gift winners) for reminding
me about that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I have even bigger items to give to those who think out of the box, who hack
their way around and are brave enough to try and change the world through software!
I have one 
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001AWCS52/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B001AWCS52&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=atodorovorg-20"&gt;Lenovo Thinkpad Business Backpack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B001AWCS52" width="1" height="1" border="0"  style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;
and one 
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00004TX7H/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00004TX7H&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=atodorovorg-20"&gt;Lowepro D-Res 20 AW Digital Camera Bag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00004TX7H" width="1" height="1" border="0"  style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;
(a bit bigger than the one on Amazon, easily fits a BlackBerry Z10) as seen on the pictures below.
Plus some small Red Hat branded items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lenovo bagpack" src="/images/hackfmi/lenovo_bagpack.jpg" title="Lenovo bagpack" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lowepro case" src="/images/hackfmi/lowepro_case.jpg" title="Lowepro case" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Get The Gifts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no rules, I will make a decision as I go along.
I can give away all items or none. It's up to you! Surprise me! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I will be mentoring the teams who decided to work with Django but
I'm happy to talk to anyone who needs help or just wants to grab the
cool stuff! See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="hackfmi"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Talk: Fedora Test Days in Sofia</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-09-14T23:11:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-09-14:blog/2013/09/14/upcoming-talk-fedora-test-days-in-sofia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On September 28th I will be giving a short talk about
&lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Test_Days"&gt;Fedora Test Days&lt;/a&gt; at the regular
Linux for Bulgarians
&lt;a href="http://www.linux-bg.org/cgi-bin/y/index.pl?page=news&amp;amp;key=459487176"&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt;.
I will explain what these are and how one can participate. I will also announce
my plans and schedule to organize some
&lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/QA/Fedora_20_test_days"&gt;Fedora 20 test days&lt;/a&gt;
locally in Sofia. If you are a fan of Fedora and want to file bugs and kick 
some developers' ass this is the way to do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other talks include Alexander Shopov's „Oracle's take on NoSQL“ which I wanted
to hear since this summer and TBA talks about MicroTik routers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference will take place on September 28th at the French Institute at
Sofia University
(see &lt;a href="http://conf.linux-bg.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/su-2.png"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt;).
It starts at 13:00 and my talk should be at the beginning. See you there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: this post was initially written on my &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/12y4ewJ"&gt;BlackBerry Z10&lt;/a&gt;
with Penzus Editor - another small step in 
&lt;a href="/blog/2013/08/01/laptop-vs-smartphone-part-one/"&gt;retiring my laptop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Fedora"></category><category term="QA"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Notes From Two Interesting GUADEC Talks</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-07T14:33:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-08-07:blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As this year's &lt;a href="https://www.guadec.org/"&gt;GUADEC&lt;/a&gt; is coming to an end
I'm publishing an interesting update from 
&lt;a href="https://cz.linkedin.com/in/mullerpetr"&gt;Petr Muller&lt;/a&gt; for 
those who were not able to attend.
Petr is a Senior Quality Engineer at Red Hat. His notes were
sent to an internal QE mailing list and re-published with permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;As this year&amp;#39;s GUADEC happened in the same building where I have my
other office, I decided to attend. I&amp;#39;m sharing my notes from the two
sessions I consider to be especially interesting for the audience of
this mailing list:

== How to not report your UX bug ==
Speaker:    Fabiana Simões
Blog:       http://fabianapsimoes.wordpress.com/
Twitter:    https://twitter.com/fabianapsimoes

Do not do this stuff:
* Do not simply present a preferred solution, but describe a problem (a
difficulty you are having, etc.)
* Do not use &amp;quot;This sucks&amp;quot; idiom, not even hidden in false niceties like
&amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s not user friendly&amp;quot;
* Do not talk for majority, when you are not entitled to (&amp;quot;most users
would like&amp;quot;)
* Do not consider all UX issues as minor: an inability to do stuff is
not a minor issue

What is actually interesting for the designer in a report?
* What were you trying to do?
* Why did you want to do it?
* What did you do?
* What happened?
* What were your expectations?

More notes
* Write as much as needed
* Describe what you see, did and *how you felt*
* Print screen is your friend!
* *Give praise*

== Extreme containment measures: keeping bug reports under control ==
Speaker:  Jean-Francois Fortin Tam
Homepage: http://jeff.ecchi.ca
Twitter:  https://twitter.com/nekohayo

Discussed the problem lot of OS projects are having: lot of useless
(old, irrelevant, waiting for decision no one wants to make) bug/rfe
reports in their bug tracking systems. Lots of food for thought about
our own projects, internal or external. Clever applications of
principles from personal productivity systems such as GTD and Inbox Zero
for bug tracking.  

The talk was mostly an applied version of this blog post, which is worth
reading:
http://jeff.ecchi.ca/blog/2012/10/08/reducing-our-core-apps-software-inventory/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I particularly like the UX bug reporting guide lines. Need to take those into
account when reporting UI issues. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still haven't read the second blog post which also looks interesting although 
not very applicable to me. After all I'm the person reporting bugs not the one
who decides what and when gets fixed.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="QA"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>The 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-07T12:10:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-08-07:blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two hours ago I've heard on the radio about
&lt;a href="http://acl2013.org/site/"&gt;the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics&lt;/a&gt;
which is held at the moment in Sofia
According to the guest speaker (a professor from Bulgarian Academy of Science) the official
program will be over today but the next two days will feature workshops and tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely not to be missed if you are in Sofia. I'm not unfortunately :(.
If you can please visit and share what you saw with me. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer Hackathon in Sofia</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-02T14:45:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-08-02:blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hackfmi/Logo_SummerHackFMI.png" alt="Summer HackFMI" style="display:block;clear:both" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com/spontanen-leten-hachathon/"&gt;summer hackathon&lt;/a&gt;
will be held in Sofia between 16th and 22nd of August. The week prior to the
event (12th to 15th) will be full of lectures and workshops to prepare the students
for their task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal this time is to create a new system for the Student Council organization
which will host their new website and also provide more transparency into the 
organization and the work they do. The idea is initiated by the chairman of the
council which is quite surprising for me to hear. You can read his motivation
(in Bulgarian) &lt;a href="https://github.com/Hackfmi/SummerHackathon/blob/master/motivation.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment it is agreed that the system will be written in Python and Django
and this is where I join. Together with Kiril Vladimirov I will be leading the
Python/Django lecture and workshop in one of the days, likely 14th of August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program is not yet finalized so I can't share more info. Please watch this
space for more details when they are available. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="hackfmi"></category></entry><entry><title>July Events - BlackBerry Mini Jam and Devel Conference</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/01/july-events-blackberry-mini-jam-and-devel-conference/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-01T11:06:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-07-01:blog/2013/07/01/july-events-blackberry-mini-jam-and-devel-conference/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you happen to be on holiday in Bulgaria but would still like to meet
some hackers there are three events this month that I find interesting:
Plovdiv Conf, BlackBerry Mini Developer Jam and Varna Conf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/code.jpg" alt="source code" style="display:block;clear:both;"/&gt;
Image: source code from a game development course held at Sofia University couple of years ago.
Own work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Plovdiv Conf&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://plovdivconf.com/"&gt;Plovdiv Conf&lt;/a&gt; will be held at the Plovdiv Fair
on July 6th 2013. There isn't an official program but the speaker profiles are
interesting. Among them are guys well known for their Ruby and Linux skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the given list I recognize only half the names. One speaker that sounds
interesting to me claims experience with programming assembler for the mainframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend &lt;a href="http://akurtakov.blogspot.com/"&gt;Alexander Kurtakov&lt;/a&gt; from Red Hat/Eclipse
will be there as well so I'm planning to attend this event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;BlackBerry 10 Mini Jam Sofia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organized by BlackBerry Developer Group Balkan the 
&lt;a href="http://bb10jamsofia2013.eventbrite.com/"&gt;BlackBerry 10 Mini Jam Sofia&lt;/a&gt; will be held
on July 11th 2013 at &lt;a href="http://betahaus.bg"&gt;betahaus Sofia&lt;/a&gt;. Last time I visited
a &lt;a href="/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/"&gt;BlackBerry developers session&lt;/a&gt; it
was very interesting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal interest at the moment is not developing mobile applications but I'd like to hear
more about the possibilities. My understanding is that BlackBerry 10 is much more flexible
as a development platform compared to Android and iOS. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will definitely attend this event because there will be a shiny new &lt;strong&gt;BlackBerry Z 10&lt;/strong&gt;
waiting for me there :). I will tell you how to secure one after I get it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Varna Conf&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://varnaconf.com/"&gt;Varna Conf&lt;/a&gt; is organized by the same people who do Plovdiv Conf.
It will be held on July 20th 2013 at Cherno More hotel in Varna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the speakers I don't know but there are couple of topics about testing and refactoring
which look interesting. However I will be more likely to socialize with the local development
groups rather than listening to all talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure if I will attend though. My initial plan was to attend but there are other personal
errands that are popping up. Given that it is not near Sofia I will probably skip it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you happen
to be on holiday at the Bulgarian sea side however, you should definitely check it out. And Varna is
a very nice city too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know if there are other interesting events in the vicinity! Use the comments and tell me where
are you going this month.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Balkan Venture Forum Sofia Post-mortem</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-23T13:29:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-05-23:blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/bkvf_sofia.png" alt="BkVF Sofia" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.balkanventureforum.org/"&gt;Balkan Venture Forum&lt;/a&gt; in Sofia is over. It's been two
very exciting days, full of many interesting talks both on stage and off stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were so many things that happened and so many new people I met that it will be hard
to mention all of that in a single blog post. I just want to highlight the things I enjoyed
the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Networking &amp;amp; pitching at the bar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been invited to BkVF long ago. However my initial intention was not to attend because
this month proved to be very busy. I've changed my mind after Boyan Benev, one of the organizers
invited me 10 days ago with an interesting proposal - distribute &lt;a href="http://www.dif.io"&gt;Difio&lt;/a&gt;'s beer mats at the bar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/difio_beermats.jpg" alt="Difio beer mats" style="float:left;clear:both;display:inline-block;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was there for the networking. As I used to say when people asked me if I was pitching&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pitching at the bar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Networking was very intensive both during the coffee breaks and cocktail and during the sessions.
I've now got close to 50 new business cards in my pocket. I've met very cool guys and gals both
developers and non-tech. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the companies that were pitching in the main hall I particularly liked
&lt;a href="http://imagga.com/"&gt;Imagga&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://transmetrics.eu/"&gt;Transmetrics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://kimola.com/"&gt;Kimola&lt;/a&gt;.
Imagga was probably the most deep-tech/science oriented company at BkVF while Transmetrics
and Kimola focus on cloud and big data solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;BlackBerry development session&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, I'm not into mobile technology nor smart phones but that may change soon. 
BlackBerry had a strong presence and I was able to talk to some of their developer
support folks.
The OS of BlackBerry 10 is based on QNX kernel with multiple SDKs available to write apps.
Most of all I like the fact that it is POSIX compliant with C/C++ native SDK available.
Qt/QML is also available. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm particularly interested in how hard it will be to port
some existing open source tools to BlackBerry. I'm talking Bash, Python and the
command line tools I currently use on Linux. I'll be contacting them in the near future
to get a device for testing and hacking and will keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="start-up"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>HackFMI Post-mortem</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-15T10:27:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-04-15:blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hackfmi/hackfmi_beer.jpg" alt="HackFMI" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt; event is now over :(. It was HUGE!
Kudos to the organizers, sponsors, mentors and all teams who took part and worked hard during
the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 100 people participated. There were 22 different teams presenting at the
finale yesterday evening. That in my opinion counts as a BIG success. I was surprised
to see so many people, lots of them first and second year at the university. There were
a good number of female hackers too, which I also didn't expect.
&lt;em&gt;DISCLAIMER: I've graduated a different university where the culture and male/female ratio
was different so my expectations were biased.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People had interesting ideas and were passionate about them. They set off hacking
on a big scale. At times they wanted to create too big of an application and had to
cut off some features due to time constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congrats to all of them and hopefully they continue hacking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Happened&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't able to talk to all the teams nor stay at the event full time but here is
how I saw things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organization was perfect. The best organized non-commercial local event I've seen in years.
There was food, beverages, T-shirts, even beer :). There were six big IT companies
&lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com/sponsors-and-partners/"&gt;sponsoring&lt;/a&gt; the
event. All of these are successful Bulgarian born companies.
Let that serve as an example!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The faculty was supporting the event too.
There were API and SQL dump for the teams to use. The entire building was open
during the weekend and during the night. Teams were able to make use of many rooms. 
From what I know some of the successful ideas will be implemented into the faculty
administration as well. All of this is a first time and quite unexpected for a 
Bulgarian university. I smell the wind of change already. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My technology view of the event is limited to the teams I've mentored explicitly and the ones
I happened to walk by and interfere with. Naturally I gravitated around 4 teams using
Django and found two teams using PHP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Django guys were doing well despite one of the teams not having any experience with it. 
Most of the applications were such that didn't require extensive knowledge of Django internals
but require mere programming of all features they wanted to implement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What stroked me is that folks were making their database models too complicated. 
I stumbled across two use cases in different teams where they wanted to have 
one to many or many to many relationships. I strongly advised against this.
Hopefully they will remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Django makes schema design a child's play and probably this is why lots of people
abuse and misuse that. My advise is keep the database as simple as possible
and move everything up the application layer. It's easier to change and to maintain
that way. Not to mention experienced DBAs are hard to find. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the DB simple and know your tools well! &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With PHP the case was pretty much the same. Guys had some extra fields in their DB schema
which were unnecessary. They also wanted to abuse the data types of the DB and not use native types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these technological misunderstandings are coming from inexperience, I know.
To get a closer look at why it is important to have a simple schema look at:
&lt;a href="http://ontwik.com/python/disqus-scaling-the-world%E2%80%99s-largest-django-application/"&gt;Disqus: Scaling the World’s Largest Django Application&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Hackers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During one of the breaks I was outside and one of the mentors complained that
ideas were pretty much standard. No screen scraping for additional information, 
no mashing up, no revolutionary ideas. Everybody was using the provided API and
SQL dumps. Well almost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite &lt;a href="https://github.com/vcrazy/project-6"&gt;teams&lt;/a&gt; set off to
write a PHP robot which will automatically login and extract information from
SUSI (the faculty information system). Unfortunately that didn't work so they
had to abandon it. They didn't known &lt;a href="http://docs.seleniumhq.org/"&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt;
and there was not enough time to
try and hack some browser side extension which will do the trick but they promised
to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of their unorthodox approach from the start they became my personal favorites
and received Red Hat swag from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Team Six" src="/images/hackfmi/hackfmi2013_team_six_rh_swag.jpg" title="Team Six" /&gt;
Adrian and Vihren are Team Six!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I didn't like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't like the fact that there was lots of duplicate work and ideas. Only one team
built a mobile application based on API and services provided by another team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest there's a #hackfmi IRC channel next time so that people can communicate
with each other and focus on building great apps not reinventing the wheel. 
&lt;strong&gt;Use IRC, you are hackers!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I was missing is that nobody proposed a pure cloud or big data application.
I don't know if there was enough data provided by the faculty for such kind of
ideas, probably there wasn't. Maybe next time there will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ohloh Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not participating actively except for a few hours of mentoring I found a
way to contribute. Many of the projects repositories are listed under
&lt;a href="https://www.ohloh.net/p/hackfmi2013"&gt;https://www.ohloh.net/p/hackfmi2013&lt;/a&gt; which provides some interesting insight
and stats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list is incomplete. Lots of teams didn't have any GitHub repos
or didn't push the code recently. I will be contacting all of them in the next few days
and hopefully we will have a more accurate statistics by the end of the week.
Expect a separate blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you missed this event you should be sorry. &lt;a href="/blog/2013/03/24/upcoming-hackathons-in-sofia/"&gt;You were warned&lt;/a&gt;!
If you attended please share your experience with me. What you liked, what you didn't. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="hackfmi"></category><category term="events"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Hackathons in Sofia</title><link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/03/24/upcoming-hackatons-in-sofia/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-24T22:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Todorov</name></author><id>tag:atodorov.org,2013-03-24:blog/2013/03/24/upcoming-hackatons-in-sofia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon"&gt;Hackathons&lt;/a&gt;
have been organized in Sofia and generally through Bulgaria for the
past several years but as far as I know they were mostly underground events.
There are two upcoming events which are somewhat different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Record Voting" Hackathon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="hackathon logo" src="/images/opengov.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organized by &lt;a href="http://iped.bg/en"&gt;INSTITUTE FOR PUBLIC ENVIRONMENT DEVELOPMENT&lt;/a&gt;
this hackathon is the first I know of, which will focus on government provided data.
The objective is to process data
(&lt;a href="http://results.cik.bg/el2011_t1.zip"&gt;sample&lt;/a&gt;) from the 2011 elections
and find persons who were able to vote in the last minute, between 20:00-21:00 hours thus
changing the election results by 20% in their voting section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event starts at 09:29 on 30th Mar 2013 @ &lt;a href="http://www.betahaus.bg"&gt;betahaus Sofia&lt;/a&gt;.
More info in Bulgarian &lt;a href="http://bogomil.info/4805"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://iped.bg/bg/news-read/news1c"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd love to attend but will be visiting a conference about mobile devices in
another town at the same time :(. If you do attend, let me know how fun it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dare to read more on the topic about open government? I recommend starting with
&lt;em&gt;Open Government: Collaboration, Transparency, and Participation in Practice by
Daniel Lathrop and Laurel Ruma&lt;/em&gt; (
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0596804350/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0596804350&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=atodorovorg-20"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=atodorovorg-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0596804350" width="1" height="1" border="0"  style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;
|
&lt;a href="http://www.dpbolvw.net/click-7040110-11260198?url=http%3A%2F%2Fshop.oreilly.com%2Fproduct%2F9780596804367.do%3Fcmp%3Daf-none-book-product_cj_9780596804350_%25zp&amp;cjsku=9780596804367" target="_top"&gt;O'Reilly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.tqlkg.com/image-7040110-11260198" width="0" height="0" border="0" style="display:none; margin:0;padding:0"/&gt;
). This is an excellent book with tons of examples and easy to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HackFMI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HackFMI" src="/images/hackfmi/cropped-hackfmi.png" title="HackFMI" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FMI stands for &lt;em&gt;Faculty of Mathematics and Informatics at the Sofia University&lt;/em&gt; 
(not where I graduated). It's one of the
best, arguably the best, places to study for an IT career. Like most other universities in Bulgaria
its administration and processes suck big time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackfmi.com/"&gt;HackFMI&lt;/a&gt; is the first ever hackathon which will focus on students
improving faculty/university systems and processes. This is HUGE! As far as I know it is also the first
hackathon which is supported by academia. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already &lt;a href="https://github.com/Hackfmi/Organization-Details/pull/2"&gt;volunteered&lt;/a&gt; to be
a mentor at HackFMI. I am looking forward to this. It will be fun. See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="open government"></category><category term="hackfmi"></category><category term="events"></category></entry></feed>