<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | atodorov.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-02T17:09:24+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes From Two Interesting GUADEC Talks]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T14:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/notes-from-two-interesting-guadec-talks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As this year's <a href="https://www.guadec.org/">GUADEC</a> is coming to an end
I'm publishing an interesting update from
<a href="cz.linkedin.com/in/mullerpetr">Petr Muller</a> for
those who were not able to attend.
Petr is a Senior Quality Engineer at Red Hat. His notes were
sent to an internal QE mailing list and re-published with permission.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>As this year's GUADEC happened in the same building where I have my<br/>other office, I decided to attend. I'm sharing my notes from the two<br/>sessions I consider to be especially interesting for the audience of<br/>this mailing list:</p></p><p><p>== How to not report your UX bug ==<br/>Speaker:    Fabiana Simões<br/>Blog:       http://fabianapsimoes.wordpress.com/<br/>Twitter:    https://twitter.com/fabianapsimoes</p></p><p><p>Do not do this stuff:<br/>* Do not simply present a preferred solution, but describe a problem (a<br/>difficulty you are having, etc.)<br/>* Do not use "This sucks" idiom, not even hidden in false niceties like<br/>"It's not user friendly"<br/>* Do not talk for majority, when you are not entitled to ("most users<br/>would like")<br/>* Do not consider all UX issues as minor: an inability to do stuff is<br/>not a minor issue</p></p><p><p>What is actually interesting for the designer in a report?<br/>* What were you trying to do?<br/>* Why did you want to do it?<br/>* What did you do?<br/>* What happened?<br/>* What were your expectations?</p></p><p><p>More notes<br/>* Write as much as needed<br/>* Describe what you see, did and <em>how you felt</em><br/>* Print screen is your friend!<br/>* <em>Give praise</em></p></p><p><p>== Extreme containment measures: keeping bug reports under control ==<br/>Speaker:  Jean-Francois Fortin Tam<br/>Homepage: http://jeff.ecchi.ca<br/>Twitter:  https://twitter.com/nekohayo</p></p><p><p>Discussed the problem lot of OS projects are having: lot of useless<br/>(old, irrelevant, waiting for decision no one wants to make) bug/rfe<br/>reports in their bug tracking systems. Lots of food for thought about<br/>our own projects, internal or external. Clever applications of<br/>principles from personal productivity systems such as GTD and Inbox Zero<br/>for bug tracking.</p></p><p><p>The talk was mostly an applied version of this blog post, which is worth<br/>reading:<br/>http://jeff.ecchi.ca/blog/2012/10/08/reducing-our-core-apps-software-inventory/</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Petr Muller</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I particularly like the UX bug reporting guide lines. Need to take those into
account when reporting UI issues.</p>

<p>I still haven't read the second blog post which also looks interesting although
not very applicable to me. After all I'm the person reporting bugs not the one
who decides what and when gets fixed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T12:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/07/the-51st-annual-meeting-of-the-association-for-computational-linguistics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two hours ago I've heard on the radio about
<a href="http://acl2013.org/site/">the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</a>
which is held at the moment in Sofia
According to the guest speaker (a professor from Bulgarian Academy of Science) the official
program will be over today but the next two days will feature workshops and tutorials.</p>

<p>Definitely not to be missed if you are in Sofia. I'm not unfortunately :(.
If you can please visit and share what you saw with me. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer Hackathon in Sofia]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T14:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/08/02/summer-hackathon-in-sofia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/hackfmi/Logo_SummerHackFMI.png" alt="Summer HackFMI" style="display:block;clear:both" /></p>

<p>A <a href="http://hackfmi.com/spontanen-leten-hachathon/">summer hackathon</a>
will be held in Sofia between 16th and 22nd of August. The week prior to the
event (12th to 15th) will be full of lectures and workshops to prepare the students
for their task.</p>

<p>The goal this time is to create a new system for the Student Council organization
which will host their new website and also provide more transparency into the
organization and the work they do. The idea is initiated by the chairman of the
council which is quite surprising for me to hear. You can read his motivation
(in Bulgarian) <a href="https://github.com/Hackfmi/SummerHackathon/blob/master/motivation.md">here</a>.</p>

<p>At the moment it is agreed that the system will be written in Python and Django
and this is where I join. Together with Kiril Vladimirov I will be leading the
Python/Django lecture and workshop in one of the days, likely 14th of August.</p>

<p>The program is not yet finalized so I can't share more info. Please watch this
space for more details when they are available.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[July Events - BlackBerry Mini Jam and Devel Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/01/july-events-blackberry-mini-jam-and-devel-conference/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T11:06:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/07/01/july-events-blackberry-mini-jam-and-devel-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you happen to be on holiday in Bulgaria but would still like to meet
some hackers there are three events this month that I find interesting:
Plovdiv Conf, BlackBerry Mini Developer Jam and Varna Conf.</p>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/code.jpg" alt="source code" style="display:block;clear:both;"/>
Image: source code from a game development course held at Sofia University couple of years ago.
Own work.</p>

<h2>Plovdiv Conf</h2>

<p><a href="http://plovdivconf.com/">Plovdiv Conf</a> will be held at the Plovdiv Fair
on July 6th 2013. There isn't an official program but the speaker profiles are
interesting. Among them are guys well known for their Ruby and Linux skills.</p>

<p>From the given list I recognize only half the names. One speaker that sounds
interesting to me claims experience with programming assembler for the mainframe.</p>

<p>My friend <a href="http://akurtakov.blogspot.com/">Alexander Kurtakov</a> from Red Hat/Eclipse
will be there as well so I'm planning to attend this event.</p>

<h2>BlackBerry 10 Mini Jam Sofia</h2>

<p>Organized by BlackBerry Developer Group Balkan the
<a href="http://bb10jamsofia2013.eventbrite.com/">BlackBerry 10 Mini Jam Sofia</a> will be held
on July 11th 2013 at <a href="http://betahaus.bg">betahaus Sofia</a>. Last time I visited
a <a href="/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/">BlackBerry developers session</a> it
was very interesting.</p>

<p>My personal interest at the moment is not developing mobile applications but I'd like to hear
more about the possibilities. My understanding is that BlackBerry 10 is much more flexible
as a development platform compared to Android and iOS.</p>

<p>I will definitely attend this event because there will be a shiny new <strong>BlackBerry Z 10</strong>
waiting for me there :). I will tell you how to secure one after I get it.</p>

<h2>Varna Conf</h2>

<p><a href="http://varnaconf.com/">Varna Conf</a> is organized by the same people who do Plovdiv Conf.
It will be held on July 20th 2013 at Cherno More hotel in Varna.</p>

<p>Most of the speakers I don't know but there are couple of topics about testing and refactoring
which look interesting. However I will be more likely to socialize with the local development
groups rather than listening to all talks.</p>

<p>I'm not sure if I will attend though. My initial plan was to attend but there are other personal
errands that are popping up. Given that it is not near Sofia I will probably skip it.</p>

<p>If you happen
to be on holiday at the Bulgarian sea side however, you should definitely check it out. And Varna is
a very nice city too.</p>

<p>Let me know if there are other interesting events in the vicinity! Use the comments and tell me where
are you going this month.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Balkan Venture Forum Sofia Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T13:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/05/23/balkan-venture-forum-sofia-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/bkvf_sofia.png" alt="BkVF Sofia" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"/></p>

<p><a href="http://www.balkanventureforum.org/">Balkan Venture Forum</a> in Sofia is over. It's been two
very exciting days, full of many interesting talks both on stage and off stage.</p>

<p>There were so many things that happened and so many new people I met that it will be hard
to mention all of that in a single blog post. I just want to highlight the things I enjoyed
the most.</p>

<br /><br />


<h2>Networking &amp; pitching at the bar</h2>

<p>I've been invited to BkVF long ago. However my initial intention was not to attend because
this month proved to be very busy. I've changed my mind after Boyan Benev, one of the organizers
invited me 10 days ago with an interesting proposal - distribute <a href="http://www.dif.io">Difio</a>'s beer mats at the bar!</p>

<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/difio_beermats.jpg" alt="Difio beer mats" style="float:left;clear:both;display:inline-block;"/></p>

<p>So I was there for the networking. As I used to say when people asked me if I was pitching</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I am pitching at the bar!</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Networking was very intensive both during the coffee breaks and cocktail and during the sessions.
I've now got close to 50 new business cards in my pocket. I've met very cool guys and gals both
developers and non-tech.</p>

<p>From the companies that were pitching in the main hall I particularly liked
<a href="http://imagga.com/">Imagga</a>, <a href="http://transmetrics.eu/">Transmetrics</a> and <a href="http://kimola.com/">Kimola</a>.
Imagga was probably the most deep-tech/science oriented company at BkVF while Transmetrics
and Kimola focus on cloud and big data solutions.</p>

<h2>BlackBerry development session</h2>

<p>OK, I'm not into mobile technology nor smart phones but that may change soon.
BlackBerry had a strong presence and I was able to talk to some of their developer
support folks.
The OS of BlackBerry 10 is based on QNX kernel with multiple SDKs available to write apps.
Most of all I like the fact that it is POSIX compliant with C/C++ native SDK available.
Qt/QML is also available.</p>

<p>I'm particularly interested in how hard it will be to port
some existing open source tools to BlackBerry. I'm talking Bash, Python and the
command line tools I currently use on Linux. I'll be contacting them in the near future
to get a device for testing and hacking and will keep you posted.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
