<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-11T16:52:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary of Evolve Digital]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T22:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/evolve_digital.jpg" title="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" alt="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" /></p>

<p>Yesterday I've visited an event organized by the
<a href="http://www.atlantic-club.org/index.php?en">Atlantic Club of Bulgaria</a> which
officially marked the launch of a digital national alliance in Bulgaria. This is
part of an initiative of the European Commission, called
<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/grand-coalition-digital-jobs">Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs</a>,
which aims to address the lack of
sufficient amount and quality professionals in Europe working in the
field of Information and Communication technologies.</p>

<p>The first part was few short keynotes, including one from deputy prime minister
and memorandum signing and group photo. In the keynotes (and afterwards)
the stress was on the lack of relevant ICT skills and the need of an estimated
1 million digital workers by 2020 in EU alone.</p>

<p>The next two sessions were panel discussions. The first one presenting the local
chapter of the Digital Coalition in Bulgaria.</p>

<p>The goals of the coalition are to:</p>

<ul>
<li>help more people master more digital skills (not only as developers but also
proper usage of social media, how to create content, etc)</li>
<li>enable more people to choose digital jobs</li>
<li>help local talents present themselves on the global scene</li>
</ul>


<p>How it (is supposed to) works:</p>

<ul>
<li>initiate own ideas and propose them for implementation (to the ICT industry and broad public I guess)</li>
<li>stimulate learning through doing, learning by example using real use cases</li>
<li>help (and possibly sponsor) outside projects and ideas</li>
</ul>


<p>Then the various companies supporting the coalition pledged how they are going to
help. The most interesting news from this panel was the announcement of a new HP
data center in Sofia which will be used as a training lab with access available to
students.</p>

<p>The second panel was about education and how to bridge the gap! The interesting points were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Ministry of Education and Science admits they have finally realized that our educational
system and programs are behind current tendencies and need concrete steps in order to boost
education and science research;</li>
<li>Samsung will open their innovation lab at Sofia University to outside students as well;</li>
<li>We need to pay more attention to content and training of teachers because they also have
a skills gap while young children do not;</li>
</ul>


<p>I particularly liked what Prof. Petar Kenderov from the Institute of Mathematics and Informatics
at Bulgarian Academy of Sciences said - in the outside world children are constantly sharing
and communicating with each other while at school (also to some extent in universities) they
are expected to not communicate, not share and keep quiet. He emphasized the value of learning through
experimentation vs. learning through reading and writing, e.g. the current way things work
and the old way of teaching.</p>

<p>Another thing that was obvious was that otherwise competing companies (e.g. Microsoft, Oracle, SAP,
VMware) were working together to fix some of the problems mentioned. However I'm a bit skeptical
that large multi-national companies will be flexible enough to make a positive change.
I'd bet on the independent organizations like <a href="https://hackbulgaria.com/">HackBulgaria</a> and
Svetlin Nakov's <a href="https://softuni.bg/">Software University</a> or initiatives by local Bulgarian companies
like the already proven <a href="http://academy.telerik.com/">Telerik Academy</a>.</p>

<p>Here's the entire program of the event, for anyone interested:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>“EVOLVE DIGITAL”<br/>10th June 2014 (Tuesday)</p></p><p><p>10:00 – 10:10 Opening: Gergana Passy, Digital Champion Bulgaria</p></p><p><p>10:10 – 10:20 Daniela Bobeva, Deputy Prime-Minister of the Republic of Bulgaria<br/>10:20 – 10:30 Constantijn van Oranje, Head of Cabinet of Vice-President of EC Neelie Kroes<br/>10:30 – 10:40 Jonathan Murray, Director, Digital Europe<br/>Special guest: Sandi Češko, Founder &amp; President, Studio Moderna</p></p><p><p>10:40 – 10:50 Memorandum Signing and Group Photo<br/>10:50 – 11:00 Pause</p></p><p><p>11:00 – 12:15 Digital Coalition Bulgaria</p></p><p><pre><code>            Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li</p><p>            Rennie Popcheva, CEO, Digital Coalition Bulgaria<br/>            Boyko Iaramov, Co-founder &amp; Chief Process Officer, Telerik<br/>            Marta Poslad, Senior Policy Advisor, CEE Google<br/>            Petar Ivanov, General Manager, Microsoft Bulgaria<br/>            Iravan Hira, General Manager, Hewlett-Packard Bulgaria<br/>            Atanas Dobrev, CEO, VIVACOM<br/>            Danny Gooris, Senior Manager, Oracle Academy<br/>            Dimitar Dimitrov, Relationship Business Development, Lenovo<br/>            Stamen Kochkov, Vice-president, SAP Labs Bulgaria, Chairman of BASSCOM<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>12:15 – 12:30 Coffee Break</p></p><p><p>12:30 – 13:45 Education in the Digital Era</p></p><p><pre><code>            Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li</p><p>            Ivan Krastev, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Education and Science, Republic of Bulgaria<br/>            George Stoytchev, Executive Director, Open Society Institute Sofia<br/>            Sabina Stirb, Public Affairs &amp; Corporate Citizenship Manager, Samsung<br/>            Prof. Petar Kenderov, Institute of Mathematics and Informatics, Bulgarian<br/>            Academy of Sciences<br/>            Dr. George Sharkov, Director, European Software Institute - Center Eastern<br/>            Europe<br/>            Elena Marinova, President, Musala Soft, Chair of the Educational Commission,<br/>            Bulgarian Association of Information Technologies<br/>            Svetlin Nakov, Founder, Software University<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>13:45 – Lunch in Restaurant “At the Eagles”</p></p><p><pre><code>            11 Dyakon Ygnatiy str., in the building of Ministry of transport, 18th Floor<br/></code></pre></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bulgaria Web Summit Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T09:02:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week ended up with <a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.com/">Bulgaria Web Summit</a>.
The event was very big this year, with 4 halls and 600 visitors.
I was moderating the so called <em>JavaScript</em> hall and will concentrate on
what happened there.</p>

<p><img src="/images/bgws2014.jpg" title="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" alt="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" />
This is what my hall looked like at around 10:00 and stayed pretty much the same
during the entire day.</p>

<p>Speakers at hall Rhodopi were (in order of appearance)</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/delian">Delian Delchev</a> talking about the JavaScript
revolution taking over the world and how this language has become the most
widely used programming language in the world.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/hkdobrev">Haralan Dobrev</a> with some tips about development
workflows, git, continuous integration and unit testing.</li>
<li>Yoga for Geeks during the lunch break.</li>
<li>Boyan Dzhumakov with topics about home automation and Internet of things, who
demonstrated his bed side lamp controlled via a light sensor and Arduino.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.boyanov.org/">Neven Boyanov</a> continuing on the hardware topics with
comparison of ATmel, Arduino and Raspberry Pi and showing more examples of
small programmable devices.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/attodorov">Angel Todorov</a> from Infragistics with a very
interesting talk about JavaScript instrumentation for performance analysis.
A very cool presentation and you should definitely check out his
<a href="https://github.com/attodorov/cheetah.js">cheetah.js</a> framework.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/KrasimirTsonev">Krasimir Tsonev</a> with
<a href="http://absurdjs.com/">AbsurdJS</a> - a JavaScript library with superpowers.
Teaser: Krasimir is also publishing a book caled
<a href="https://twitter.com/atodorov_/status/472723298053537792">Node.js Blueprints</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/krokodilerian">Vasil Kolev</a> with a talk about security
and web service design and how most of the web is doing it wrong :).</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately there is no video or audio recording available. If you find
some of the talks interesting and would like to get more info about it let
me know. I will ask the presenters to share their slides or give more details
where possible.</p>

<p>Don't worry if you've missed the Web Summit in Sofia. There will be another one
in the autumn, held at Veliko Tarnovo. For more info please subscribe to the
<a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.us6.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=44058a4036fe9516b0ea2004c&amp;id=e768a8c09a">newsletter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DigitalK Day 2 Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T20:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing to report on the last few events that took place in Sofia this week.</p>

<p>Day #2 of DigitalK started with the presentation of Piotr Jas of BlaBla Car.
What I really liked about it (picture TBA) was one particular graph depicting
the various types of travel (time before travel vs. cost of travel) and
visualizing different industries (e.g. air travel) or competitor companies.
The image clearly exhibited a blank space which is the exact market segment
where BlaBla Car have positioned themselves in.</p>

<p>A very practical and easy to use tool for entrepreneurs in my opinion.</p>

<p>From the rest of the keynotes I can outline two in particular:
Ivan Hernandez' <em>Disruptive Innovation and the future of Digital Transformation</em>
and <em>The future of Tech and Communities</em> by Tim Röhrich.</p>

<p>I liked them because both were very inspirational although not telling you
something which you haven't heard before. They were basically reinforcing
the spirit of the event.</p>

<p>In the small hall there was a workshop called
<em>How to turn a good idea into a successful start-up</em> led by Daniela Neumann,
which didn't turn out to be what I expected. She was talking about the early
cycle of idea/customer validation and I don't remember any particular example
being shown. Frankly most of the people have heard about this before (myself included)
and were quite bored. Not many of them stayed till the end.</p>

<p>The evening continued with the already traditional Silicon Drinkabout in Sofia
which hosted many of the conference attendees. I did a quick visit only
because I had to prepare myself for Bulgaria Web Summit on the next day!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twilio meetup and DigitalK 2014 Day 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/29/twilio-meetup-and-digitalk-2014-day-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T22:31:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/05/29/twilio-meetup-and-digitalk-2014-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The conference season (this week) is officially open! So here's my report about it.</p>

<p>It started by accident last evening with a
<a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/629009950539772/">warm-up event</a>
sponsored by Twilio at betahaus Sofia. I had the pleasure to have a long chat
with <a href="https://twitter.com/lilaineurope">Lisa from Twilio</a> over a few beers.</p>

<p>Today was Day #1 of <a href="http://digitalk.bg/">DigitalK</a> which is the leading SEE
technology event. I've also visited the event last year and must say that this
time it is bigger. The main hall was totally packed. The WiFi connectivity has been
improved since last year but still sucked. I had more success using my 3G instead.</p>

<p>The most interesting part of Day #1 was the mini Seedcamp session which presented
10 startups. In order of appearance they are</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.adtapsy.com/">AdTapsy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bitcoini.com/">Bitcoini.com</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ikollect.net/">iKollect</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.rocketads.co/">RocketAds</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.scalewhale.eu/">ScaleWhale</a></li>
<li><a href="https://angel.co/smartoken">Smartoken</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stepsss.co/">Stepsss</a></li>
<li><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=co.talkie_kids.talkie">Talkie</a></li>
<li><a href="http://viblast.com/">Viblast</a></li>
<li><a href="http://wiziva.com">Wiziva</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Viblast, Stepsss and Talkie were the 3 finalists who also presented at the main hall.
Needless to say the coolest one from technology point of view is Viblast, which is
a peer-to-peer video streaming platform, utilizing WebRTC. They were also strong at the
presentation and look very strong at the business level as well. I wish them good luck.</p>

<p>Stepsss is essentially a shoe sole with sensors paired with smart-phone apps to
give runners more info and feedback. I like it because they are a hardware company
although there's lots of competition in this space. I'd like to beta test their product
and see what happens when I go dancing all night long :).</p>

<p>Talkie is an educational app for children which helps them learn new languages. I had the
pleasure to see it in action before the actual presentation. The design is very cool
and the app does seem usable and complete. However I don't see much of a technological
challenge here and I'm not sure how will they deal with the strong competition in the ed-tech
space. We'll have to wait and see.</p>

<p>From the rest ScaleWhale and Smartoken do seem interesting but I really failed to get how things
will be organized on the technology side. Both ideas are run by a single person team, which
is a recipe for disaster (judging from my own experience).</p>

<p>Tomorrow is Day #2 of DigitalK and on Saturday I'm moderating one of the rooms at
<a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.com/">Bulgaria Web Summit</a>. Expect more reports soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HackFMI 3.0 Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/30/hackfmi-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-30T00:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/04/30/hackfmi-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://atodorov.org/images/hackfmi/hackfmi_beer.jpg" alt="HackFMI" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /></p>

<p>The fourth <a href="http://hackfmi.com/hackfmi3-winners/">HackFMI</a>,
now traditional, hackathon was held this weekend.
It is over and I still can't wrap my head around what happened during these 3 nights. Here's
bits of code, beer, energy drinks and fun as I saw it.</p>

<p>A big thanks goes to Lilly and Misha who were running around like
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uL6e3co4Qqc">robots</a> managing the day-to-day activities.
Kudos to the rest of the team as well because they've established HackFMI as a tradition
and people already ask when is going to be the next event.</p>

<h2>What</h2>

<p>This year the topic was <em>Hack for charity</em> and immediate goal of raising money for
a sick kid. Most of the teams got to work to meet these goals. Only a few had worked
on slightly different charity (broadly defined) ideas.</p>

<p>My favorite two apps were Blago-darenie and SMShelp although they were not
developed with Django.</p>

<p><a href="http://blago-darenie.outernetnotes.com/">Blago-darenie</a> is a simple WordPress
site listing donation campaigns. Instead of directly donating money one needs to
promise something (an action, an object, etc) and put a price tag on it. When the
promise is claimed the two parties donate the money to that particular campaign
and exchange the promised goods or services. I've promised to cook dinner
involving tasty meatballs from horse meat and serve one of my wine bottles to whoever
decides to donate 25 EUR. (disclaimer: I'm a good cook and love wine more than code).</p>

<p><a href="http://ganev.bg/project-8/">SMShelp</a> is an aggregator of donation campaigns via SMS
which are very popular in the country but lack a central repository for all of them.
A simple web site, live Android app and wonderful design secured the team the first place!
BTW Team 8 was <a href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2013/04/15/hackfmi-post-mortem/">Adrian and Vihren</a>
who took part in all previous editions as well.</p>

<h2>TODO</h2>

<p>I'm glad both organizers and teams had listened to some of my feedback but there are
still things to improve. The most obvious one was that a quick communication channel
to all the teams is needed. Facebook and email just didn't cut it.</p>

<p>I already have couple of quick ideas involving Django and Twilio's cloud services.
Let me take a few more days to get it clear before going any further.</p>

<h2>/me</h2>

<p>I found myself mentoring as much as I could helping folks with Django or just
with general ideal or concepts, serving cake provided by <a href="http://www.chaosgroup.com">Chaos Group</a>
and opening stacks of energy drinks, going door to door and letting teams know deployment and presentation
details for the last day.</p>

<p>What surprised me a bit was that there were many new teams (some involving previous contestants)
who were very diverse in their technological background. This presented a challenge to
some of them as they had to use a technology which nobody on the team knew very well
and had to make a working app with that. One team even changed from Python to PHP in the
middle of day 2.</p>

<p>On Sunday I was pretty much helping the HackFMI team with whatever I can,
checking on my favorite teams from time to time and giving access to cloud servers
left and right to people who needed them.</p>

<p>Unfortunately I missed the Grand Finale due to unexpected hardware problems involving
big iron and 150 litters of loose water :(. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
