<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | atodorov.org - you can logoff, but you can never leave]]></title>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atodorov.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-17T10:25:40+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://atodorov.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Todorov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Data Event Coming to Sofia]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/07/01/open-data-event-coming-to-sofia/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-01T11:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/07/01/open-data-event-coming-to-sofia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/17565601186">Open Data and Intelligent Government</a>
is the name of upcoming event organized by <a href="http://sofiatech.bg/en/">Sofia Tech Park</a>
on July 14th.</p>

<p>The (preliminary) topics for this event are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Government vision for opening data;</li>
<li>Presentation of national platform for open data;</li>
<li>Legal aspects of open data;</li>
<li>Presentation of <a href="http://opendata.government.bg/">Bulgarian open data portal</a>;</li>
<li>Europe and open data;</li>
<li>Open, coordinated e-government for citizens and business;</li>
<li>What has already been done by municipalities in Bulgaria;</li>
<li>Strategy of Sofia municipality for open data;</li>
<li>Upcoming open data programming contest organized by Sofia municipality.</li>
</ul>


<p>I will also be participating in this event by covering two topics I'm close to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Entrepreneurship and open data - sharing my limited experience with Difio
and processing open data;</li>
<li>Technical tips for successful open data hackathon - sharing my observations as
a mentor at <a href="http://hackfmi.com">HackFMI</a> and giving some recommendations which will
help the alleged open data contest make a difference not being just another dull event
organized by governmental agencies.</li>
</ul>


<p>So far other confirmed speakers are Rado from <a href="http://hackbulgaria.com">HackBulgaria</a>/
<a href="http://hackfmi.com">HackFMI</a> and <a href="https://www.obshtestvo.bg/">Obshtestvo.bg</a> which are
working in the field of open government and open data.</p>

<p>I'm also in touch with the event organizers and helping a little bit with the program.
If you're interested in speaking please get in touch with me ASAP.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DEVit Conf 2015 Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/22/devit-conf-2015-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T12:01:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2015/05/22/devit-conf-2015-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a busy week after <a href="http://devitconf.org/">DEVit conf</a> took place in
Thessaloniki. Here are my impressions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/devit2015.jpg" title="Crack, Train, Fix, Release" alt="Crack, Train, Fix, Release" /></p>

<h2>Sessions</h2>

<p>I've started the day with the session called "Crack, Train, Fix, Release" by
Chris Heilmann. While it was very interesting for some unknown reason I
was expecting a talk more closely related to software testing. Unfortunately at the
same time in the other room was a talk called "Integration Testing from the Trenches"
by Nicolas Frankel which I missed.</p>

<p>At the end Chris answered the question "What to do about old versions of IE ?".
And the answer pretty much was "Don't try to support everything, leave them with
basic functionality so that users can achieve what they came for on your website.
Don't put nice buttons b/c IE 6 users are not used to nice things and they get confused."</p>

<p>If you remember I had a similar question to Jeremy Keith at
<a href="/blog/2015/04/20/videos-from-bulgaria-web-summit-2015/">Bulgaria Web Summit</a> last month
and the answer was similar:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Q: Which one is Jeremy's favorite device/browser to develop for.<br/>A: Your approach is wrong and instead we should be thinking in terms of what features are<br/>essential or non-essential for our websites and develop around features<br/>(if supported, if not supported) not around browsers!</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Btw I did ask Chris if he knows Jeremy and he does.</p>

<p>After the coffee break there was "JavaScript ♥ Unicode" by Mathias Bynens which
I saw last year at <a href="http://how.camp/">How Camp</a> in Veliko Tarnovo so I just stopped by
to say hi and went to listen to
"The future of responsive web design: web component queries" by Nikos Zinas.
As far as I understood Nikos is a local rock-star developer. I'm not much into web
development but the opportunity to create your own HTML components (tags) looks
very promising. I guess there will be more business coming for
<a href="http://telerik.com">Telerik</a> :).</p>

<p>I wanted to listen to "Live Productive Coder" by Heinz Kabutz but that one started
in Greek so I switched the room for
"iOS real time content modifications using websockets" by  Benny Weingarten-Gabbay.</p>

<p>After lunch I went straight for
"Introduction to Docker: What is it and why should I care?" by Ian Miell
which IMO was the most interesting talk of the day. It wasn't very technical but
managed to clear some of the mysticism around Docker and what it actually is.
I tried to grab a few minutes of Ian's time and we found topics of common interest
to talk about (<a href="http://www.projectatomic.io/">Project Atomic</a> anyone?) but later
failed to find him and continue the talk. I guess I'll have to follow online.</p>

<p>Tim Perry with "Your Web Stack Would Betray You In An Instant" made a great show.
The room was packed, I myself was actually standing the whole time. He described a series
of failures across the entire web development stack which gave developers hard times
patching and upgrading their services. The lesson: everything fails, be prepared!</p>

<p>The last talk I visited was "GitHub Automation" by Forbes Lindesay. It was more of an
inspirational talk, rather than technical one. GitHub provides cool API so why not use it?</p>

<h2>Organization</h2>

<p><img src="/images/devit2015team.jpg" title="DEVit team" alt="DEVit team" /></p>

<p>From what I know this is the first year of DEVit. For a first timer the team did great!
I particularly liked the two coffee breaks before lunch and in the early afternoon and the
sponsors pitches in between the main talks.</p>

<p>All talks were recorded but I have no idea what's happening with the videos!</p>

<p>I will definitely make a point of visiting Thessaloniki more often and follow the local
IT and start-up scenes there. And tonight is Silicon Drinkabout which will be the official
after party of <a href="http://digitalk.bg/">DigitalK</a> in Sofia.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary of Evolve Digital]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T22:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/11/summary-of-evolve-digital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/evolve_digital.jpg" title="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" alt="Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs" /></p>

<p>Yesterday I've visited an event organized by the
<a href="http://www.atlantic-club.org/index.php?en">Atlantic Club of Bulgaria</a> which
officially marked the launch of a digital national alliance in Bulgaria. This is
part of an initiative of the European Commission, called
<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/grand-coalition-digital-jobs">Grand Coalition for Digital Jobs</a>,
which aims to address the lack of
sufficient amount and quality professionals in Europe working in the
field of Information and Communication technologies.</p>

<p>The first part was few short keynotes, including one from deputy prime minister
and memorandum signing and group photo. In the keynotes (and afterwards)
the stress was on the lack of relevant ICT skills and the need of an estimated
1 million digital workers by 2020 in EU alone.</p>

<p>The next two sessions were panel discussions. The first one presenting the local
chapter of the Digital Coalition in Bulgaria.</p>

<p>The goals of the coalition are to:</p>

<ul>
<li>help more people master more digital skills (not only as developers but also
proper usage of social media, how to create content, etc)</li>
<li>enable more people to choose digital jobs</li>
<li>help local talents present themselves on the global scene</li>
</ul>


<p>How it (is supposed to) works:</p>

<ul>
<li>initiate own ideas and propose them for implementation (to the ICT industry and broad public I guess)</li>
<li>stimulate learning through doing, learning by example using real use cases</li>
<li>help (and possibly sponsor) outside projects and ideas</li>
</ul>


<p>Then the various companies supporting the coalition pledged how they are going to
help. The most interesting news from this panel was the announcement of a new HP
data center in Sofia which will be used as a training lab with access available to
students.</p>

<p>The second panel was about education and how to bridge the gap! The interesting points were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Ministry of Education and Science admits they have finally realized that our educational
system and programs are behind current tendencies and need concrete steps in order to boost
education and science research;</li>
<li>Samsung will open their innovation lab at Sofia University to outside students as well;</li>
<li>We need to pay more attention to content and training of teachers because they also have
a skills gap while young children do not;</li>
</ul>


<p>I particularly liked what Prof. Petar Kenderov from the Institute of Mathematics and Informatics
at Bulgarian Academy of Sciences said - in the outside world children are constantly sharing
and communicating with each other while at school (also to some extent in universities) they
are expected to not communicate, not share and keep quiet. He emphasized the value of learning through
experimentation vs. learning through reading and writing, e.g. the current way things work
and the old way of teaching.</p>

<p>Another thing that was obvious was that otherwise competing companies (e.g. Microsoft, Oracle, SAP,
VMware) were working together to fix some of the problems mentioned. However I'm a bit skeptical
that large multi-national companies will be flexible enough to make a positive change.
I'd bet on the independent organizations like <a href="https://hackbulgaria.com/">HackBulgaria</a> and
Svetlin Nakov's <a href="https://softuni.bg/">Software University</a> or initiatives by local Bulgarian companies
like the already proven <a href="http://academy.telerik.com/">Telerik Academy</a>.</p>

<p>Here's the entire program of the event, for anyone interested:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>“EVOLVE DIGITAL”<br/>10th June 2014 (Tuesday)</p></p><p><p>10:00 – 10:10 Opening: Gergana Passy, Digital Champion Bulgaria</p></p><p><p>10:10 – 10:20 Daniela Bobeva, Deputy Prime-Minister of the Republic of Bulgaria<br/>10:20 – 10:30 Constantijn van Oranje, Head of Cabinet of Vice-President of EC Neelie Kroes<br/>10:30 – 10:40 Jonathan Murray, Director, Digital Europe<br/>Special guest: Sandi Češko, Founder &amp; President, Studio Moderna</p></p><p><p>10:40 – 10:50 Memorandum Signing and Group Photo<br/>10:50 – 11:00 Pause</p></p><p><p>11:00 – 12:15 Digital Coalition Bulgaria</p></p><p><pre><code>            Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li</p><p>            Rennie Popcheva, CEO, Digital Coalition Bulgaria<br/>            Boyko Iaramov, Co-founder &amp; Chief Process Officer, Telerik<br/>            Marta Poslad, Senior Policy Advisor, CEE Google<br/>            Petar Ivanov, General Manager, Microsoft Bulgaria<br/>            Iravan Hira, General Manager, Hewlett-Packard Bulgaria<br/>            Atanas Dobrev, CEO, VIVACOM<br/>            Danny Gooris, Senior Manager, Oracle Academy<br/>            Dimitar Dimitrov, Relationship Business Development, Lenovo<br/>            Stamen Kochkov, Vice-president, SAP Labs Bulgaria, Chairman of BASSCOM<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>12:15 – 12:30 Coffee Break</p></p><p><p>12:30 – 13:45 Education in the Digital Era</p></p><p><pre><code>            Moderator: Boyan Benev, Founder, Forward.li</p><p>            Ivan Krastev, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Education and Science, Republic of Bulgaria<br/>            George Stoytchev, Executive Director, Open Society Institute Sofia<br/>            Sabina Stirb, Public Affairs &amp; Corporate Citizenship Manager, Samsung<br/>            Prof. Petar Kenderov, Institute of Mathematics and Informatics, Bulgarian<br/>            Academy of Sciences<br/>            Dr. George Sharkov, Director, European Software Institute - Center Eastern<br/>            Europe<br/>            Elena Marinova, President, Musala Soft, Chair of the Educational Commission,<br/>            Bulgarian Association of Information Technologies<br/>            Svetlin Nakov, Founder, Software University<br/></code></pre></p><p><p>13:45 – Lunch in Restaurant “At the Eagles”</p></p><p><pre><code>            11 Dyakon Ygnatiy str., in the building of Ministry of transport, 18th Floor<br/></code></pre></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bulgaria Web Summit Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T09:02:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/02/bulgaria-web-summit-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week ended up with <a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.com/">Bulgaria Web Summit</a>.
The event was very big this year, with 4 halls and 600 visitors.
I was moderating the so called <em>JavaScript</em> hall and will concentrate on
what happened there.</p>

<p><img src="/images/bgws2014.jpg" title="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" alt="BGWS Rhodopi Hall at 10:00" />
This is what my hall looked like at around 10:00 and stayed pretty much the same
during the entire day.</p>

<p>Speakers at hall Rhodopi were (in order of appearance)</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/delian">Delian Delchev</a> talking about the JavaScript
revolution taking over the world and how this language has become the most
widely used programming language in the world.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/hkdobrev">Haralan Dobrev</a> with some tips about development
workflows, git, continuous integration and unit testing.</li>
<li>Yoga for Geeks during the lunch break.</li>
<li>Boyan Dzhumakov with topics about home automation and Internet of things, who
demonstrated his bed side lamp controlled via a light sensor and Arduino.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.boyanov.org/">Neven Boyanov</a> continuing on the hardware topics with
comparison of ATmel, Arduino and Raspberry Pi and showing more examples of
small programmable devices.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/attodorov">Angel Todorov</a> from Infragistics with a very
interesting talk about JavaScript instrumentation for performance analysis.
A very cool presentation and you should definitely check out his
<a href="https://github.com/attodorov/cheetah.js">cheetah.js</a> framework.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/KrasimirTsonev">Krasimir Tsonev</a> with
<a href="http://absurdjs.com/">AbsurdJS</a> - a JavaScript library with superpowers.
Teaser: Krasimir is also publishing a book caled
<a href="https://twitter.com/atodorov_/status/472723298053537792">Node.js Blueprints</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/krokodilerian">Vasil Kolev</a> with a talk about security
and web service design and how most of the web is doing it wrong :).</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately there is no video or audio recording available. If you find
some of the talks interesting and would like to get more info about it let
me know. I will ask the presenters to share their slides or give more details
where possible.</p>

<p>Don't worry if you've missed the Web Summit in Sofia. There will be another one
in the autumn, held at Veliko Tarnovo. For more info please subscribe to the
<a href="http://bulgariawebsummit.us6.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=44058a4036fe9516b0ea2004c&amp;id=e768a8c09a">newsletter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DigitalK Day 2 Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T20:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://atodorov.org/blog/2014/06/01/digitalk-day-2-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing to report on the last few events that took place in Sofia this week.</p>

<p>Day #2 of DigitalK started with the presentation of Piotr Jas of BlaBla Car.
What I really liked about it (picture TBA) was one particular graph depicting
the various types of travel (time before travel vs. cost of travel) and
visualizing different industries (e.g. air travel) or competitor companies.
The image clearly exhibited a blank space which is the exact market segment
where BlaBla Car have positioned themselves in.</p>

<p>A very practical and easy to use tool for entrepreneurs in my opinion.</p>

<p>From the rest of the keynotes I can outline two in particular:
Ivan Hernandez' <em>Disruptive Innovation and the future of Digital Transformation</em>
and <em>The future of Tech and Communities</em> by Tim Röhrich.</p>

<p>I liked them because both were very inspirational although not telling you
something which you haven't heard before. They were basically reinforcing
the spirit of the event.</p>

<p>In the small hall there was a workshop called
<em>How to turn a good idea into a successful start-up</em> led by Daniela Neumann,
which didn't turn out to be what I expected. She was talking about the early
cycle of idea/customer validation and I don't remember any particular example
being shown. Frankly most of the people have heard about this before (myself included)
and were quite bored. Not many of them stayed till the end.</p>

<p>The evening continued with the already traditional Silicon Drinkabout in Sofia
which hosted many of the conference attendees. I did a quick visit only
because I had to prepare myself for Bulgaria Web Summit on the next day!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
